<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Kim Hung Bui</title>
<link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>My Personal Website</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Farm animals and Vegetables</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-farm-animals-vegetables/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>It has been suggested that primary children should learn how to grow vegetables and keep animals.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Do the advantages of this outweigh the disadvantages?</strong></p>
<p>David Lang’s essay:</p>
<p>Some today have argued that it would be a sensible policy to teach children how to farm and raise animals at school. In my opinion, though this would require enormous resources, it would be beneficial in terms of both physical and intellectual development.</p>
<p>Those arguing against this proposal point out the resources needed. In order to implement such an ambitious programs, schools would firstly need land nearby where animals and crops be raised. This might be possible within a school’s pre-existing grounds, but there would still need to be significant investment in infrastructure. Schools would therefore have to reallocate a significant portion of their budget, potentially reducing the money for crucial facilities, staff, and teaching resources.</p>
<p>However, the advantages for the holistic development of children is overwhelming. Students today spend more time than ever before passively using technological devices. By spending more time outdoors learning about animals and crops, students will better understand their position within the natural food chain. Overtime, this may lead them to adopt environmentally friendlier, compassionate lifestyle choices such as becoming vegetarians or shopping locally rather than buying from large chains. Moreover, the work outdoors would necessarily involve physical exercise. Since obesity is a growing concern in most countries, this time outside could help to improve standards of physical fitness and establish healthy lifelong habits.</p>
<p>In conclusion, despite the money this reform would require, schools should adopt it when possible so as to achieve a more complete education for students. Governments should consider the long-term effects when deciding on such policies.</p>
<section id="chat-gpt" class="level1">
<h1>Chat gpt</h1>
<p>The proposal to incorporate agricultural and animal husbandry education into primary school curricula has garnered attention. In my view, while such initiatives offer certain benefits, the potential drawbacks, particularly concerning resource allocation and health risks, are more significant.</p>
<p>Advocates highlight that engaging children in growing vegetables and caring for animals can foster responsibility and a connection to nature. These activities may enhance students’ understanding of food sources and promote environmental stewardship. However, implementing such programs requires substantial resources. Schools would need to invest in appropriate land, infrastructure, and trained personnel to oversee these activities. This financial commitment could divert funds from essential academic subjects, potentially compromising the quality of core education.</p>
<p>Moreover, there are health and safety concerns associated with young children handling soil and animals. Exposure to allergens, zoonotic diseases, and physical injuries are risks that cannot be overlooked. Ensuring proper hygiene and safety measures would necessitate additional oversight and training, further straining school resources.</p>
<p>In conclusion, while teaching primary children to cultivate plants and care for animals has educational merits, the associated disadvantages, particularly in terms of resource allocation and health risks, outweigh the benefits. Schools should prioritize core academic subjects and consider integrating environmental education through less resource-intensive methods.</p>
<p>💡 Why David Lang’s Essay Feels Simple but Scores High</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Clear structure</li>
</ol>
<p>Introduction: Directly paraphrases the question + gives a clear opinion.</p>
<p>Body 1: Discusses the opposite view.</p>
<p>Body 2: Presents his own view (which he supports).</p>
<p>Conclusion: Restates the opinion and wraps up.</p>
<p>👉 Why it works: Examiners love clarity. They’re not grading you on how “fancy” your structure is — just that it’s logical and easy to follow.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Precise vocabulary, not fancy vocabulary</li>
</ol>
<p>He uses natural, topic-specific language, like:</p>
<p>“holistic development”</p>
<p>“environmentally friendlier”</p>
<p>“passively using technological devices”</p>
<p>👉 Why it works: Band 9 vocabulary is about being accurate and appropriate, not sounding like a thesaurus.</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Balanced ideas + developed examples</li>
</ol>
<p>He acknowledges the disadvantages (cost, resources) and then shows why advantages outweigh them (fitness, habits, awareness). He explains his points — not just states them.</p>
<p>👉 Why it works: IELTS cares about depth more than how many ideas you list. One strong idea with support = better than five weak ones.</p>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Grammar is natural and controlled</li>
</ol>
<p>He uses complex sentences when needed, not to show off.</p>
<p>👉 Example:</p>
<p>“Since obesity is a growing concern in most countries, this time outside could help…”</p>
<p>That’s complex, but clear. No over-complicated structures.</p>
<p>✅ How YOU Can Write Like David Lang</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Follow a clean structure</li>
</ol>
<p>Intro: Paraphrase + opinion</p>
<p>Body 1: Opposing view</p>
<p>Body 2: Your view (with examples)</p>
<p>Conclusion: Restate opinion</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Use precise, topic-relevant words</li>
</ol>
<p>Learn how to talk naturally about big topics (education, health, environment) with words that fit.</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Don’t list ideas — explain them</li>
</ol>
<p>Pick 1–2 strong points per paragraph and expand with why, how, and an example.</p>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Write like you’re explaining, not performing</li>
</ol>
<p>Pretend you’re talking to a smart friend, not an examiner. Make it natural and reasoned, not robotic or flowery.</p>
<p>✏️ Step 1: Write the Introduction</p>
<p>✅ What we need:</p>
<p>Paraphrase the question</p>
<p>Give a clear opinion</p>
<p>🧠 Example:</p>
<p>Some believe that it would be beneficial for young children to be taught farming skills at school. However, I believe that the drawbacks of such a policy outweigh the potential benefits.</p>
<p>🔍 Why this works:</p>
<p>It’s short.</p>
<p>Clear opinion.</p>
<p>No fancy words. Just focused.</p>
<p>Would you like to try writing your own version of the introduction before we move on?</p>
<p>Or should we go ahead to Body Paragraph 1?</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>advantage disadvantage</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-farm-animals-vegetables/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ielts task 1 - Household work</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-the-internet-books/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>In the past, knowledge was contained in books. Nowadays, knowledge is uploaded to the internet. Do the advantages of this outweigh the disadvantages?</strong></p>
<p>It is a fact of modern life that most information today is store online, rather than in physical books as it was in the past. In my opinion, this is a negative despite its obvious conveniences.</p>
<p>Supporters of this trend can point to the numerous ways knowledge kept online can be disseminated and used. Online information is almost universally accessible, narrowing socioeconomic differences in society and allowing for various conveniences. First of all, users can find relevant information on search engines from a wide range of sources including user-generated sites like Wikipedia to news outlets like The New York Times and academic journals as well. Once an individual locates the information they are looking for, it is also easier to search within that article, share it with others, have it wherever they go and store more than would be possible if it were a hard copy.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, storing information online encourages a dependence on computer technology that is harmful for the human mind. In the past, if a person wanted to research a given topic, they would have to check out a library book or talk with an expert. This process was much slower and open to the possibility of bias. However, it also meant that individuals were more conscientious and patiently learned from fuller, more nuanced sources. Nowadays, most people read short articles, hastily written to attract more clicks and generate advertising revenue. These tap into a fundamental human need to be constantly engaged and feeling pleasure. Over time, this has led to a generation addicted to devices, lacking the healthy habits engendered by careful research and study.</p>
<p>In conclusion, despite the handiness of online information, the impact on the human psyche makes this a negative trend on level. Individuals must themselves find ways to counter these potentially injurious effects.</p>
<p>Sample positive essay:</p>
<p>In the digital age, the migration of knowledge from physical books to online platforms has become a defining feature of global society. While critics argue that this shift undermines intellectual depth and fosters dependency, I firmly believe the advantages of accessible, dynamic, and. collaborative information far surpass its drawbacks.</p>
<p>Proponent of online knowledge store emphasize its unparalleled capacity to democratize information. Unlike traditional books, which are more constrained by physical availability and cost, digital platforms grant instantaneous access to vast repositories of data for anyone with an internet connection. Students in remote villages, for instance, can now access lectures from Ivy League universities, download academic journals, or participate in global forums - opportunities once reserved for the socioeconomically privileged. Moreover, search engines and algorithms allow users to pinpoint precise information within seconds, a task that previously required hours of library search. The integration of multimedia - such as video, interactive graphs, and hyperlinks- further enriches understanding, catering to diverse learning styles. Crucially, digital storage eliminates the environmental toll of paper production, reducing deforestation and carbon emissions linked to printing and distributing physical books.</p>
<p>Detractors, however, contend that the internet fosters misinformation, distraction, and superficial engagement. While valid, these concern are not insurmountable. It is true that unverified content proliferates online, yet this issue is counterbalanced by the rise of fact-checking tools, peer-reviewed databases, and digital literacy programs that empower users to discern credible sources. Similarly, although the constant influx of notifications and bite-sized content risks fragmenting attentions spans, individuals and educators can cultivate disciplined usage through structured learning frameworks and mindfulness practices. The digital divide-limited internet access in impoverished regions - remains a challenge, yet global initiatives to expand connectivity, such as satellite internet projects and affordable mobile data, are steadily bridging this gap.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the transition to online knowledge storage represents a net positive for humanity. Its capacity to democratize education, enhance efficiency, and promote sustainability far outweighs manageable risks like misinformation and distraction. To maximize benefits, society must prioritize digital literacy and equitable access, ensuring the internet remains a force for collective progress.</p>
<section id="speaking" class="level1">
<h1>Speaking</h1>
<ol type="1">
<li>How often do most people use the internet? Most people use the internet daily, if not constantly. Smartphones and Wi-Fi have made it ubiquitous whether for work, social media, or streaming. For instance, younger generations might spend 6+ hours online, while older adults might use it less frequently but still rely on it for news or banking.</li>
<li>Are there drawbacks to its overuse? Absolutely. Overuse can lead to addiction, reduced productivity, and mental issues like anxiety or loneliness. Physically, screen time strains eyes and disrupts sleep. Socially, it erodes face-to-face interactions - think of families ignoring each other to scroll through phones. Moderation is key.</li>
<li>What kind of information can people find online? Virtually <em>anything</em>. From academic research on Google Scholar to DIY tutorials on Youtube, and even niche forums discussing obscure hobbies. However, misinformation is rampant too - fake news, biased articles, or conspiracy theories. Critical thinking is essential to navigate this flood of data.</li>
<li>How was this changed the way people get their information? It’s deepen integration into daily life. Think smart homes controlled via apps, AI-driven healthcare consultations, or virtual reality workspaces. However, privacy concerns will grow, and the digital divide may widen unless access becomes universal. Education and jobs will increasingly depend on digital literacy.</li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>advantage disadvantage</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-the-internet-books/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IELTS Essay Writing by Hand</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-by-hand/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Question:</p>
<p><strong>Fewer and fewer people today write by hand using a pen or pencil.</strong></p>
<p><strong>What are the reasons for this?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Is this a positive or a negative development?</strong></p>
<p>David Lang’s essay:</p>
<p>Today, the act of writing by hand using a pen or pencil has become increasingly uncommon. This essay will delve into the reasons behind this trend and evaluate whether it is a positive or negative development for individuals and society as a whole.</p>
<p>One primary reason for the dwindling use of handwriting is the pervasive presence of technology. Inn an age dominated by computers, smartphones, and tables, individuals find it more convenient to type their thoughts and ideas rather than engaging in the laborious process of writing by hand. The speed and efficiency offered by digital devices have made it easier to edit, store, and share written content, rendering handwriting seemingly obsolete. To illustrate this, consider the rapid rise of communication platforms such as email, instant messaging apps, and social media. These platforms provide users with the ability to effortlessly send and receive messages, eliminating the need for handwritten letters or notes. This convenience extends to practical considerations for professionals in various fields, such as journalists, researchers, and writers, who often rely on digital platforms and word processors for their work. The ease of editing, revising, and sharing digital content outweighs the traditional pen-and-paper approach.</p>
<p>While the decline of handwriting may offer certain advantages, it also brings forth potential negative consequences. Handwriting is an essential skill that fosters cognitive development, improves memory retention, and allows for creative expression. The act of physically forming letters and words engages different areas of the brain, promoting better comprehension and critical thinking skills. Losing this skill may hinder individuals ability to think and express themselves effectively. Most importantly, the personal touch and emotional connection associated with handwritten letters or cards cannot be replicated by digital alternatives. Handwritten messages convey sincerity, thoughtfulness, and a see of intimacy. Losing the art of handwriting may irrevocably erode these meaningful human connections.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the decline of handwriting can be attributed to the prevalence of technology and practical considerations. While there are advantages to digital communication and typing, the negative implications for cognitive development and personal connections are more significant and must be mitigated by the relevant authorities.</p>
<p>Arguing that it is a positive development</p>
<p>In today’s digital age, fewer and fewer people write by hand and using a pen or pencil. This shift can be attributed to pared technological advancements and changing educational practices, and I firmly believe that it is a positive development. The move away from handwriting not only enhances efficiency and accessibility but also reflects progress towards modern communication methods.</p>
<p>The decline in handwriting is primarily driven by the ubiquity of digital devices and evolving communication needs. With the widespread availability of computers, smartphones, and tablets, individuals find it more convenient to type and send messages instantly. Educational institutions are increasingly incorporating technology into their curricula, emphasizing digital literacy over traditional penmanship. Moreover, the rise of social media and email as primary communication tools has diminished the need for handwritten correspondence. These factors have collectively contributed to a cultural shift where efficiency and speed in communication are prioritized over the art of handwriting.</p>
<p>Transitioning from handwriting to digital writing brings several significant benefits. Firstly, digital communication enhances productivity by enabling rapid information exchange and easy editing, which is especially beneficial in professional and academic settings. Additionally, typing reduces issues related to illegible handwriting, thereby minimizing misunderstandings. Digital platforms also offer vast storage and the ability to search through documents instantly, streamlining information management. Furthermore, this shift is environmentally friendly, as it reduces the consumption of paper and other stationery supplies. Overall, the adoption of digital writing foster greater accessibility and adaptability in our fast-pace, globalized world, contributing to more efficient and sustainable practices.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the decreasing reliance on handwriting in favor of digital communication is driven by technological advancements and evolving social practices. I contend that this development is positive, as it significantly boosts efficiency, clarity, and environmental sustainability while aligning with the demands of modern life. Embracing digital writing is not only a natural progression but also a vital step towards more effective and accessible communication in the 21st century.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>double question</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-by-hand/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IELTS Essay Having Children at an Older Age</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/having-children-at-older-age/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Question:</p>
<p><strong>Some people choose to have their first child at an older age.</strong> <strong>What are the reasons?</strong> <strong>Do the advantages outweigh the disadvantages?</strong></p>
<p>David Lang’s sample In recent years, an increasing number of individuals have opted to start their families later in life. This trend raises the question of why more people are choosing to have their first child at an older age and whether the benefits of doing so justify the drawbacks.</p>
<p>One of the primary reasons for delaying parenthood is the pursuit of career stability in a worrying economic climate. In today’s competitive job market, many individuals, particularly women, prefer to establish themselves professionally before starting a family. By focusing on their careers in their twenties and early thirties, they can achieve financial security and attain higher positions, which often translates to job satisfaction and greater resources for their future children. This growing trend is reflected in how mainstream society now places significant emphasis on personal development and achieving personal goals before embarking on parenthood. For that reason, many young adults prioritize their own personal and financial welfare, a situation that engenders an atmosphere less conductive to having children early in life.</p>
<p>There are legitimate disadvantages connected with having children later in life. One of the primary concerns is the potential health risks for both the mother and the child. Advanced maternal age is often associated with a higher risk of complications such as gestational diabetes, hypertension, and chromosomal abnormalities. However, despite these drawbacks, the advantages of having children later in life due to greater maturity overshadow the hypothetical drawbacks. The emotional maturity and life experience that older parents bring to child-rearing can result in a more stable and nurturing environment. Older parents are likely to be more financially secure and better prepared to provide for their children’s education and well-being. The ability to make well-considered decisions and the patience developed over time can contribute to a more thoughtful and deliberate approach to parenting.</p>
<p>In conclusion, while there are valid concerns regarding the health risks associated with having children later in life, the benefits, such as financial stability, emotional maturity, and better preparation for parenthood, outweigh these disadvantages. As societal norms and medical advancements continue to evolve, the rend of delaying parenthood is likely to remain prevalent, reflecting the changing priorities and values of modern individuals.</p>
<p>Sample, disadvantages over advantages.</p>
<p>An increasing number of individuals are choosing to have their first child at an older age. This trend is driven by factors such as career prioritization, financial security, and a desire for greater personal maturity. While some argue that the benefits of delayed parenthood - like improved financial stability and enhanced life experience - outweigh the disadvantages, I strongly disagree. The potential health risks, fertility issues, and other practical challenges mean that the disadvantages ultimately outweigh any advantages.</p>
<p>Modern society has shifted priorities, and many couples now postpone parenthood for several reasons. Primarily, individuals strive to establish their careers and achieve financial stability before starting a family. This approach allows prospective parents to create a secure environment for their child, free from economic uncertainty. Furthermore, many believe that greater life experience and emotional maturity can lead to more thoughtful parenting decisions. As a result, the decision to delay having a first child is often seen as a strategic move to optimize one’s personal and professional circumstances.</p>
<p>Despite these reasons, the drawbacks of having a first child at an older age are significant. Health concerns are paramount; older mothers face increased risks of pregnancy complications, such as gestational diabetes and hypertension, which can jeopardize both maternal and infant health. Additionally, advancing age is closely linked to decreased fertility, often necessitating expensive and emotionally draining fertility treatments. Beyond health, older parents might experience reduced physical stamina, which is crucial for the demanding nature of childcare, and a larger generational gap that can affect the parent-child relationship. These challenges make the prospect of delayed parenthood less attractive, as the risks and long-term implications overshadow the benefits of waiting.</p>
<p>In conclusion, although delaying parenthood may provide some advantages in terms of financial and emotional preparedness, the significant health risks, fertility challenges, and practical issues associated with having a first child later in life outweigh these benefit. Therefore, i contend that the disadvantages of postponing parenthood ultimately make it a less favorable option compared to earlier family planning.</p>
<p>Sample, advantages over disadvantages.</p>
<p>In recent years, an increasing number of individuals have chosen to have their first child at an older age. This trend is largely influenced by factors such as the pursuit of career goals, the desire for financial stability, and the accumulation of life experience before entering parenthood. I firmly believe that these advantages not only lead to more secure and thoughtful family planning but also contribute to improved parenting outcomes, ultimately outweighing the potential disadvantages.</p>
<p>Modern societal shifts have prompted many prospective parents to postpone starting a family. Primarily, individuals are keen to establish a stable career and secure a robust financial foundation before welcoming a child. This approach allows them to create a nurturing environment where the child’s needs are met without the stress of <strong>economic uncertainty</strong>. Furthermore, waiting until later in life often results in enhanced emotional maturity and life experience, enabling parents to make more considered decisions and effectively manage the challenges of raising a child. These reasons underscore why many see value in delaying parenthood as a strategic, long-term investment in both personal and familial well-being.</p>
<p>The advantages of choosing to have a child at an older age are manifold. With a well-established career and financial security, older parents are better equipped to provide for their child’s educational and extracurricular needs, contributing to the child’s overall development. In addition, greater maturity and life experience often translate into more patient, empathetic, and balanced parenting. Such parents typically possess enhanced problem-solving skills and resilience, which can be invaluable when navigating the inevitable challenges of childcare. Moreover, studies have shown that older parents tend to invest more time and resources in their children’s upbringing, resulting in a more stable and nurturing home environment. Collectively, these advantages not only promote healthier family dynamics but also pave the way for the child’s long-term success and well-being.</p>
<p>In conclusion, while there are inherent challenges associated with delayed parenthood, the benefits- ranging from financial stability and career establishment to increased emotional maturity and effective parenting- clearly outweigh the drawbacks. By choosing to have a child at an older age, many individuals are better prepared to offer a secure, supportive, and enriching environment for their children, ultimately leading to more positive outcomes for families.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>double question</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/having-children-at-older-age/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to Structure a ‘Two Question’ Essay</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/two-question-essay/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Let’s look at an example of this kind of question:</p>
<pre><code>*Nowadays governments are investing more in public transport such as buses and trains rather than in building new roads.*
*What are the reasons for this?*
*Is this a positive or negative development?*</code></pre>
<section id="clear-position" class="level1">
<h1>Clear position</h1>
<p>For this kind of task we need to discuss both questions. In the first question, we are given a situation and asked to explain why. The second question requires a clear opinion so <strong>we must choose a side.</strong> This is very important for our task response score. If we don’t choose a side and support that ‘position’ clearly, we will lose marks for our task response. We will get a maximum of 5 for task achievement if we do not choose a side.</p>
<p>It’s not important which side we choose as long as we choose one. Here are the options for the second questions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Agree</strong>: We think it’s a positive development that governments are spending more money on public transport. We support this opinion.</li>
<li><strong>Disagree:</strong> We think it’s a negative development that governments are spending more money on public transport. We support this opinion.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="clear-essay-structure" class="level1">
<h1>Clear essay structure</h1>
<p>David Lang recommend that we should give our opinion in the introduction as well as the conclusion (for all IELTS Task 2 questions). It’s OK to write a very general introduction and leave our opinion to the end. But it’s not as clear and we might run out of time before we’ve hot to our conclusion, so overall it’s a risky strategy. If we don’t choose a side and support that ‘position’ clearly, we will lose marks for our task response.</p>
<p>Therefore, him suggested essay structure is four paragraphs. The opinion is presented in the introduction and re-stated in the conclusion. Ideally each body paragraph in the introduction and re-stated in the conclusion.</p>
</section>
<section id="possible-essay-structures" class="level1">
<h1>Possible Essay structures</h1>
<p><strong>1. Agree</strong> - we feel it’s a positive development that governments are spending more money on public transport.</p>
<p>We need at least <strong>one good reason</strong> why it’s happening and <strong>one good reason</strong> why it’s a positive development.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 21%">
<col style="width: 78%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Paragraph 1<br><br> (intro)</td>
<td>Paraphrase both questions and state your overall opinion (you feel it’s a positive development)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Paragraph 2<br><br> (body 1)</td>
<td>Explain and support your reason why governments are spending more money on public transport.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Paragraph 3<br><br> (body 2)</td>
<td>Explain and support your reason why this is a positive development.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Paragraph 4 (conclusion)</td>
<td>Re-state your overall opinion (you feel it’s a positive development) and &nbsp;summarise your main reasons.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>2. Disagree:</strong> - we feel it’s a negative development that governments are spending more money on public transport.</p>
<p>We need at least <strong>one good reason</strong> why it’s happening and <strong>one good reason</strong> why it’s a negative development. Only the parts highlighted below are different from the first essay</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 79%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>#### Paragraph 1 (intro)</td>
<td>#### Paraphrase both questions and state your overall opinion<br><br> <strong>(you feel it’s a negative development)</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>#### Paragraph 2 (body 1)</td>
<td>#### Explain and support your reason why governments are spending more money on public transport.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>#### <strong>Paragraph 3 (body 2)</strong></td>
<td>#### <strong>Explain and support your reason why this is a negative development.</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>#### Paragraph 4 (conclusion)</td>
<td>#### Re-state your overall opinion <strong>(you feel it’s a negative development)</strong> and &nbsp;summarise your main reasons.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>double question</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/two-question-essay/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IELTS Essay Financial Matters</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/financial-matters/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Question:</p>
<p><strong>In numerous nations, there is a growing trend for individuals to frequently discuss financial matters, such as their earnings or expenditure, in everyday conversation</strong>. <strong>What are the reasons behind this phenomenon?</strong> <strong>Is it advantageous or detrimental?</strong></p>
<hr>
<p>There is an increasing tendency for individuals in the modern world to openly discuss their finances in daily conversation. In my opinion, this is a result of a general lack of self-awareness and is decidedly negative given the opportunity cost it engenders.</p>
<p>The primary reason many people are prone to talk their financial dealings originates in society generally. In the past, a sense of modesty or concern for decorum might have compelled reticence. Today, some of the most widely discussed topics in the media, online, in film, and in literature concern cryptocurrencies, the real estate market, stock equities, the price of gold, and other investments. A person discussing these matters is likely only interested in subtle boasting if venting frustrations without awareness of the emotions or engagement of their interlocutor. The result over time has been that many people have developed a shameless habit.</p>
<p>In my view, discussion finances often precludes a number of more worthwhile topics of conversation. Since the majority of useful financial research can be conducted online or done in professional settings, there are more pressing areas that should be discussed in daily life. For example, two friends having a conversation at a cafe would derive greater value from telling stories, joking with one another, or delving into a more serious topic related to politics, the arts, or psychology. Such discussions are likely to develop their understanding of the world and their emotional intelligence. Discussion of money, on the other hand, wastes valuable time and energy for little concrete outcome.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the inclination to speak of one’s personal finances stems from a fundamentally modern self-indulgence and often prevents the discussion of more enjoyable or meaningful topics. Naturally, these generalizations do not apply to all individuals.</p>
<hr>
<p>ChatGPT’s essay:</p>
<p>In numerous nations, a growing trend has emerged where people openly discuss financial matters, including their earnings and expenditures, in everyday conversations. This phenomenon can be attributed to a range of social and economic factors, and i firmly believe that it is advantageous. Open dialogue about personal finances not only foster financial literacy but also encourages better money management and transparency within communities.</p>
<p>One primary reason for this trend is the rapid spread of financial education and the influence of digital media. With the advent of social media platforms and financial blogs, individuals have unprecedented access to information about budgeting, investing, and saving. This exposure has led many to feel more confident in discussing their financial situations, as they seek advice and validation from peers. Additionally, economic uncertainty in many regions has prompted individuals to share personal financial experiences as a way of coping and learning from one another. For instance, during periods of economic downturn, people often exchange tips on reducing expenses or finding alternative income sources. This collective sharing not only helps individuals navigate challenging time but also creates a support network where practical financial strategies are exchanged openly.</p>
<p>The open discussion of financial matters carries significant benefits for both individuals and society at large. Firstly, it promotes financial literacy by normalizing conversations about money, which can demystify complex financial topic and empower people to make informed decisions. As people become more knowledgeable about financial planning and investment strategies, they are better equipped to secure their futures and contribute to economic growth. Secondly, this trend encourages transparency and accountability, reducing the stigma around discussing personal finances. For example, when individuals talk about budgeting and debt management, it can inspire others to examine their own spending habits, ultimately leading to a more financially responsible community. By fostering an environment where financial struggles and successes are shared openly, society as a whole benefits from improved financial stability and reduced inequality.</p>
<p>In conclusion, the increasing tendency for individuals to discuss financial matters in everyday conversation is driven by greater access to information and a need for mutual support during uncertain economic times. I contend that this development is advantageous, as it enhances financial literacy, transparency, and responsible money management. Ultimately, such open dialogue can empower communities to achieve greater financial stability and economic well-being.</p>
<section id="grammar-structures" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="grammar-structures">Grammar structures</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Complex Sentence Structures</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Use of subordinate clauses to add detail. <em>Example:</em> “With the advent of social media platforms and financial blog, individuals have unprecedented access to information about budgeting, investing, and saving.”</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Cause and Effect Constructions</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Phrases such as “can be attributed to” and “leads to” explain reasons and consequences. <em>Example:</em> “This phenomenon can be attributed to a range of social and economic factors.”</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Conditional and Hypothetical Phrasing:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Implicit conditionals that suggest potential outcomes or benefits. Example: “when individuals talk about budgeting and debt management, it can inspire others to examine their own spending habits.”</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Comparative Structure:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using comparisons to show differences in outcomes. Example: “For instance, during periods of economic downturn, people often exchange tips on reducing expenses or finding alternative income sources.”</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Use of Passive Voice:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Passive constructions to emphasize processes or outcomes rather than actors.<br>
<em>Example:</em> “This phenomenon can be attributed to a range of social and economic factors.”</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Linking Devices and Transitional Phrases:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Words and phrases such as “Firstly,” “Secondly,” “In conclusion,” and “For example” to organize ideas and guide the reader.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="lexical-items" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lexical-items">Lexical Items</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Advanced Vocabulary:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Words such as “unprecedented,” “demystify,” “transparency,” “accountability,” and “empower” elevate the formality and clarity of the argument.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Financial Terminology:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Specific terms related to finance like “budgeting,” “investing,” “saving,” “financial literacy,” “debt management,” and “spending habits.”</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Descriptive Adjectives:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Terms that add detail and nuance, for example “open dialogue,” “collective sharing,” “rigorous, random testing,” and “financially responsible.”</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Collocations and Fixed Phrases:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Common phrases that support the essay’s theme such as “financial matters,” “economic uncertainty,” “personal financial experiences,” and “mutual support.”</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Transitional Vocabulary:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Words that link ideas logically like “furthermore,” “additionally,” and “ultimately” ensure smooth progression throughout the essay.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Opinion and Evaluation Language:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Phrases that express clear stance such as “I firmly believe,” “it is essential,” “I contend that,” and “I contend that this development is advantageous.”</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>double question</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/financial-matters/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Ielts task 1 - Household work</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/household-work/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>The bar chart below shows the average duration of household women did (unemployed, part-time employed and full-time) when compared to men who had full-time work in the UK between 1985 and 2005.</em></p>
<p><em>Summarise the information by selecting and reporting the main features, and make comparisons where relevant.</em></p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/household-work/Pasted image 20250328022514.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The bar chart details hours of housework completed in the UK from 1985 to 2005 by fully employed males and females with various states of employment. Looking from an overall perspective, it is readily apparent that time spent on housework rose for all groups with the exception of unemployed women, which was stable overall. However, the latter category undertook by far the most housework, while men with full-time jobs did comparatively little.</p>
<p>Unemployed women led throughout the period in terms of hours, at a peak of 7 hours in 1985 and 2005 and a slight dip to 6.5 hours in between. In contrast, men with full-time work were unchanged at just 1 hour in 1985 and 1995, though there was a slight rise to 1.5 hours in 2005.</p>
<p>Women with part-time employment were slightly lower than their unemployed counterparts throughout the period, beginning at 5.3 hours in 1985, before declining to 5 hours over the next 5 years, and then finishing the period with a surge to 6 hours. The figures for women with full-time employment resembled those of men, though they were marginally higher at 2, 1.5, and 2.8 hours in 1985, 1995, and 2005, respectively.</p>
<section id="speaking" class="level1">
<h1>Speaking</h1>
<section id="tidiness" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tidiness"><strong>Tidiness</strong></h4>
<ol type="1">
<li>Are you a tidy person? Yes, I would say I’m quite a tidy person. I like to keep my things organized, whether it’s my room, desk, or digital files. I find that being tidy helps me concentrate better and reduces stress.</li>
<li>Are you more tidy at home or at school? I’m generally tidy in both places, but I’d say I’m more careful about tidiness at school or work. I think that’s because I want to create a good impression and maintain a productive environment. At home, I might be a bit more relaxed, especially when I’m tired.</li>
<li>Were you tidy as a child? Not really! When I was a child, I was pretty messy. My toys and clothes were usually all over the place, and my parents had to remind me constantly to clean up. It wasn’t until I got older that I started appreciating the value of being organized.</li>
<li>Are people in your country very tidy? It depends on the individual, but in general, I think people in my country value cleanliness and order, especially in public spaces. There’s a strong emphasis on hygiene and keeping things neat, though of course, there are exceptions.</li>
</ol>
<p>not tidy:</p>
<ul>
<li>To be honest, I’m not the tidiest person. I try to keep things in order, but I often get caught up in other tasks and end up leaving a bit of a mess behind. It’s not that I enjoy clutter - I just tend to prioritize other things over cleaning. That said, I do try to do a proper tidy-up when it gets out of hand.</li>
<li>I’m definitely less tidy at home. When I’m at school or work, I feel a bit more pressure to maintain a neat space, especially if I’m sharing it with others. But at home, I tend to [[let things slide]] - especially if I’m busy or tired. My room isn’t chaotic, but it’s far from spotless.</li>
<li>Not at all. I was one of those kids who always had toys and books scattered everywhere. My parents used to joke that a tornado had hit my room. Tidiness just wasn’t something I [[paid attention to]] - I was more interested in playing or creating things than cleaning up after myself.</li>
<li>I think it varies a lot. Some people are incredibly meticulous and keep everything spotless, while others are more laid-back like me. I wouldn’t say tidiness is a national trait - it really depends on the individuals and sometimes on how they were raised.</li>
</ul>
<p>Tidiness: 1. Are you a tidy person ? Yes, I would definitely consider myself a tidy person. I find that having a clean and organized environment helps my think more clearly and stay focused. Tidiness isn’t just about appearance for me - it’s more about creating a calm and efficient space where I can function at my best. 2. Are you more tidy at home or at school? I’d say I’m equally tidy in both settings, but in slightly different ways. At home, I like everything to be in its space - I clean regularly and keep my space minimalist. At school or work, I might not be as meticulous with deep cleaning, but I still keep my desk organized and clutter-free. It helps me stay productive and avoid distractions. 3. Were you tidy as a child? Yes, even as a child I had a habit of keeping things neat. I used to arrange my books by color and make sure my toys were stored properly after playing. It wasn’t something my parents had to enforce - I think I just naturally liked having order around me. That tendency has definitely [[carried over]] into adulthood. 4. Are people in your country very tidy? I believe it depends on the person, but overall, people in my country do value cleanliness and order, especially in shared or public spaces. There’s a strong cultural emphasis on personal hygiene and maintaining a tidy home, particularly when guest are visiting. However, standards or tidiness can vary widely from one household to another.</p>
</section>
<section id="part-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="part-3">Part 3</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Do you think tidiness is important in the workplace? Absolutely. A tidy workplace not only creates a more professional image but also boosts efficiency. When things are organized, it’s easier to find what you need, which saves time and reduce stress. Moreover, a clean environment can promote better focus and even improve team morale.</li>
<li>Why do some people struggle to stay tidy? There could be a few reasons. Some people simply lead very busy lives and don’t prioritize tidiness, while others may not have developed habits of organization from a young age. In some cases, people might not even notice the mess around them - they’ve grown accustomed to it. For a few, it could also be tied to mental health challenges, like anxiety or ADHD, which can effect one’s ability to maintain order.</li>
<li>How can parents teach children to be tidy? The most effective way is by setting a good example. If children see their parents consistently keeping things organized, they’re more likely to adopt those habits themselves. It also helps to make tidying part of a daily routine and turn it into something fun or rewarding - for instance, though games or praise. Teaching them to take pride in their space can go a long way.</li>
<li>Do you think technology helps people stay more organized and tidy? Definitely. There are so many apps and digital tools now that can help people manages their time, declutter digitally, and keep track of tasks or schedules. Even simple things like calendar reminder or to-do list apps can encourage tidier habits. That said, technology can also contribute to digital clutter if not used mindfully.</li>
<li>Is there a difference in tidiness between younger and older generations? In some ways, yes. Older generations often place a high value on physical tidiness, perhaps because they grew up in a time when everything had to be done manually. Younger people, on the other hand, might prioritize digital organization - like keeping their phones or laptops neatly arranged. However, i think personal habits play a bigger role than age.</li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>time</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/household-work/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Performance-Enhancing Drugs in Sports</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/performance-enhancing-drug/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>In recent years, there has been a rise in the use of performance-enhancing substances in sports.</em> <em>What are the consequences of doping for athletes?</em> <em>What measures should be taken to combat this issue?</em></p>
<p>There has been a considerable rise in detections for performance-enhancing substances in athletic competitions recently. In my opinion, the most likely consequences for athletes concern their careers and this infraction is best tackled through more sophisticated screening tests.</p>
<p>In the majority of cases, athletes risk lasting career repercussions when caught doping. The first and most obvious consequences are financial. An athlete who tests positive for a banned substance will certainly be banned for a defined amount of time, potentially permanently in serious cases, and will forfeit salary and prize money over this period. Beyond raw salary, most athletes receive endorsements and a worsening public image will undoubtedly damage those business relationships as well. Relatedly, an athlete’s legacy is also at stake. A well-known example of this would be the baseball player Barry Bonds who not only lost the final years of an illustrious career to suspensions but has also not been inducted into the Baseball Hall of Fame due to his past transgressions and numerous failed tests.</p>
<p>In order to combat the pervasiveness of performance-enhancing drugs, sporting authorities must invest in modernized testing procedures. The most complex testing is currently utilized in the Olympics, however there are flaws in this system as it is often compromised by corruption and the equally sophisticated doping methods of certain nations. A more pertinent case of study would be in sports such as boxing and MMA where testing can literally mean the difference between life and death. In boxing, athletes often agree to their own testing procedures contractually. This method is inferior to vesting power in an authority, such as the UFC, that can ensure tests are modern and fairly conducted. Most UFC athletes are tested at random points throughout the year as well as prior to and immediately after bouts. Applying such a policy across various sports would not only catch the bast majority of infractions but also, more importantly, deter abuse even beginning.</p>
<p>In conclusion, athletes risk reputational and financial damage by doping and this can be prevented as testing becomes more comprehensive and potent. These measures are necessary to safeguard the integrity of sporting competitions around the world.</p>
<hr>
<p>In recent years, the use of performance-enhancing drugs in sports has increased, posing significant challenges to fair competition. Doping not only harm an athlete’s career and finances but also damages the trust between fans, sponsors, and sporting institutions. I firmly believe that to protect the integrity of sports, it is essential to implement more advanced and transparent testing procedures.</p>
<p>Athletes who resort to doping face serious long-term consequences that extend beyond temporary suspensions. When an athletes tests positive for banned substances, they risk losing salaries, prize money, and lucrative endorsements. For example, a renowned baseball player might be suspended, causing them to forfeit not only their immediate earnings but also potential future opportunities, such as Hall of Fame induction. This example clearly shows that doping can irreversibly tarnish an athlete’s legacy and career, leading to both financial ruin and a permanent stain on their reputation.</p>
<p>To effectively counter the issue of doping, sports authorities must adopt modern, comprehensive testing protocols. While major competitions like the Olympics employ advanced testing, the current is sometimes undermined by corruption and the ever-evolving sophistication of doping techniques. In sports like boxing and mixed martial arts, for instance, some athletes are subjected to self-regulated tests and lack objectivity. In contrast, organizations such as the UFC implement rigorous, random testing both before and after events, ensuring a fairer system. Adopting these strict measures across all sports would not only detect infractions more reliably but also serve as a strong deterrent against doping. By ensuring that testing is both modern and impartial, the integrity of competitive sports can be maintained, safeguarding athletes’ careers and reputation of the sport.</p>
<p>In conclusion, doping leads to severe financial and reputational damage for athletes while undermining the fairness of sports competitions. Only through the implementation of advanced, transparent testing procedures can we hope to deter doping and preserve the true spirit of sportsmanship for future generations.</p>
<section id="vocabulary" class="level1">
<h1>Vocabulary</h1>
<p><strong><em>For extra practice, write an antonym (opposite word) on a piece of paper to help you remember the new vocabulary:</em></strong> 1. There has been a considerable rise in detections - There has been a significant increase in identifications 2. performance-enhancing substances - performance-boosting substances 3. athletic competitions - sporting events 4. most likely consequences for - probable outcomes for</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>double question</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/performance-enhancing-drug/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Health Services</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-health-services/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Health services are a basic necessity. However, private companies have made them quite costly for ordinary individuals</em> <em>Do the advantages of private health care outweigh its disadvantage</em></p>
<section id="analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis">Analysis</h2>
<p>Advantages of Private Health Care: - Efficiency and shorter Waiting Times: Private hospitals offer quicker services compare to public hospitals, where long waiting lists are common. - Better facilities and advanced technology: Many private health institution provide cutting-edge medical technology, specialized treatments, and higher standards of care. - Greater Patient Choice: Individuals can select their preferred doctors, hospitals, and treatment plans, leading to more personalized care. Disadvantages of Private Health Care: - High costs and Limited Accessibility: Private health care is expensive, making it inaccessible for low-income individuals who cannot afford quality treatment. - Profit-driven System: The focus on profit can sometimes lead to unnecessary medical procedures, overcharging, or prioritizing financial gain over patient well-being. - Health inequality: A reliance on private health care can widen the gap between the rich and the poor, as only those who can afford it receive top-tier medical services. ## Sample essay Health care is an essential service, yet private medical facilities often make it unaffordable for many individuals. While private health care offers significant advantages such as efficiency, superior technology, and greater patient choice, it also has considerable drawbacks, particularly its high costs and contribution to social inequality. In my view, although private health care enhances medical standards, its disadvantages outweigh its benefits due to its exclusive and financial burden on ordinary citizens.</p>
<p>One of the key benefits of private health care is it efficiency. Unlike public hospitals, which often suffer from overcrowding and long waiting times, private institutions provide quicker access to medical attention. This is particularly crucial for emergency treatments or specialized procedures that require immediate intervention. Additionally, private hospitals invest heavily in advanced medical technology and modern infrastructure, ensuring high-quality treatment and specialized care. For instance, many private institutions offer robotic surgeries and personalized cancer treatments, which are not always available in public hospitals. Furthermore, private health care allows patients to choose their doctors and treatment plans, leading to a more personalized and comfortable experience.</p>
<p>However, the drawbacks of private health care are significant. The most pressing concern is its exorbitant cost, making it unaffordable for a large portion of the population. Many life-saving procedures and medications are out of reach for lower-income individuals, forcing them to rely on overstretched public health systems. Furthermore, because private hospitals overate on a profit-driven model, there is a risk of unnecessary procedures being performed to maximize revenue, sometimes at the expensive of patient welfare. Lastly, the presence of an expensive private health care sector creates a divide between the wealthy and the poor, exacerbating health inequalities. In countries without strong public health care, the underprivileged often suffer from preventable diseases simply due to financial constraints.</p>
<p>In conclusion, while private health care provides high-quality services and efficiency, its high costs and potential for exploitation make it a less viable option for the general population. A well-functioning public health system remains crucial to ensuring that medical care is accessible to all, regardless of financial status. Governments should regulate private health care costs and prioritize investment in public health services to balance quality with accessibility.</p>
</section>
<section id="structure" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="structure">Structure</h2>
<p><strong>1.</strong> Health care is an essential service, yet private medical facilities often make it unaffordable for many individuals. <strong>2.</strong> While private health care offers significant advantages such as efficiency, superior technology, and greater patient choice, it also has considerable drawbacks, particularly its high costs and contribution to social inequality. <strong>3.</strong> In my view, although private health care enhances medical standards, its disadvantages outweigh its benefits due to its exclusive and financial burden on ordinary citizens. 1.<strong><em>Paraphrase the question.</em></strong> 2.<strong>Mention both advantages and disadvantages.</strong><em> 3.</em><strong>Clearly state your opinion.</strong>* <strong>1</strong>. One of the key benefits of private health care is its efficiency, as it ensures faster access to treatment, advanced medical technology, and personalized care. <strong>2.</strong> Unlike public hospitals, which often suffer from overcrowding and long waiting times, private institutions provide quicker access to medical attention. <strong>3.</strong> This is particularly crucial for emergency treatments or specialized procedures that require immediate intervention. Additionally, private hospitals invest heavily in advanced medical technology and modern infrastructure, ensuring high-quality treatment and specialized care. <strong>4.</strong> For instance, many private institutions offer robotic surgeries and personalized cancer treatments, which are not always available in public hospitals. <strong>5.</strong> Furthermore, private health care allows patients to choose their doctors and treatment plans, leading to a more personalized and comfortable experience. 1.Write a topic sentence with a clear main idea at the end. 2.Explain our main idea 3.Develop it fully 4.Develop it with specific or hypothetical examples 5.Better to have more detail</p>
<p><strong>1.</strong> However, the drawbacks of private health care are significant. <strong>2.</strong> The most pressing concern is its exorbitant cost, making it unaffordable for a large portion of the population. <strong>3.</strong> Many life-saving procedures and medications are out of reach for lower-income individuals, forcing them to rely on overstretched public health systems. <strong>4.</strong> Furthermore, because private hospitals overate on a profit-driven model, there is a risk of unnecessary procedures being performed to maximize revenue, sometimes at the expensive of patient welfare. Lastly, the presence of an expensive private health care sector creates a divide between the wealthy and the poor, exacerbating health inequalities. <strong>5.</strong> In countries without strong public health care, the underprivileged often suffer from preventable diseases simply due to financial constraints.</p>
<p>1.Write a new topic sentence with a new main idea at the end 2.Explain our new main idea. 3.Include specific details and examples. 4.Add as much information as we can and make sure it links logically. 5.This country is a bit long - aim for about 275 words.</p>
<p><strong>1.</strong> In conclusion, while private health care provides high-quality services and efficiency, its high costs and potential for exploitation make it a less viable option for the general population. 2. A well-functioning public health system remains crucial to ensuring that medical care is accessible to all, regardless of financial status. Governments should regulate private health care costs and prioritize investment in public health services to balance quality with accessibility.</p>
<p>1.Summaries our main idea. 2.Include a final thought.</p>
</section>
<section id="david-langs-essay" class="level1">
<h1>David Lang’s essay</h1>
<p>Today, the cost of basic health services due to privatization has risen dramatically. In my opinion, although this can lead to greater innovation in the medical field, it is a negative burden overall for the average person.</p>
<p>Those who argue in favor of private medical care point out the benefits for medical knowledge generally. There is significant evidence in a wide range of industries as to the efficacy of privatization in driving innovation. The medical field i no different as hospitals in countries such as United States compete to develop innovative therapies and procedures that can enhance their reputations and generate higher revenues. These efforts in turn encourage the hiring of the brightest medical minds in the world. Without such competition, it is unlikely that many current advances in medical technology would exist at all.</p>
<p>However, these advances do little do alleviate the dramatic financial repercussions for ordinary citizens. In the United States, a person without medical insurance is likely to owe at least thousands for relatively simple procedure. Contrast this approach with many western European nations that function on a socialized approach to medicine. In these countries, a person is comforted by the knowledge that a trip to the hospital or consultation with a doctor will be largely paid for by the government. The result of this more equal system is that there is little disparity in the care given to the wealthy and less affluent segments of population.</p>
<p>In conclusion, despite the value of stimulating competition among medical institutions, there would be greater impact in a scheme wherein the individual could receive medical care without incurring excessive expenses. In many countries, this is already the situation.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>advantages disadvantage</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-health-services/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Grammar Present time</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/present-time/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="present-simple" class="level1">

<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 30%">
<col style="width: 69%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Use to</th>
<th>Example</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>General truths</td>
<td><em>The left-hand side of the brain <strong>controls</strong> the right-hand side of the body.</em></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Current habits</td>
<td><em>I <strong>don’t</strong> always go to lectures that are early in the morning.</em></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Permanent</strong> situations and states</td>
<td>Angie <strong>teaches</strong> French at a local adult education centre.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>grammar</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/present-time/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IELTS Writing Task 2 - Topic Sentences – The Fastest Way to Improve your Score</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-topic-sentence/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="what-are-topic-sentence" class="level1">
<h1>What are topic sentence ?</h1>
<p>The standard essay structure for a IELTS Task 2 essay is four paragraphs - an introduction, two body paragraphs and a conclusion.</p>
<p>The topic sentence is the first sentence of each body paragraph. It tells the examiner the main idea of the paragraph so it functions like a mini introduction.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-are-topic-sentences-important" class="level1">
<h1>Why are Topic Sentences Important?</h1>
<p>Good topic sentences help to make our paragraphs clear and easy to read.</p>
<p>As we can see from the table below, clear paragraphs really help our coherence and cohesion score.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 50%">
<col style="width: 43%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Band Score</strong></td>
<td><strong>Official IELTS description</strong><br><br> <strong>(Coherence and Cohesion)</strong></td>
<td><strong>What it means.</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>7+</td>
<td>“logically organises information and ideas…presents a clear central topic within each paragraph.”</td>
<td>Body paragraphs have one main idea.<br><br> Topic sentences are clear.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>6</td>
<td>“arranges information and ideas coherently…uses paragraphing, but not always logically.”</td>
<td>Body paragraphs don’t always have one main idea.<br><br> Topic sentences are not always clear.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>5</td>
<td>“presents information with some organisation…may not write in paragraphs, or paragraphing may be inadequate.”</td>
<td>Paragraphs are not used well.<br><br> Topic sentences are not clear.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="how-to-write-a-good-topic-sentence" class="level1">
<h1>How to Write a Good Topic Sentence ?</h1>
<p>A good topic sentence should be clear and simple.</p>
<p>A basic topic sentence has two parts: 1. The topic. 2. The reason / main idea. ![[18920776_935567866585887_4103732896360495495_o-768x575.jpg]]</p>
<p><strong>Example Question</strong></p>
<pre><code>Global warming/Climate change are pressing problems that every country and the world will have to deal with in the future.
What are the causes of global warming ?
What are some possible solutions ?</code></pre>
<p><strong>Body paragraph 1 (the main cause of global warming)</strong> Topic: the main cause of global warming Reason/ main idea: mass consumption of fossil fuels</p>
<p>So the topic sentence is: The main cause of climate change is the mass consumption of fossil fuels.</p>
<p><strong>Body paragraph 2 (a possible solution)</strong></p>
<p>Topic: one possible solution for dealing with global warming Reason/main idea: higher taxes on automobiles</p>
<p>The topic sentence is: One possible solution for dealing with climate change could be higher taxes on automobiles.</p>
</section>
<section id="topic-sentence-will-help-us-to-stay-married-to-one-main-idea." class="level1">
<h1>Topic sentence will help us to stay married to one main idea.</h1>
<p>As we saw in the table above, we should “present a clear central topic within each paragraph”. This means each body paragraph should be focused on just one main idea.</p>
<p>Therefore planning for our topic sentences helps us to decide what is the main idea for that paragraph.</p>
<p>After that we should ONLY think of support for that idea. We are married to that main idea. We can’t cheat on it with another main idea.</p>
<p>So for the following topic sentence, we should only discuss the mass consumption of fuels.</p>
<pre><code>The main cause of climate change is the mass consumption of fossil fuels.</code></pre>
<p>Some students spend nearly the whole paragraph discussing one main idea. But then near the end, they seem to panic or get overexcited, and suddenly add a second unrelated idea e.g.&nbsp;deforestation or methane emissions from animals. This is a very common mistake but as the table above showed this will lower our coherence and cohesion score. Remember each paragraph can only have “one central topic”. As part of our planning stage in the task 2 writing exam, we should write down our topic sentences. This will make it easier when we start writing our essay to keep our supporting ideas clear, and focused on our main idea. If we accidentally include a second main idea at the end - cross it out. Stay focused.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-to-practice-topic-sentences" class="level1">
<h1>How to Practice Topic Sentences</h1>
<section id="analyze-sample-essays" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analyze-sample-essays">Analyze sample essays</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Look at some task 2 sample essays.</li>
<li>Highlight the topic sentence(s) - what is the topic? What is the main idea?</li>
<li>Read the body paragraph(s) - do all the supporting ideas relate to that idea?</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="practice-writing-topic-sentences-for-sample-essays" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice-writing-topic-sentences-for-sample-essays">Practice writing topic sentences for sample essays</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Look at some task 2 sample essay.</li>
<li>Cover up the first sentence of the body paragraph(s).</li>
<li>Read the body again - what is the topic and main idea ?</li>
<li>Write a topic sentence for that paragraph, then compare it with the original one. ## Analyze our own writing</li>
<li>Look back through our old task 2 essays.</li>
<li>Are the topic sentences good? If not, write new ones. ## Practice writing topic sentences for new question</li>
<li>Look at some sample task 2 question (there is one below)</li>
<li>Analyze the question and brainstorm main ideas.</li>
<li>Choose the main topic and main idea for each body paragraph.</li>
<li>Write our topic sentences.</li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-topic-sentence/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Zoos</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-writting-zoos/zoos.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Zoos have long been a subject of debate. While some people argue that zoos play a crucial role in conserving endangered species and educating the public about wildlife, others contend that confining animals to artificial environments is unethical. Discuss both views and give your own opinion.</em></p>
<section id="analysis" class="level1">
<h1>Analysis</h1>
<p>Advantage: pros: Conservation zoos often participate in breeding programs and reintroduction efforts for endangered species. Education: They provide a unique opportunity for the public to learn about wildlife and environmental issues. Research: Zoos support scientific research and rehabilitation programs that can benefit species survival</p>
<p>Disadvantage Cons: Ethical concerns: Confining animals can lead to physical and psychological stress, raising serious animal welfare issues. Natural Behavior: The artificial habitats in zoos may prevent animals from expressing their natural behaviors, potentially leading to a diminished quality of life.</p>
</section>
<section id="sample" class="level1">
<h1>Sample</h1>
<p>In recent years, zoos have become a focal point of heated debate. On the one hand, proponents argue that zoos are indispensable for conserving endangered species and educating the public. On the other hand, critics maintain that confining animals to unnatural settings is inherently unethical. In my view, while the welfare of captive animals must be a priority, the benefits of well-managed zoos in conservation and education are substantial.</p>
<p>Supporters of zoos highlight their critical role in preserving biodiversity. With numerous species facing extinction, zoos provide a controlled environment where endangered animals can be bred and nurtured away from the threats of habitat loss and poaching. Many institutions have pioneered successful breeding programs, subsequently reintroducing species into the wild. Moreover, zoos serve as a vital educational platform, offering visitors first-hand exposure to wildlife. This experience not only fosters environmental awareness but also inspires future generations to engage in conservation efforts. Additionally, ongoing research in these settings has led to significant advancements in veterinary medicine and species rehabilitation.</p>
<p>Conversely, opponents argue that the confinement of animals infringes on their natural rights. Critics assert that even the most well-intentioned zoos cannot replicate the complex ecosystems that wild animals depend on, often leading to behavioral and psychological issues. The ethical debate is further intensified by instances of inadequate care and substandard living conditions in some facilities. While these concerns are valid, they underscore the need for stringent regulations rather than the outright dismissal of zoos as an institution.</p>
<p>In conclusion, although the ethical implications of captivity are significant, I believe that the conservation, education, and research benefits provided by zoos justify their existence - provided that animal welfare is rigorously safeguarded. This balanced approach can ensure that zoos continue to contribute positively to both wildlife preservation and public understanding of environmental issues.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>advantages disadvantage</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-writting-zoos/zoos.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
