<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Kim Hung Bui</title>
<link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>My Personal Website</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Compound sentence</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/compound-sentence/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A sentence can contain more than one sentence within it, for example:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Jane put the glass vase on the table and her mother picked it up.</li>
</ol>
<p>This is an example of a compound sentence. It actually contain two sentences. The first is <em>Jane put the glass vase on the table</em>. Since a sentence within a sentence is called a clause, we can also say that sentence 1 contains two clauses. Just as a simple sentence must contain at least a subject and a verb phrase, each of the sentences (clauses) within a compound sentence must contain its own subject and verb phrase.</p>
<p>Recall, conjunctions like <em>and, or, but</em> join things. In fact, the two sentences within sentence 1 are joined by the conjunction <em>and</em>. Recall also that there are two kinds of conjunctions, coordinating and subordinating. The sentences in a compound sentence are joined together by a coordinating conjunction. There are three common coordinating conjunctions they are <em>and, or,</em> and <em>but</em>. Four less common ones are <em>for, so, yet</em>, and <em>nor</em>. (FANBOYS)</p>
<section id="exercises" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Exercises</h1>
<p>Each of the sentences below is a compound sentence consisting of two sentences (clauses). Underline each of the sentences which is in the compound sentence. Sample: I felt restless after breakfast and I wandered around the house.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><u>Andre pulled the car into the street</u>, and <u>Beth began reading the directions</u>.</p></li>
<li><p><u>She enjoyed shopping for food</u>, but <u>she especially enjoyed cooking</u>.</p></li>
<li><p><u>I can do this now</u>, or <u>I can do it later</u>.</p></li>
<li><p><u>Dan does not feel well</u>, yet<u> he wants to go in to work</u>.</p></li>
<li><p><u>We missed our flight</u>, so <u>we have to wait around the airport for the next available one</u>.</p></li>
<li><p><u>He does not like to change his mind</u>, nor <u>is he willing to compromise</u>.</p></li>
<li><p><u>You deserve your good fortune</u>, for <u>you have a heart of gold.</u></p></li>
<li><p><u>The players are running onto the field</u>, and <u>then they are beginning to practice</u>.</p></li>
<li><p><u>Stephanie likes to go to concerts</u>, but <u>she will not see an opera</u>.</p></li>
<li><p><u>You can pay with cash</u>, or <u>you can take out a loan</u>.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Decide if each sentence below is a simple sentence or a compound sentence. Remember that a simple sentence contains just one sentence (clause) while a compound sentence contains at least two sentences joined by a coordinating conjunction. Sample:Wallace stared at him in the grocery store. simple</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>He can’t blame her for the problem. (simple)</li>
<li>Beth left the library, and she headed straight home. (compound sentence)</li>
<li>He was watching her, but she was pretending not to notice. (compound)</li>
<li>We like him a lot. (simple)</li>
<li>The coach wants to win, but he will be happy with a tie. (compound)</li>
<li>It will be a sunny day. (simple)</li>
<li>Jeremy likes his wife’s new dress. (simple)</li>
<li>I will have a bowl of soup, but I don’t want salad. (compound)</li>
<li>Sam called me at noon. (simple)</li>
<li>He will be going to Penn State, or he’ll study at Temple University. (compound)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>A compound sentence can contain more than two sentences:</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Nora was Zach’s stepmother but she treated him like her other children and he trusted her completely.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here, the <u>three</u> sentences that make up this sentence are: (1) <em>Nora was Zach’s stepmother</em>; (2) <em>she treated him like her other children</em>; (3) <em>he trusted her completely</em>. So the sentence <em>There was a glass vase on the table and Jane picked it up</em> contains two sentences, or clauses. In fact, a compound sentence can contain any number of sentences, though we usually limit ourselves to just a few:</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>He turned his head away and he pretended to ignore her but he continued to listen to her and in fact he hung on her every word. (4 sentences or clauses)</li>
</ol>
<p>Keep in mind that you can’t tell if a sentence is simple or compound by how long it is; you need to see if it contains one or more than one complete sentence within it. For example, the following sentence, although it is long, is just a simple sentence:</p>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>The tall man with the violin case quickly climbed the stairs to the abandoned warehouse near the railroad tracks.</li>
</ol>
<p>This is a simple sentence because it has just one subject, <em>the tall man with the violin case</em>, and one verb phrase - notice that there is just one verb, <em>climbed</em>. (The sentence is just long because it contains a few preposition phrases.) And the following sentence, although it is short, is a compound sentence: <em>John laughed and Mary cried</em>. It’s a compound sentence because it contains two sentences that can stand alone: <em>John laughed; Mary cried</em>. Each of these has its own subject and verb phrase.</p>
<section id="exercises-1" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-1"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Each sentence below is either a simple or compound sentence. Identify the number of clauses in each sentence. If there is more than one clause in the sentence, underline each clause. Sample:The bear watched his movements closely. 1</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Vicki was always looking at herself in the mirror, but MaryAnn was extremely self-confident, and she never gave herself a second glance. 3</li>
<li>Her father was devoted to her. 1</li>
<li>Our firm’s CEO will be flying to Chicago next week, but he’ll be returning the same day. 2</li>
<li>The lady in the elegant blue dress entered the well-lit room with her perky little dog in her arms. 1</li>
<li>Our boat was hit with strong winds, and we had to return to our cabins. 2</li>
<li>We don’t have much time left in the zoo, but we should visit the bird cage, and we must see the monkeys, or we should at least feed the goats in the petting area, but I definitely want to take a look at the elephants. 5</li>
<li>We can catch a movie, or we can visit a museum, but we won’t be seeing a Broadway show. 3</li>
<li>Many people walk in the woods in autumn. 1</li>
<li>The economy is getting worse, and many people are worried about their jobs. 2</li>
<li>My car is getting old, and it’s pretty banged up, but I hope to get another year out of it. 3</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Keep in mind that a compound <u>phrase</u> is not the same thing as a compound <u>sentence</u>. For example, the following sentence has a compound noun phrase.</p>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>The teacher graded <u>the student’s exam and their papers</u>.</li>
</ol>
<p>We’ve certainly got a coordinating conjunction, <em>and</em>, in sentence 5. However, the question is, what the <em>and</em> joining? If we look at what’s on each side of the <em>and</em>, we find the following: <em>The teacher graded the student’s exams</em>, which is a sentence, and <em>their papers</em>; <em>their papers</em> is not a sentence by itself. In this case, the conjunction <em>and</em> is joining two noun phrases: <em>the students’ exams</em> and <em>their papers</em>. It’s not joining two complete sentences, and so the sentences is not a compound sentence but is a simple sentence.</p>
</section>
<section id="exercises-2" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-2"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Decide if each sentence below is a simple or compound sentence. Remember that a compound sentence contains a complete sentence on either side of the conjunction.</p>
<p>Sample: Kyle turned around and stared at the screen. simple</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>It was a scene of joy but one thing spoiled the moment. (compound)</li>
<li>The boxer fell to his knees but he managed to get back up. (compound)</li>
<li>The designer and his assistants quickly brought order to the chaos. (simple)</li>
<li>Matt was driving to NewYork with his kids and his neighbor’s son. (simple)</li>
<li>I like to drink coffee or tea after dinner. (simple)</li>
<li>The weather is already getting chilly, but I am not ready for winter just yet. (compound)</li>
<li>His speech should be brief and to the point. (simple)</li>
<li>You must get ready immediately or I’ll leave without you. (compound)</li>
<li>The flight attendant offered me beef or chicken for the entree. (simple)</li>
<li>She likes classical music but rarely goes to concerts. (compound)</li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>grammar</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/compound-sentence/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Complex Sentence - Part 2</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/complex-sentence-2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>PART 2: ADJECTIVE CLAUSES # An Introduction to Relative Clauses</p>
<section id="review" class="level2" data-number="0.1">
<h2 data-number="0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review"><span class="header-section-number">0.1</span> Review</h2>
<p>A complex sentence is a sentence that contains an independent clause and one or more subordinate clauses.</p>
<p>Subordinate clauses can be classified as adverb clauses, <strong>adjective clauses</strong>, or noun clauses.</p>
<p>Those subordinate clauses that function as adjectives are known as <strong>relative clauses</strong>.</p>
<p>Relative clauses begin with one of the following <strong>relative pronouns</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>who, what, which, whom, whose, what, when, where, why</em>. We are going to focus on three that we use most often in our writing: <em>who, that</em>, and <em>which</em>. Examples:</p></li>
<li><p>I met a man {who had lost the ability to cry or sing}. (The independent clause <em>I met a man</em> + the relative clause <em>who had lost the ability to cry or sing</em>).</p></li>
<li><p>There came a dream of hopes {that never yet had flushed his cheek}. (The independent clause <em>there came a dream of hopes</em> + the relative clause <em>that never yet had flushed his cheek</em>).</p></li>
<li><p>The speaker spoke of youth, {which night and time have quenched forever}. (the independent clause <em>the speaker spoke of youth</em> + the relative clause <em>which night and time have quenched forever</em>).</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="exercises" class="level2" data-number="0.2">
<h2 data-number="0.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises"><span class="header-section-number">0.2</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Identify the independent and relative clauses contained in the following complex sentences.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The men of England plow for the lords who oppress them. [What is the relative clause in this sentence? Hint: it starts with who, that, or which.] -who oppress them</p></li>
<li><p>The men of England plow for the lords who oppress them. [What is the independent clause in this sentence? Hint: it is all the words not contained in your previous answer.] -the men of England plow for the lords</p></li>
<li><p>At last we understood the woe that had wasted him. [What is the relative clause in this sentence? Hint: it starts with who, that, or which.] -that had wasted him.</p></li>
<li><p>At last we understood the woe that had wasted him. [What is the independent clause in this sentence? Hint: it is all the words not contained in your previous answer.] -At last we understood the woe</p></li>
<li><p>Encircling ivy covered the halls, which the waterfalls willed with unfailing sound. [What is the relative clause in this sentence? Hint: it starts with who, that, or which.] -which the waterfalls willed with unfailing sound.</p></li>
<li><p>Encircling ivy covered the halls, which the waterfalls willed with unfailing sound. [What is the independent clause in this sentence? Hint: it is all the words not contained in your previous answer.] -Encircling ivy covered the halls.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="the-medial-position" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> The Medial Position</h1>
<p>In the previous lesson, we took our first look at relative clauses. Each of the sentences contained in that lesson features a relative clause in the <strong>terminal position</strong> (the position to the right of an independent clause): - Independent clause + relative clause. However, relative clauses may also appear in the <strong>medial position</strong>: The terms <em>introductory, medial,</em> and <em>terminal</em> help us to refer to key places within a sentence. Quite simply:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>introductory</strong> = at the beginning</li>
<li><strong>medial</strong> = in the middle</li>
<li><strong>terminal</strong> = at the end</li>
</ul>
<p>Here is an example of a relative clause in the medial position:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The man {who had lost the ability to cry or sing} <strong>was sitting</strong> in the corner. Here, the relative clause <em>who had lost the ability to cry or sing</em> sits in the medial position - between the subject <em>man</em> and the verb <em>was sitting</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>The hopes {that never yet had flushed his cheek} <strong>would</strong> soon <strong>be realized</strong>. Here, the relative clause <em>that never yet had flushed his cheek</em> sits in the medial position - between the subject <em>hopes</em> and the verb <em>would be realized</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Youth, {which night and time have quenched forever}, cannot be recaptured. Here, the relative clause <em>which night and time have quenched forever</em> sits in the medial position-between the subject <em>youth</em> and the verb <em>can be recaptured</em>.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="exercises-1" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-1"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Identify the independent and relative clauses contained in the following complex sentences. In each case, the relative clause sits in the medial position —between the subject and verb of the independent clause.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The living winds, WHICH flow like waves above the living waves below, are creating navigational difficulties for the nightingales. [What is the relative clause in this sentence? Hint: it starts with who, that, or which.] -which flow like waves above the living waves below</p></li>
<li><p>The living winds, WHICH flow like waves above the living waves below, are creating navigational difficulties for the nightingales. [What is the independent clause in this sentence? Hint: it is all the words not contained in your previous answer.] -the living winds are creating navigational difficulties for the nightingales.</p></li>
<li><p>The sounds THAT soothed her sleep came in through the open window. [What is the relative clause in this sentence? Hint: it starts with who, that, or which.] -that soothed her sleep</p></li>
<li><p>The sounds THAT soothed her sleep came in through the open window. [What is the independent clause in this sentence? Hint: it is all the words not contained in your previous answer.] -the sound came in through the open window</p></li>
<li><p>The people WHO are lost in stormy vision need our sympathy. [What is the relative clause in this sentence? Hint: it starts with who, that, or which.] -who are lost in stormy vision</p></li>
<li><p>The people WHO are lost in stormy vision need our sympathy. [What is the independent clause in this sentence? Hint: it is all the words not contained in your previous answer.] -the people need our sympathy.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="subjects-and-verbs-in-sentences-with-relative-clauses" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Subjects and Verbs in Sentences with Relative Clauses</h1>
<p>Relative clauses are clauses that function as adjectives. How so? Three <strong>relative clauses</strong>, with their subjects and verbs marked:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>who</em> <strong>fall</strong> in love</p></li>
<li><p><em>that</em> <strong>sits</strong> in the center of the circle</p></li>
<li><p><em>which</em> <strong>remained</strong> obscure in the mind of his listeners</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Each of these word groups is a clause because each contains a subject and a verb. Each is subordinate because each is unable to stand alone as its own independent sentence.</p>
<p>To gain their status as clauses, these word groups cheat a bit: they use their own relative pronouns as subjects. They lack independence because their subject are not true subjects. The relative pronouns that serve as subjects (<em>who, that,</em> and <em>which</em>) cannot exist without the <strong>antecedents</strong> they point to.</p>
<p>Let’s take the three relative clauses from above and add them to some independent clauses.</p>
<section id="complex-sentence-1" class="level3" data-number="2.0.1">
<h3 data-number="2.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="complex-sentence-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.1</span> Complex Sentence 1</h3>
<ul>
<li>People {<em>who</em> <strong>fall</strong> in love} <strong>know</strong> the movement of time.</li>
</ul>
<p>In this example, the medial relative clause sits between the primary subject and verb.</p>
<ul>
<li>primary subject-verb: <em>people know</em></li>
<li>secondary subject-verb: who fall</li>
</ul>
<p>With the relative clause <em>who fall in love</em>, we find that the relative pronoun <em>who</em> serves not only as the clause’s first word, but also as its subject. Because <em>who</em> is a pronoun, it exists courtesy of an <strong>antecedent</strong> it can point to - which happens to be <em>people</em>, the subject of the independent clause. In this case, the subject of the relative clause is linked to the subject of the independent clause via pronoun-antecedent connection.</p>
</section>
<section id="complex-sentence-2" class="level3" data-number="2.0.2">
<h3 data-number="2.0.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="complex-sentence-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.2</span> Complex Sentence 2</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>The <em>object</em> {<em>that</em> <strong>sits</strong> in the center of the circle} <strong>resembles</strong> a silver tear. In this example, the medial relative clause once again sits between the primary subject and verb.</p></li>
<li><p>primary subject-verb: object resembles</p></li>
<li><p>secondary subject-verb: that sits</p></li>
</ul>
<p>With the relative clause <em>that sits in the center of the circle</em>, we find that the relative pronoun <em>that</em> serves not only as the clause’s first word, but also as it subject. Because <em>that</em> is a pronoun, it exists courtesy of an antecedent it can point to- which happens to be <em>object</em>, the subject of the independent clause. Once again, we find that the subject of the relative clause is linked to the subject of the independent clause.</p>
</section>
<section id="complex-sentence-3" class="level3" data-number="2.0.3">
<h3 data-number="2.0.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="complex-sentence-3"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.3</span> Complex Sentence 3</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>The <em>chatterer</em> <strong>provided</strong> no details in support of his statement, {<em>which</em> <strong>remained</strong> obscure in the mind of his listeners}. In this example, the relative clause is not in the medial position, as it was in the two previous examples, but in the terminal position.</p></li>
<li><p>primary subject-verb: chatterer provided</p></li>
<li><p>secondary subject-verb: which remained</p></li>
</ul>
<p>With the relative clause <em>which sits in the center of the circle</em>, we find that the relative pronoun <em>which</em> serves not only as the clause’s first word, but also as its subject. Because <em>which</em> is a pronoun, it exists courtesy of an antecedent it can point to, which happens to be the noun <em>statements</em>, not the subject <em>chatterer</em>. We see, then, that when relative clauses are moved to positions further from the primary subject, the subjects of the two clauses no longer maintain a pronoun-antecedent connection.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-makes-relative-clauses-adjectival" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-makes-relative-clauses-adjectival"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> What makes relative clauses adjectival?</h2>
<p>We need to demonstrate that relative clauses do, in fact, function as adjectives. Let’s use the three example sentences we saw earlier:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>People</em> {<em>who</em> <strong>fall</strong> in love} <strong>know</strong> the movement of time. Here, the relative clause <em>who fall in love</em> is describing the noun <em>people</em>; thus it is functioning as an adjective.</p></li>
<li><p>The <em>object</em> {<em>that</em> <strong>sits</strong> in the center of the circle} <strong>resembles</strong> a silver tear. Here, the relative clause <em>that sits in the center of the circle</em> is describing the noun <em>object</em>; thus it is functioning as an adjective.</p></li>
<li><p>The <em>chatterer</em> <strong>provided</strong> no details in support of his statement, {which <strong>remained</strong> obscure in the mind of his listeners}. Here, the relative clause <em>which remained obscure in the mind of listeners</em> is describing the noun <em>statements</em>; thus it is functioning as an adjective.</p></li>
</ul>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>As a rule, relative clauses sit immediately next to the nouns they describe.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="exercises-2" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Here we will focus on the adjectival quality of relative clauses by identifying relative clauses and the nouns those clauses are describing.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The rumormonger took the money from the safe, WHICH had been left unlocked. [What is the relative clause? This relative clause is functioning as an adjective because it is describing which noun?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>which had been left unlocked</li>
<li>the safe</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>The savage, WHO wore a sassy leopard skin, defended his territory against all invaders. [What is the relative clause? Which noun it is describing?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><p>who wore a sassy leopard skin</p></li>
<li><p>the savage</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>The shelter THAT was made of straw was blown down by the wolf. [What is the relative clause? Which noun it is describing?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><p>that was made of straw was blown down by the wolf</p></li>
<li><p>the shelter</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>The trophy went to the sweeper WHO used the longest broom. [What is the relative clause? Which noun it is describing?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>who used the longest broom</li>
<li>the sweeper</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>The toddler chose the diaper THAT had been hanging on the clothesline. [What is the relative clause? Which noun it is describing?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>that had been hanging on the clothesline</li>
<li>the diaper</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>The toboggan, WHICH was painted magenta, raced down the icy hillside. [What is the relative clause? Which noun it is describing?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>which was painted magenta</li>
<li>the toboggan</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="restrictive-and-nonrestrictive-relative-clauses" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Restrictive and Nonrestrictive Relative Clauses</h1>
<p>Some of the relative clauses have been punctuated with commas, some without. This is because relative clauses are either <strong>restrictive</strong> or <strong>nonrestrictive</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>restrictive</strong> = no commas</li>
<li><strong>nonrestrictive</strong> = commas Here is the difference between the two: Often, restrictive clauses serve the purpose of narrowing the possibilities within a group; nonrestrictive clauses serve no such purpose.</li>
</ul>
<p>For example, suppose we have a group of actors. During rehearsal that day some actors attend rehearsal; some did not. By using a restrictive relative clause, we can reduce the larger group of <em>all</em> actors to a smaller group - those who didn’t attend rehearsal.</p>
<ul>
<li>The actor {<em>who</em> failed to attend rehearsal} were forgetting their lines.</li>
</ul>
<p>When we use relative clauses, we must be consciously aware of our purpose in using them: Are we restricting a larger group (restrictive clause)? Or are we just adding additional information (restrictive clause)? We must also be conscious of our punctuation choice: Are we restricting a large group? (If so, we don’t use commas). Or are we just adding additional information? (If so, we do use commas.)</p>
<section id="exercises-3" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-3"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>For each sentence below, first identify the relative clause; then determine whether that clause is restrictive or nonrestrictive.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>On every side now rose rocks, WHICH lifted their barren pinnacles in the light of evening. [What is the relative clause? Is it restrictive or nonrestrictive?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Which lifted their barren pinnacles in the light of evening.</li>
<li>nonrestrictive - have commas, it does not restrict a group of rock from a larger group.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>The eagle, WHO can scale Heaven in a mighty flash, soars and screams round her empty nest. [What is the relative clause? Is it restrictive or nonrestrictive?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Who can scale Heaven in a mighty flash</li>
<li>nonrestrictive, in that sentence, just has 1 eagle.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>The eddying waters rose, circling fast and dashing the roots of trees THAT stretched their arms in darkness. [What is the relative clause? Is it restrictive or nonrestrictive? What larger group of things is being restricted to a smaller group?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>THAT stretched their arms in darkness.</li>
<li>It is restrictive, the roots of trees are being restricted to a smaller group-just those that stretched their arms in the darkness.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>The great moon, WHICH suspended her mighty horn over the wide world, guided us safely home. [What is the relative clause? Is it restrictive or nonrestrictive?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Which suspended her mighty horn over the wide world.</li>
<li>it is nonrestrictive, just one moon</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>The sweet brook THAT rose from the secret springs of a dark fountain gurgled its way down the mountainside. [What is the relative clause? Is it restrictive or nonrestrictive? What larger group of things is being restricted to a smaller group?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>that rose from the secret springs of a dark fountain</li>
<li>restrictive-the larger group of brooks is being restricted to a smaller group-just the one that rose from the secret springs of the dark fountain.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>These were the famous Euganean hills, WHICH bear the likeness of a clump of islands. [What is the relative clause? Is it restrictive or nonrestrictive?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>which bear the likeness of a clump of islands</li>
<li>nonrestrictive</li>
</ul>
<ol start="7" type="1">
<li>They do not borrow their glory from men WHO make the world their prey. [What is the relative clause? Is it restrictive or nonrestrictive? What larger group of people is being restricted to a smaller group?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>who make the world their prey</li>
<li>restrictive-the larger group of men is being restricted to a smaller group-just those who make the world their prey</li>
</ul>
<ol start="8" type="1">
<li>We looked out upon the grass THAT trembled with the sense of an unaccustomed presence. [What is the relative clause? Is it restrictive or nonrestrictive? What larger group of things is being restricted to a smaller group?]</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>that trembled with the sense of an unaccustomed presence.</li>
<li>restrictive-the larger group of grass is being restricted to a smaller group-just the grass that trembled with the sense of an unaccustomed presence.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="focus-on-relative-pronouns" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Focus on Relative Pronouns</h1>
<section id="which-versus-that" class="level2" data-number="4.1">
<h2 data-number="4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="which-versus-that"><span class="header-section-number">4.1</span> Which Versus That</h2>
<p>With few exceptions, the relative pronoun <em>which</em> is punctuated with commas while the relative pronoun <em>that</em> is used without commas. In other words, <em>which</em> is used to create nonrestrictive clauses and <em>that</em> is used to create restrictive clauses.</p>
</section>
<section id="exercises-4" class="level2" data-number="4.2">
<h2 data-number="4.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-4"><span class="header-section-number">4.2</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>For each of the following, first identify the relative clause. Then decide whether the sentence needs one comma, two commas, or none at all. Clauses formed from which need commas; clauses formed from that go without.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Travelers crossing the water hear the bell that calls the maniacs from their cells.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>relative clause: that calls the maniacs from their cells</li>
<li>without commas - because clauses formed from that.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>The city that gave you refuge calls for you to return.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>that gave you refuge</li>
<li>without commas</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>This wild spirit which moves everywhere is both a destroyer and a preserver.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>which moves every where</li>
<li>rewrite: this wild spirit, which moves everywhere, is both a destroyer and a preserver.</li>
<li>use which, need 2 commas.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>And they dragged the cruel King to kiss their bloodied feet which threatened to trample him.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>which threatened to trample him.</li>
<li>rewrite: And they dragged the cruel King to kiss their bloodied feet, which threatened to trample him.</li>
<li>use which, need 1 comma</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="who-versus-that" class="level2" data-number="4.3">
<h2 data-number="4.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="who-versus-that"><span class="header-section-number">4.3</span> Who Versus That</h2>
<p>With few exceptions, we use <em>who</em> with people and we use <em>that</em> with things. A common error occurs when we fail to notice that we have used <em>that</em> when we should have used <em>who</em>.</p>
</section>
<section id="exercises-5" class="level2" data-number="4.4">
<h2 data-number="4.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-5"><span class="header-section-number">4.4</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Correct each of the following sentences by applying the rule use “who” with people and use “that” with things. 5. Freedom remains with those that are truly free.</p>
<ul>
<li>freedom -&gt; human</li>
<li>Corrected: Freedom remains with those who are truly free.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>There yet remained a few that would not bow their spirits to the Conqueror.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>their spirits to the Conqueror -&gt; human</li>
<li>Corrected: There yet remained a few who would not bow their spirits to the Conqueror.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="7" type="1">
<li>The sleeping mother dreamed of the children that once roamed throughout her house.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>the children -&gt; human</li>
<li>Corrected: The sleeping mother dreamed of the children who once roamed throughout her house.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="8" type="1">
<li>This is the poet that can’t stop quoting haikus at his guests.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>poet -&gt; human</li>
<li>Corrected: This is the poet who can’t stop quoting haikus at his guests.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="who-versus-whom-1" class="level1" data-number="5">
<h1 data-number="5"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Who Versus Whom 1</h1>
<section id="subjective-versus-objectives-forms" class="level2" data-number="5.1">
<h2 data-number="5.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="subjective-versus-objectives-forms"><span class="header-section-number">5.1</span> Subjective Versus Objectives Forms</h2>
<p><em>Who</em> and <em>Whom</em> are actually two forms of the same word: <em>who</em> is the <strong>subjective</strong> form and while <em>whom</em> is the <strong>objective</strong> form.</p>
<p>At this point, we could digress into an explanation of the subjective case and the objective case- but we won’t. Instead, we’ll take a shortcut by learning this general rule:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>Whom</em> is followed by a noun or pronoun; <em>who</em> is followed by a verb. Study these two examples:</p></li>
<li><p>This Earth has been peopled with the servants <em>whom</em> <strong>you require</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p>I am the only man <em>who</em> <strong>writes in the margins</strong>.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>In each example, the relative clause is boldfaced and the relative pronoun is italicized. Notice that <em>whom</em> is followed by the pronoun <em>you</em> and <em>who</em> is followed by the verb <em>writes</em>.</p>
</section>
<section id="exercises-6" class="level2" data-number="5.2">
<h2 data-number="5.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-6"><span class="header-section-number">5.2</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Complete the sentences below by inserting who or whom in place of the blank. If the word after the blank is a verb, use who; if the word after the blank is a noun or pronoun, use whom.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Such aggressive action reminded us of the owl ___ faces whatever she sees.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>faces is a verb, use who</li>
<li>Rewrite: Such aggressive action reminded us of the owl who faces whatever she sees.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>That heavenly maiden ___ mortals call the Moon glides across the night sky.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>mortals is a noun - use whom</li>
<li>Rewrite: That heavenly maiden whom mortals call the Moon glides across the night sky.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>The people ___ she loves move through the familiar rooms.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>she is a noun -&gt; use whom</li>
<li>Rewrite: The people whom she loves move through the familiar rooms.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>This was the massive father ___ lifted the boy high with one hand.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>lifted is a verb -&gt; use who</li>
<li>This was the massive father who lifted the boy high with one hand.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>This is the man ___ fame singled out as her favorite.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>fame is a noun -&gt; use whom</li>
<li>Rewrite: This is the man whom fame singled out as her favorite</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>Today we would study the poet ___ wrote of the oval office.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>wrote is a noun, so that we use who</li>
<li>Rewrite: Today we would study the poet who wrote of the oval office.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="who-versus-whom-2" class="level1" data-number="6">
<h1 data-number="6"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Who Versus Whom 2</h1>
<section id="a-writing-trick-with-whom-as-the-object-of-a-preposition" class="level2" data-number="6.1">
<h2 data-number="6.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-writing-trick-with-whom-as-the-object-of-a-preposition"><span class="header-section-number">6.1</span> A Writing Trick with <em>Whom</em> As the Object of a Preposition</h2>
<p>Another function of the objective relative pronoun <em>whom</em> is to serve as the object of a preposition. The preposition category includes such words as <em>at, below, by, for, from, in, of, on, through, to,</em> and <em>with</em>.</p>
<p>Using <em>whom</em> as the object of a preposition allows us to perform the following trick. This trick can be performed with any relative clause that ends with a preposition.</p>
<p>Example:</p>
<ul>
<li>He was the kind of knight <em>whom</em> ladies could be proud <strong>of</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now, we take the preposition (of) from the end of the relative clause and move it to the front of the relative clause:</p>
<ul>
<li>He was the kind of knight <strong>of</strong> <em>whom ladies could be proud</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>One more example, with the relative clause in the medial position:</p>
<ul>
<li>The people <em>whom you smiled <strong>on</strong></em> were warmed to the heart. -becomes-</li>
<li>The people <em><strong>on</strong> whom you smiled</em> were warmed to the heart.</li>
</ul>
<p>This simple trick can lend a more formal and stylish tone to our writing.</p>
</section>
<section id="exercises-7" class="level2" data-number="6.2">
<h2 data-number="6.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-7"><span class="header-section-number">6.2</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>In each sentence below, move the preposition from the end of the relative clause to the front of the relative clause. Note the more elevated tone that results. For this one, you might try voicing your results out loud. 1. I knew one like you whom this city gave welcome to.</p>
<ul>
<li>Rewrite: I knew one like you to whom this city gave welcome.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>The people whom Percy argued with were the ones he most tried to avoid.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Rewrite: The people with whom Percy argued were the ones he most tried to avoid.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>We failed to recognize the shepherd whom wolves would flee from.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Rewrite: We failed to recognize the shepherd from whom wolves would flee.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>The sister whom you share your secrets with has written you a new song.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Rewrite: The sister with whom you share your secrets has written you a new song.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>We now have a list of the souls whom the bell tolls for.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Rewrite: We now have a list of the souls for whom the bell tolls.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="reduction-of-relative-clauses" class="level1" data-number="7">
<h1 data-number="7"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Reduction of Relative Clauses</h1>
<p>We must also learn to pay heed to this word of caution:</p>
<ul>
<li>It is often better to <strong>reduce</strong> relative clauses to shorter phrases.</li>
</ul>
<p>We often find that perfectly good phrases are hiding inside relative clauses, waiting to be freed. We free them by removing the relative pronoun (<em>who, that, which</em>) and the <em>to be</em> verb (<em>is, am, are, was, were</em>) that follows the relative pronoun.</p>
<ul>
<li>Example 1: The mountain, <strong>which was</strong> unconquered by those who scale it, cannot be mistaken for a molehill.</li>
</ul>
<p>Remove <em>which was</em> we get: <em>The mountain, unconquered by those who scale it, cannot be mistaken for a molehill.</em></p>
<ul>
<li>Example 2: The nation adores its hermits, <strong>who are</strong> the preservers of solitude.</li>
</ul>
<p>Remove <em>who are</em> and we get: <em>The nation adores its hermits, the preservers of solitude</em></p>
<ul>
<li>Example 3: The tree <strong>that is</strong> growing in Eden embodies opposites in balance.</li>
</ul>
<p>Remove <em>that is</em> and we get: <em>The tree growing in Eden embodies opposites in balance</em>.</p>
<p>Relative pronouns are also deletable when they are objective pronouns.</p>
<p>Examples: - The bed of flowers <del>that</del> she slept in … - The children <del>whom</del> she once raised …</p>
<section id="exercises-8" class="level2" data-number="7.1">
<h2 data-number="7.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-8"><span class="header-section-number">7.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Each of the sentences below contains a relative clause, and each relative clause contains a phrase in need of liberation. Liberate those phrases by deleting the relative pronoun (who, that, which) and the to be verb (is, am, are, was, were). Simply read the sentences to yourself without voicing the two deletable words. 1. The billy goat, which is watching without judgment from behind his strange eyes, stands patient for two millennia.</p>
<ul>
<li>Rewrite: The billy goat, watching without judgment from behind his strange eyes, stands patient for two millennia.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>I greeted the new ones, who were the frightened and longing ones.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Rewrite: I greeted the new ones, the frightened and longing ones.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>The flowering chestnuts, which are red and white in the morning light, drift above the watery pavement.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The flowering chestnuts, red and white in the morning light, drift above the watery pavement.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>I cannot reach the handkerchief that is drying on the hook.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>I cannot reach the handkerchief drying on the book.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>The husband and wife, who are like two scrappy parlor pets, share an established glee.</li>
</ol>
<p>The husband and wife, like two scrappy parlor pets, share an established glee.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>grammar</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/complex-sentence-2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Complex Sentence - Part 3</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/complex-sentence-3/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>PART 3: NOUN CLAUSES.</p>
<section id="creating-noun-clauses" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Creating Noun Clauses</h1>
<section id="review" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Review</h2>
<p>We began our study of complex sentences by learning that a complex sentence is an independent clause (a sentence) plus a subordinate clause. We learned that there are three types of subordinate clauses: adverb, adjective (the relative clause), and noun.</p>
<p>We have covered subordinate clauses of the adverb and adjective variety. The adverbial clauses appear to the left or the right of independent clauses and begin with subordinating conjunctions:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>after, as if, as long as, as soon as, although, as, as if, because, before, even if, if, since, so that, though, till, unless, until, when, whenever, wherever, while</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The adjectival clauses are relative clauses. We focused on three key relative pronouns: <em>who, that,</em> and <em>which</em>.</p>
<p>This bring us to our final clause type-the <strong>noun clause</strong>.</p>
<p>Like their cousins are adverbial and relative clauses, the noun clauses, too, begin with key words. We can call these key word <strong>noun-clause markers</strong>.</p>
<p>Here is a list:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>that, if, whether</em></li>
<li>{words that can be used to create question} <em>how, what, when, where, whom, why</em></li>
<li>{the -ever words} <em>however, whatever, whenever, wherever, whichever, whoever, whomever</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>If we take an independent clause (a sentence) and add a noun-clause marker to the front of it, we get a noun clause.</p>
<ul>
<li>noun-clause marker + independent clause = noun clause</li>
</ul>
<p>Examples:</p>
<p><strong>take a sentences</strong>: <em>the foal was delivered by helicopter</em></p>
<p><strong>add a noun-clause marker</strong>: <em>that</em></p>
<p><strong>get a noun clause</strong>: <em>that the foal was delivered by helicopter</em></p>
<p>Once more:</p>
<ul>
<li>take a sentence: the Shah wanted it delivered</li>
<li>add a noun-clause marker: whenever</li>
<li>get a noun clause: whenever the Shah wanted it delivered.</li>
</ul>
<p>When a noun clause get added to an independent clause, the result is a complex sentence. Study two examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>example 1: <em>What the clown found so funny</em> was a mystery. (complex sentence? no)</li>
<li>example 2: We did not understand <em>why George was twitching in the forsythias</em> (complex sentence? yes)</li>
</ul>
<p>A complex sentence consists of an independent clause and at least one subordinate clause. Example 1 above consists of a noun clause plus a predicate (<em>was a mystery</em>) and, therefore, is not a complex sentence. In example 2, however, we do find one independent and one subordinate clause.</p>
<ul>
<li>independent clause: we did not understand</li>
<li>subordinate clause: why George was twitching in the forsythias</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="exercises" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Decide which noun-clause markers from the bulleted list below can be attached to which of the following sentences. (Not all noun-clause markers will work with all sentences.)</p>
<p>Keep in mind that you are creating noun clauses, not sentences. A noun clause is a type of subordinate clause and, therefore, cannot stand alone. In fact, the noun-clause marker you add is the word that converts what would have been an independent clause into a subordinate clause.</p>
<ul>
<li>noun-clause markers: that, if, whether, how, what, when, where, whom, why, however, whatever, whenever, wherever, whichever, whoever, whomever</li>
</ul>
<ol type="1">
<li>that the time was far away</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>that the time was far away</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>the old woman had painted a picture of a dozen oranges</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>how the old woman had painted a picture of a dozen oranges</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>truth is a mix of gold and silver</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>when truth is a mix of gold and silver</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>the duck had spoken to the drake</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>whatever the duck had spoken to the drake</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>the opposite of kite is yo-yo</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>that the opposite of kite is yo-yo</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>the weatherman would stop to bow</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>whenever the weatherman would stop to blow</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="noun-clauses-in-sentences" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Noun Clauses in Sentences</h1>
<p>Complex sentences take this form:</p>
<ul>
<li>independent clause + subordinate clause</li>
</ul>
<p>Noun clauses are one type of subordinate clause, so when we add noun clauses to sentences, we create complex sentences.</p>
<p>Noun clauses function as nouns; consequently, wherever we can place a noun, we can also place a noun clause. And we can test for <em>nounness</em> by using the key word <strong>something, somewhere,</strong> and <strong>someone</strong>. Whatever can replace any of these three words is a noun.</p>
<p>Examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>We did not understand <em>something</em>.</li>
<li>We did not understand <em>why George was twitching in the forsythias</em></li>
</ul>
<p>In this example, the noun clause <em>why George was twitching in the forsythias</em> functions as a single noun.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>When using noun clauses to create complex sentences, the number of forms such sentences can take is limited. The number of verbs can be used in the creation of complex sentences with noun clauses is also limited.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Here is a list of verbs that can precede noun clauses:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>accept, admire, adore, appreciate, ask, catch, cherish, claim, comprehend, covet, decide, demand, desire, despise, detest, doubt, enjoy, feel, hate, have, hear, know, lack, like, love, make, miss, own, prefer, realize, recognize, require, see, smell, take, taste, understand, value, want, wonder.</em></li>
</ul>
<section id="exercises-1" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Step 1: Turn the second independent clause into a noun clause by adding a noun-clause marker to the front of it.</p>
<p>Step 2: Place the noun clause into the independent clause-simply replace the word <em>something</em>.</p>
<p>Example:</p>
<ul>
<li>first independent clause: you knew <em>something</em></li>
<li>second independent clause: the time was far away</li>
</ul>
<p>Step 1: second independent clause + noun-clause marker = <em>that the time was far away</em></p>
<p>Step 2: Insert the result of step 1 into the first independent clause = you knew that the time was far away.</p>
<p>Result? We have created a complex sentence containing a noun clause.</p>
<p><strong>Number 1</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>first independent clause: she understands <em>something</em></li>
<li>second independent clause: truth is a mix of gold and silver</li>
<li>noun clause-markers: that, if, whether, how, what, when, where, whom, why, however, whatever, whenever, wherever, whichever, whoever, whomever</li>
</ul>
<p>step 1: when truth is a mix of gold and silver</p>
<p>step 2: she understands when truth is a mix of gold and silver.</p>
<p><strong>Number 2</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>first independent clause: they did not comprehend <em>something</em></li>
<li>second independent clause: the duck had spoken to the drake</li>
</ul>
<p>step 1: whenever the ducker had spoken to the drake</p>
<p>step 2: they did not comprehend whenever the duck had spoken to the drake.</p>
<p><strong>Number 3</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>first independent clause: we loved <em>something</em></li>
<li>second independent clause: the weatherman would stop to bow</li>
</ul>
<p>step 1: if the weatherman would stop to bow</p>
<p>step 2: we loved if the weatherman would stop to bow.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="subjects-and-verbs-in-complex-sentences-with-noun-clauses." class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Subjects and Verbs in Complex Sentences with Noun Clauses.</h1>
<p>Clauses contain one or more subjects and one or more verbs; noun clauses are no exception.</p>
<p>Here are two clauses with their subjects and verbs marked:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>how</em> the <em>cat</em> <strong>got</strong> into the pantry</li>
<li>why <em>he</em> <strong>had slept</strong> so late</li>
</ul>
<p>And here are two independent clauses with their subjects and verbs maked:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>We</em> <strong>could</strong> not <strong>tell</strong> something.</li>
<li><em>Jameson</em> <strong>began</strong> to <strong>explain</strong> something.</li>
</ul>
<p>By adding our noun clauses to the independent clauses, we get complex sentences consisting of one independent and one subordinate clause:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>We</em> <strong>could</strong> not <strong>tell</strong> something</p></li>
<li><p><em>We</em> <strong>could</strong> not <strong>tell</strong> {how the <em>cat</em> <strong>got</strong> in to the pantry}.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Jameson</em> <strong>began</strong> to explain something.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Jameson</em> <strong>began</strong> to explain {why <em>he</em> <strong>had slept</strong> so late}.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="exercises-2" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-2"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>For each of the following, identify the primary and secondary subjects and verbs. The secondary subject-verb combination will appear within the noun clause.</p>
<ul>
<li>Example: I know THAT the hand of God is the mirror of my own.</li>
</ul>
<p>In this sentence, the primary subject-verb is I know and the secondary subject-verb (within the noun clause) is hand is.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>I dreamed THAT I went into a forest.</li>
</ol>
<p>In this sentence, the primary subject-verb is I dreamed and the secondary subject-verb (within the noun clause) is I went into.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>You saw WHY five old pieces of fish-line hung from his lower lip.</li>
</ol>
<p>In this sentence, the primary subject-verb is You saw and the secondary subject-verb is pieces hung.</p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>They will know WHETHER it is all happening in the only possible way.</li>
</ol>
<p>In this sentence, the primary subject-verb is They will know and the secondary subject-verb is it is.</p>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>I am afraid WHENEVER I go with the Northern Army on the long march south.</li>
</ol>
<p>In this sentence, the primary subject-verb is I am afraid and the secondary subject-verb is I go</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="review-1" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Review</h1>
<p>We have learned that a complex sentence consists of an independent clause (a sentence) and a dependent or subordinate clause. Once we understand this, we also understand that the study of complex sentences is really the study of subordinate clauses.</p>
<p>We have studied each type of subordinate clause: the adverb clause, the adjective (relative) clause, and the noun clause.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Adverb clauses begin with subordinating conjunctions</strong>: <em>after, as if, as long as, as soon as, although, as, as if, because, before, even if, if, since, so that, though, till, unless, until, when, whenever, wherever, while</em>.</li>
<li><strong>Adjective (relative) clauses begin with relative pronouns</strong>: <em>who, that, which</em> (the three most commonly used).</li>
<li><strong>Noun clauses begin with noun-clause markers</strong>: <em>that, if, whether, how, what, when, where, whom, why, however, whatever, whenever, wherever, whichever, whoever, whomever</em>.</li>
</ul>
<section id="that-the-noun-clause-marker-vs.-that-the-relative-pronoun" class="level2" data-number="4.1">
<h2 data-number="4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="that-the-noun-clause-marker-vs.-that-the-relative-pronoun"><span class="header-section-number">4.1</span> <em>THAT</em> THE NOUN-CLAUSE MARKER VS. <em>THAT</em> THE RELATIVE PRONOUN</h2>
<p>But wait a minute. If a word <em>that</em> can mark both relative clauses and noun clauses, how can we tell them apart?</p>
<p>Let’s do a comparison.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>relative clause</strong>: The trout <em>that swim in the center of the river</em> keep themselves safe.</li>
<li><strong>noun clause</strong>: I know <em>that the hand of God is the mirror of my own</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Both examples contain a clause that begins with <em>that</em>. Let’s let RC stand for <em>relative clause</em> and NC stand for <em>noun clause</em>. There are three differences between these two clauses.</p>
<section id="difference-1-the-part-of-speech" class="level3" data-number="4.1.1">
<h3 data-number="4.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="difference-1-the-part-of-speech"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.1</span> Difference 1: the part of speech</h3>
<section id="rc" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rc">RC:</h4>
<p>The relative clause, being an adjective, will describe a noun-in this case, the noun <em>trout</em>. What kind of trout? Trout <em>that swim in the center of the river</em>.</p>
</section>
<section id="nc" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nc">NC:</h4>
<p>The noun clause, being a noun, will pass the <em>something</em> test:</p>
<ul>
<li>I know <em>something</em>.</li>
<li>I know <em>that the hand of God is the mirror of my own</em>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="difference-2-the-clauses-subject" class="level3" data-number="4.1.2">
<h3 data-number="4.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="difference-2-the-clauses-subject"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.2</span> Difference 2: the clause’s subject</h3>
<section id="rc-1" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rc-1">RC</h4>
<p>The word <em>that</em> serves as the subject of the clause: <em><u>that</u> <strong>swim</strong> in the center of the river</em>.</p>
</section>
<section id="nc-1" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nc-1">NC</h4>
<p>The word <em>that</em> does not serve as the subject of the clause. (The subject-verb of the noun clause is <em>hand is</em>).</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="difference-3-the-preceding-word" class="level3" data-number="4.1.3">
<h3 data-number="4.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="difference-3-the-preceding-word"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.3</span> Difference 3: the preceding word</h3>
<p><strong>RC</strong>: The word preceding the clause (trout) is a noun. <strong>NC</strong>: The word preceding the clause (know) is a verb.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercises-3" class="level2" data-number="4.2">
<h2 data-number="4.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-3"><span class="header-section-number">4.2</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>For each of the following complex sentences, identify the independent and the subordinate clause. For each subordinate clause, decide whether the clause is functioning as an adverb, an adjective, or a noun.</p>
<p>The clause markers are listed here:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>adverb clause markers (subordinating conjunctions): after, as if, as long as, as soon as, although, as, as if, because, before, even if, if, since, so that, though, till, unless, until, when, whenever, wherever, while</p></li>
<li><p>adjective (relative) clause markers (relative pronouns): who, that, which (the three most commonly used)</p></li>
<li><p>noun-clause markers: that, if, whether, how, what, when, where, whom, why, however, whatever, whenever, wherever, whichever, whoever, whomever</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Example:</p>
<ul>
<li>AFTER he thumped the jammed vending machine, the trooper walked home in his snowshoes. (The independent clause consists of which words? The subordinate clause consists of which words? What kind of clause is the subordinate clause: adverb, adjective, or noun?)</li>
</ul>
<p>independent clause: the trooper walked home in his snowshoes</p>
<p>subordinate clause: AFTER he thumped the jammed vending machine (adverb clause)</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>I could not learn his mind because he never knew it himself. (The independent clause consists of which words? The subordinate clause consists of which words? What kind of clause is the subordinate clause: adverb, adjective, or noun?)</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>independent clause: I could not learn his mind</li>
<li>Subordinate clause: because he never knew it himself (adverb clause)</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>I followed whatever it was that whispered of love. (The independent clause consists of which words? The subordinate clause consists of which words? What kind of clause is the subordinate clause: adverb, adjective, or noun?)</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Independent clause: I followed</li>
<li>Subordinate clause: whatever it was that whispered of love. (noun-clause) (can pass something test)</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Imperfect stars create their reflections though the lake is mostly mud.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Independent clause: Imperfect stars create their reflections</li>
<li>subordinate clause: though the lake is mostly mud (adverb clause) (not pass something test, not who, which, that)</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>She wondered whether it was her heart or eyes that was faulty.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The independent clause of that sentence consists of ‘She wondered’</li>
<li>The subordinate clause of that sentence consists of ‘whether it was her heart or eyes that was faulty’ (noun clause) (pass something test)</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>We float messages to the refugees, who stand among the rubble of their flooded shelters</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The independent clause of the above sentence consists of ‘We float messages to the refugees’</li>
<li>The subordinate clause of the above sentence consists of ‘who stand among the rubble of their flooded shelters’. We know it is an adjective clause because that clause begins with the word ‘who’.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>We still hoped that they might get passage.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The independent clause of the above sentence consists of ‘We still hoped’</li>
<li>The subordinate clause of the above sentence consists of ‘that they might get passage’, and we know it is a noun clause because it can pass the something test.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="7" type="1">
<li>You might still touch the lips that once spoke.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The independent clause of the above sentence consists of ‘You might still touch the lips’.</li>
<li>The subordinate clause of the above sentence consists of ‘that once spoke’, and we know it is a relative clause-adjective clause because it cannot pass the something test, and after the word ‘that’, is a verb ‘spoke’.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="8" type="1">
<li>Your heart, which has been mined by others, will not recover its lightning and thunder</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The independent clause of the above sentence consists of ‘Your heart will not recover its lightning and thunder’.</li>
<li>The subordinate clause of the above sentence consists of ‘which has been minded by others’, and we know it is an adjective clause-relative clause because it begins with the word ‘which’.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="mixed-clauses-multiple-clauses" class="level1" data-number="5">
<h1 data-number="5"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Mixed Clauses, Multiple Clauses</h1>
<p>The complex sentences we’ve been studying represent the complex sentence at its most basic level: an independent clause (a sentence) with one subordinate clause. But in fact, complex sentence can contain mixed clauses (such as an adverb clause and a relative clause) or multiple clauses (such as three adverb clauses)</p>
<p>Here is an example of a complex sentence containing mixed clauses:</p>
<ul>
<li>{when Arjuna threw down his bow}, the warriors, {who were his cousins and kin}, ceased their fighting.</li>
</ul>
<p>This example contains an independent clause and two subordinate clauses: - <strong>independent clause</strong>: the warriors ceased their fighting. - <strong>adverb clause</strong>: when Arjuna threw down his bow. - <strong>relative clause</strong>: who were his cousins and kin.</p>
<p>Another example: - The crowd {that assembled on the sidewalks} would never understand {why he filled his conversation with so many foreign words}.</p>
<p>This example also contains an independent clause and two subordinate clauses:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>independent clause</strong>: the crowd would never understand.</li>
<li><strong>relative clause</strong>: that assembled on the sidewalks</li>
<li><strong>noun clause</strong>: why he filled his conversation with so many foreign words.</li>
</ul>
<p>Try out the next two examples independently. In the following example, see if we can identify an independent clause and <em>three</em> adverb clauses:</p>
<ul>
<li>When a teaspoonful of silkworm eggs endowed the church, when the letters of sacred testaments were unreeled in the coastal cities, when a bookworm conspired to enter the maze of empty roads, the rivers began flowing.</li>
</ul>
<p>The independent clause in that sentence is ‘the rivers began flowing’, and the three adverb clauses are: ‘when a teaspoonful of silkworm eggs endowed the church’, ‘when the letters of sacred testaments were unreeled in the coastal cities’, and ‘when a bookworm conspired to enter the maze of empty roads’.</p>
<p>And in this next example, identify an independent clause and <em>two</em> relative clauses:</p>
<ul>
<li>All this takes place on my lawn, which has nothing to do with the seasons that roll lightly by.</li>
</ul>
<p>In this sentence, the independent clause is “All this takes place on my lawn.”</p>
<p>The relative clause “which has nothing to do with the seasons that roll lightly by” adds information about “my lawn.”</p>
<p>Within that, “that roll lightly by” is a second relative clause, modifying “the seasons.”</p>
<section id="exercises-4" class="level2" data-number="5.1">
<h2 data-number="5.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-4"><span class="header-section-number">5.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>For each of the following, identify the independent and subordinate clauses.</p>
<p>For each subordinate clause, decide whether it’s an adverb clause, a relative clause (adjective), or a noun clause.</p>
<p>Before you begin, however, here are the answers to the last two examples you tried out on your own: - [WHEN a teaspoonful of silkworm eggs endowed the church], [WHEN the letters of sacred testaments were unreeled in the coastal cities], [WHEN a bookworm conspired to enter the maze of empty roads], the rivers began flowing.</p>
<p>independent: the rivers began flowing</p>
<p>adverb clause: WHEN a teaspoonful of silkworm eggs endowed the church</p>
<p>adverb clause: WHEN the letters of sacred testaments were unreeled in the coastal cities</p>
<p>adverb clause: WHEN a bookworm conspired to enter the maze of empty roads</p>
<ul>
<li>All this takes place on my lawn, [WHICH has nothing to do with the seasons] [THAT roll lightly by].</li>
</ul>
<p>independent: all this takes place on my lawn</p>
<p>relative clause: WHICH has nothing to do with the seasons</p>
<p>relative clause: THAT roll lightly by</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>As the nails began to fly away, we wondered how we were to get any work done. (1 independent; 2 subordinate)</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>In this sentence, the independent clause is ‘we wondered to get any work done’, and the adverb clause is ‘how we were’ adds information about ‘wondered’, and the relative clause ‘as the nails began to fly away’ adds information about wondered.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>The busybody who lives next door understands that the bronze statues have been draped in towels. (1 independent; 2 subordinate)</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>In this sentence, the independent clause is ‘the busybody understands’, and the relative clause ‘who lives next door’ adds information about ‘the busybody’, and the noun clause is ‘that the bronze statues have been draped in towels’.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>The donkey’s stance, which can be seen through the front window, will haunt you this day though you have left your shudders closed. (1 independent; 2 subordinate)</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>In this sentence, the independent clause is ‘the donkey’s stance will haunt you this day’, and the relative clause ‘which can be seen through the front window’ adds information about ‘the donkey’s stance’, and the adverb clause ‘though you have left your shudders closed’ adds information about ‘haunt’ (why haunt you this day).</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>The poem begins when the poet stops, when the poet gets out of the way. (1 independent; 2 subordinate)</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>In this sentence, the independent clause is ‘the poem begins’, the adverb clauses are ‘when the poet stops’, and ‘when the poet gets out of the way’.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>So that the speakers could still be heard from the steeple that graced our roof, we turned the knobs clockwise. (1 independent; 2 subordinate)</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>In this sentence, the independent clause is ‘we turned the knobs clockwise’, the relative clause is ‘that graced our roof’ adds information about ‘the steeple’ and the adverb clause ‘so that the speakers could still be heard from the steeple’ adds information about ‘turned the knobs clockwise’.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="complex-vs.-compound-sentences" class="level1" data-number="6">
<h1 data-number="6"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Complex Vs. Compound Sentences</h1>
<p>Before concluded our study of complex sentences, let’s see how the complex sentence compares with the compound sentence.</p>
<ul>
<li>Compound sentence: The parade is turning into our street, <em>for</em> the other streets have been barricaded.</li>
<li>complex sentence: The parade is turning into our street <em>because</em> the other streets have been barricaded.</li>
</ul>
<p>By studying these two examples, we note two differences: the comma and the conjunction. While complex sentences (those containing adverb clauses) are created with subordinating conjunctions (<em>although, because, when, etc</em>). Compound sentences are created with coordinating conjunctions (_for, and, nor, but, or, yet, so).</p>
<p>Stated this way, the difference between compound sentences and complex sentences seems light. And yet, they are treated as two different sentence categories. So that, really, is the difference between them?</p>
<p>Here is the difference: <em>Subordinating conjunctions attach to the right-hand sentence; coordinating conjunctions do not</em>.</p>
<p>Let’s look at our two examples once again, except that this time we’ll group the key components using bracket.</p>
<ul>
<li>Compound sentence: 1{The parade is turning into our street}, 2{for} 3{the other streets have been barricaded}.</li>
<li>Complex sentence: 1{The parade is turning into our street} 2{because the other streets have been barricaded}.</li>
</ul>
<p>The compound sentence consists of three components: (1) an independent clause, (2) a coordinating conjunction, and (3) a second independent clause. In other words, the coordinating conjunction <em>for</em> sits between the two clauses, independently and aloof.</p>
<p>The complex sentence consists of two components: (1) an independent clause (2) a subordinate (adverbial) clause. Here, the subordinating conjunction <em>attaches itself</em> to the subordinate clause.</p>
<p>In summary, it pays to understand the types of conjunctions and to be familiar with the conjunction groups that create which sentence types. Much of the work of distinguishing between simple, compound, and complex sentences can be boiled down to understanding the work being done by the conjunctions.</p>
<section id="exercises-5" class="level2" data-number="6.1">
<h2 data-number="6.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-5"><span class="header-section-number">6.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>Part 1: from Compound to Complex</p>
<p>In numbers 1-3, convert the compound sentences to complex sentences. To do this, replace the comma + coordinating conjunction (marked with small caps) with a subordinating conjunction chosen from this list:</p>
<ul>
<li>after, although, as, because, before, even if, if, since, so that, though, till, unless, until, when, whenever, wherever, while.</li>
</ul>
<ol type="1">
<li>The treasure could not be found, FOR the map had been drawn by a mad sea-captain.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The treasure could not be found because the map had been drawn by a mad sea-captain.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>We would hold our candles aloft in the rain, AND John Brown could see justice after all.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>We would hold our candles aloft in the rain so that John Brown could see justice after all.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>They had been completely surrounded by cowboys, SO the sparkling noise of horses sounded in their ears.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>They had been completely surrounded by cowboys while the sparkling noise of horses sounded in their ears.</li>
</ul>
<p>Part 2: from Complex to Compound</p>
<p>This time we’ll convert complex sentences to compound sentences. In numbers 4-6, replace the subordinating conjunction (marked with small caps) with a comma + coordinating conjunction chosen from this list: for, and, nor, but, or, yet, so.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The swift runners had begun WHILE the slow runners had gone to sleep.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The swift runners had begun, but the slow runners had gone to sleep.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>He had danced down the street’s center THOUGH the snow had continued to fall.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>He had danced down the street’s center, and the snow had continued to fall.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>You won’t hear the mourners’ song IF you are sobbing.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>You won’t hear the mourners’ song, so you are sobbing.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="compound-complex-sentences" class="level1" data-number="7">
<h1 data-number="7"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Compound-Complex Sentences</h1>
<p>To qualify as a compound-complex sentence, a sentence must have at least three clauses, two of them independent and one of them subordinate.</p>
<p>Let’s assemble a compound-complex sentence. We’ll begin with our three clauses:</p>
<ul>
<li>he bid farewell to his loved ones</li>
<li>the knight set out on an adventure</li>
<li>re remained loyal to the queen</li>
</ul>
<p>Now we’ll turn our first clause into a subordinate clause by adding the subordinating conjunction <em>after</em> to the front of it. We’ll join the other two clauses with the coordinating <em>but</em>, giving us a compound-complex sentence that looks like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>compound-complex sentence: <em>After</em> he bid farewell to his loved ones, the knight set out on an adventure, <em>but</em> he remained loyal to the queen.</li>
</ul>
<p>The simplest way to approach compound-complex sentences is to begin with a compound sentence and to add a subordinate clause to that compound sentence.</p>
<p>A compound sentence is two independent clauses joined together.</p>
<ul>
<li>independent clause [ ] independent clause</li>
</ul>
<p>Once we’ve established our compound sentence, we’ll need to insert a subordinate clause. Here are four slots where subordinate clauses can be inserted:</p>
<ul>
<li><u>1</u> independent clause <u>2</u> [ ] <u>3</u> independent clause <u>4</u></li>
</ul>
<p>The first requirement of a compound-complex sentence is the existence of three clauses. The second requirement is a way to join (or coordinate) the two independent clauses. In other words, in the formula <em>independent clause [ ] independent clause</em>, what goes inside the brackets?</p>
<p>Answer: The space inside the brackets can be filled by a coordinating conjunction, a conjunction adverb, a semicolon, or a colon. Because we have so much new material to cover, let’s limit our options here to one of the seven coordinating conjunctions: <em>for, and, nor, but, or, yet, so</em>.</p>
<p>Then, for our subordinate clause-whether it be an adverbial, a relative, or a noun clause-we will need a head- or a clause-marking word to serve as the first word of the clause.</p>
<ul>
<li>If our clause is an adverb clause, we’ll need a subordinating conjunction: <em>after, although, as, because, before, even if, if, since, so that, though, till, unless, until, when, whenever, wherever, while</em>.</li>
<li>If our clause is an adjective (relative) clause, we’ll need a relative pronoun: <em>who, that, which</em></li>
<li>If our clause is a noun phrase, we’ll need a noun-clause marker: <em>that, if, whether, how, what, when, where, whom, why, however, whatever, whenever, wherever, whichever, whoever, whomever</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now let’s bring all this together. Begin by studying the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>1 independent clause 2 [ ] 3 independent clause 4</li>
<li>1 the knight set out on an adventure 2 ; 3 <em>but</em> he remained loyal to the queen.</li>
</ul>
<p>The example above is a compound sentence consisting of two independent clauses joined by the coordinating conjunction <em>but</em>. To convert our compound sentence to a compound-complex sentence, we decide to place an adverbial subordinate clause in slot 1:</p>
<ul>
<li>{<em>After</em> he bid farewell to his loved ones}, {the knight set out on an adventure}; <em>but</em> {he remained loyal to the queen}.</li>
</ul>
<p>This compound-complex sentence consists of an adverbial subordinate clause sitting to the left (slot 1) of a compound sentence. Note that the three clauses are bracketed; note also the important role being played by the conjunctions <em>after</em> and <em>but</em>.</p>
<p>Let’s try another one. We begin with a compound sentence (two clauses joined by <em>for, and, nor, but, or, yet, so</em>):</p>
<ul>
<li>1 {The hotel kept one pet} 2, <em>yet</em> {the guests would have been happy with a kitten} 4.</li>
</ul>
<p>We decide to add a subordinate clause-this time a relative clause- to slot 2:</p>
<ul>
<li>{The hotel kept one pet}, {<em>which</em> happened to be a racehorse}; <em>yet</em> {the guests would have been happy with a kitten}.</li>
</ul>
<p>Here, note that the relative pronoun <em>which</em> is part of the clause it appears in.</p>
<p>In summary, compound-complex sentences can be created with five ingredients:</p>
<ul>
<li>clause 1</li>
<li>clause 2</li>
<li>clause 3</li>
<li><em>for, and, nor, but, or, yet, so</em> to make the sentence compound.</li>
<li>a creator of subordinate clauses: a subordinating conjunction, a relative pronoun, or a noun-clause marker.</li>
</ul>
<section id="exercises-6" class="level2" data-number="7.1">
<h2 data-number="7.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises-6"><span class="header-section-number">7.1</span> Exercises</h2>
<p>In this Your Turn you’ll do some composing. You are given four of the five ingredients found in the bulleted list above. The only thing lacking is one of the three clauses, which you will compose yourself.</p>
<p>Wherever you see the word clause, create a word group (it must contain a subject and verb) to insert into that position. Read your finished products out loud to see how your creations sound. 1. [Judy is sleeping confidently], AND AS [CLAUSE], [the sun is in no hurry to rise].</p>
<ul>
<li>Rewrite: Judy is sleeping confidently, and as the weather is winter, the sun is in no hurry to rise.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>[CLAUSE], AND she asks everyone to sit down SO THAT she can boast about the special things her children have done.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Everyone has come in, and she asks everyone to sit down so that she can boast about the special things her children have done.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>[The mayor, [WHO CLAUSE], refuses to answer my question], SO [I stick my head in the sand].</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The mayor, who is very confident, refuses to answer my question, so I stick my head in the sand.</li>
</ul>
<p>The subject of your relative clause is who, <em>which appears inside an independent clause</em>.</p>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>AS [we face each other across the table], [we wonder about our long-ago trip to Connecticut]; FOR [CLAUSE].</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>As we face each other across the table, we wonder about our long-ago trip to Connecticut; for my family can meet our son.</li>
</ul>
<p>The conjunction for means because.</p>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>[His notebook and pencil were ready], BUT [the crowd seemed too large and too frenzied] AS [CLAUSE].</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>His notebook and pencil were ready, but the crowd seemed too large and too frenzied, as they could not let him finish his test.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="test-questions" class="level1" data-number="8">
<h1 data-number="8"><span class="header-section-number">8</span> Test Questions</h1>
<p>The Test Questions section contains thirty-six complex sentences, each containing one subordinate clause. Your task is to identify the subordinate clause in each of the sentences and to label that clause as either an adverb clause, a relative clause, or a noun clause.</p>
<p>Two of the word lists below—subordinating conjunctions and noun-clause markers—contain fewer members than the lists you’ve been seeing throughout this e-book. These word lists contain just the words that are used in the test questions below.</p>
<p>Pay close attention to the word that. In the sentences that follow, that will be used at times as a relative pronoun and at times as a noun-clause marker. The difference between the two is discussed in Lesson 20.</p>
<ul>
<li>subordinating conjunctions (used to begin adverbial subordinate clauses): although, as, because, before, if, since, so that, though, till, until, when, while</li>
<li>relative pronouns (used to begin relative clauses): who, that, which</li>
<li>noun-clause markers (used to begin noun clauses): how, that, what, whatever, whether</li>
</ul>
<p>The question for each sentence is the same: The subordinate clause consists of which words? What kind of clause is it: adverb, relative, or noun?</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Although I did not understand a word they were saying, their sound surrounded me.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>subordinate clause: ‘although I did not understand a word they were saying’, adverb.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>As I run to Kim’s market, I thank my husband for his sacrifice.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘As I run to Kim’s market’, adverb</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Before you’ve had time to continue with your enthralling life story, they’re telling you their life story.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘Before you’ve had time to continue with your enthralling life story’, adverb</li>
</ul>
<ol start="4" type="1">
<li>Emily cursed the weasels that stole her chickens.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘that stole her chickens’, relative clause - adjective</li>
</ul>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>Her fair hand, which might bid heat return to a frozen age, trembles and swells once again.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘which might bid heat return to a frozen age’ - relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="6" type="1">
<li>His soft hand is placed over the mouth of the crier before it has time to gather the force of a cry.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘before it has time to gather the force of a cry’, adverb clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="7" type="1">
<li>I dined alone at a table with one rose vase as the mist advanced its coolly silvered drift of gray.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘as the mist advanced its coolly silvered drift of gray’ adverb</li>
</ul>
<ol start="8" type="1">
<li>I know the poems much better than the man because I’m willing to be honestly confused and honestly fearful.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘because I’m willing to be honestly confused and honestly fearful’, adverb</li>
</ul>
<ol start="9" type="1">
<li>I’ll tell of the things I’ve done when I am strong and able to bear arms.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘when I am strong and able to bear arms’, adverb</li>
</ul>
<ol start="10" type="1">
<li>If there is something unsoft in the city, God puts a soft stop to it.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘If there is something unsoft in the city’, adverb</li>
</ul>
<ol start="11" type="1">
<li>Life extends to the naked salty shore, which crumbles evermore.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘which crumbles evermore’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="12" type="1">
<li>Since I had kept the trust and had loved the lady, the knight withheld his giant sword and let me go.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘Since I had kept the trust and had loved the lady’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="13" type="1">
<li>The angry years feel that the flowers exist for us to fall in to.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘that the flowers exist for us to fall in to’, relative clause, cannot pass something test.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="14" type="1">
<li>The careless men who have taken to railroading have traveled off in search of salvation.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘who have taken to railroading’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="15" type="1">
<li>The caves echoed back to the writer who entered and never quite emerged.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘who entered and never quite emerge’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="16" type="1">
<li>The crumbling wall was made by the women who wear keys at their waists.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘who wear keys at their waists’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="17" type="1">
<li>The dinosaurs, who crawled like breathing lava from the earth’s cracked crust, swung their tiny heads above their lumbering tons of flesh.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘who crawled like breathing lava from the earth’s cracked crust’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="18" type="1">
<li>The empty basket of the child will float abandoned in the seaweed until the work of water unravels it in filaments of straw.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘until the work of water unravels it in filaments of straw’, adverb</li>
</ul>
<ol start="19" type="1">
<li>The house dog understands what life was like in younger and stronger times.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘what life was life in younger and stronger times’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="20" type="1">
<li>The murmuring city desires that we three walk across this bridge.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘that we three walk across this bridge’, noun clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="21" type="1">
<li>The others rang the bells till the sound filled up the garden.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘till the sound filled up the garden’, adverb clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="22" type="1">
<li>The planet that turns with them is always faithful.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘that turns with them’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="23" type="1">
<li>The soup-supper, which in the easy half-yellow light of autumn looked oddly beckoning, sat waiting on the oaken table.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘which in the easy half-yellow light of autumn looked oddly beckoning’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="24" type="1">
<li>The speakers of French suddenly remember how crows are like small black rivers.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘how crows are like small black river’, noun clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="25" type="1">
<li>The statue of the Virgin of Guadalupe is placed below the altar stairs so that Pilar can kneel before her and pray straight into her face.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘so that Pilar can kneel before her and pray straight into her face’, adverb clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="26" type="1">
<li>The youths in Union Square wonder whether fire or flowers grow crimson petals.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘whether fire or flowers grow crimson petals’, noun clause.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="27" type="1">
<li>They swim among the peaks of mountains while the old nightmares of earth settle into silt.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘while the old nightmares of earth settle into silt’, adverb clause.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="28" type="1">
<li>Those fleas that escaped earth and fire died by the cold.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘that escaped earth and fire’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="29" type="1">
<li>Those of us here will accept whatever it is that cannot be put down.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘whatever it is that cannot be put down’, noun clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="30" type="1">
<li>Though it is brightened by the last chapter of late autumn, the light returns somewhat pale.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘Though it is brightened by the last chapter of late autumn’, adverb clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="31" type="1">
<li>Today I notice them and turn away though at one time they were my joy.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘though at one time they were my joy’, adverb clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="32" type="1">
<li>Today my son realized that in the meadows at the edge of the woods are the trees of white flowers.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘that in the meadows at the edge of the woods are the trees of white flowers’, noun clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="33" type="1">
<li>When the tide turns, the water will fall by the ton.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘when the tide turns’, adverb clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="34" type="1">
<li>While the wrecks accumulate, our disbelief is suspended.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘while the wrecks accumulate’, adverb clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="35" type="1">
<li>Years of anger follow the hours that float idly down.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘that float idly down’, relative clause</li>
</ul>
<ol start="36" type="1">
<li>You should stay home if you can bring nothing to this place but your own body.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>‘if you can bring nothing to this place but your own body’, adverb clause</li>
</ul>
<p>CONGRATULATIONS!!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>grammar</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/complex-sentence-3/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>gracious</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/gracious/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Part of Speech: Adjective</p>
<section id="meaning" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Meaning</h1>
<section id="kind-polite-and-generous---especially-towards-others" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="kind-polite-and-generous---especially-towards-others"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Kind, polite, and generous - especially towards others</h2>
<ul>
<li>Often used to describe someone who is <strong>thoughtful and considerate</strong>, especially in a dignified or formal way.</li>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>She was <strong>gracious</strong> in both victory and defeat.</li>
<li>The host was extremely <strong>gracious</strong>, making sure every guest felt welcome.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="showing-elegance-or-good-taste" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="showing-elegance-or-good-taste"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> Showing elegance or good taste</h2>
<ul>
<li>Used to describe actions, gestures, or language that is <strong>refined and tasteful</strong></li>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>He gave a <strong>gracious</strong> acceptance speech after receiving the award.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="exclamatory-expressing-surprise-or-mild-shock" class="level2" data-number="1.3">
<h2 data-number="1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exclamatory-expressing-surprise-or-mild-shock"><span class="header-section-number">1.3</span> (Exclamatory) Expressing surprise or mild shock</h2>
<p>(mainly British English, informal usage) Example: Good <strong>gracious</strong>, look at the time</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="synonyms" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Synonyms</h1>
<ul>
<li>Courteous</li>
<li>Polite</li>
<li>Elegant</li>
<li>Kind-hearted</li>
<li>Considerate</li>
<li>Well-mannered</li>
<li>Civil</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="ielts-sample-sentences" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> IELTS Sample Sentences</h1>
<section id="speaking-part-1" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speaking-part-1"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Speaking Part 1:</h2>
<p>My grandmother is the most <strong>gracious</strong> person I know - she always treats everyone with kindness, no matter who they are.</p>
</section>
<section id="speaking-part-2" class="level2" data-number="3.2">
<h2 data-number="3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speaking-part-2"><span class="header-section-number">3.2</span> Speaking Part 2:</h2>
<p>The man I met during the trip was incredibly <strong>gracious</strong>. Even though I was a stranger, he offered to help me find my hotel and even gave me a bottle of water.</p>
</section>
<section id="writing-task-2" class="level2" data-number="3.3">
<h2 data-number="3.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="writing-task-2"><span class="header-section-number">3.3</span> Writing Task 2:</h2>
<p>In many cultures, being <strong>gracious</strong> and respectful is seen as essential social behavior, especially when interacting with elders or guests.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="common-collocations" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Common Collocations</h1>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 27%">
<col style="width: 72%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Phrase</th>
<th>Example</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>gracious host</td>
<td>They were gracious hosts and made us feel at home</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>gracious acceptance</td>
<td>She made a gracious acceptance speech.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>gracious behavior</td>
<td>His gracious behavior left a lasting impression.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>gracious declined</td>
<td>He graciously decline the invitation.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The number of new residential constructions in the south and the west dropped steadily from 2006 to 2012. It declined considerably from 900000 and about 450 000 in 2006 to 450000 and 200000 in 2008, respectively with the south and the west. The period between 2008 and 2010 experienced a slight decrease to 300000 and 150 000 of new house built in the south and the west, before a mild climb to about 310000 and 160 000 in 2012.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/gracious/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>task 1 - paragraphs</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/task 1/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I wrote:</p>
<pre><code>The number of new residential constructions in the south and the west dropped steadily from 2006 to 2012. It declined considerably from 900000 and about 450 000 in 2006 to 450000 and 200000 in 2008, respectively with the south and the west. The period between 2008 and 2010 experienced a slight decrease to 300000 and 150 000 of new house built in the south and the west, before a mild climb to about 310000 and 160 000 in 2012.</code></pre>
<section id="coherence-cohesion-band-5.56" class="level3" data-number="0.0.1">
<h3 data-number="0.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="coherence-cohesion-band-5.56"><span class="header-section-number">0.0.1</span> Coherence &amp; Cohesion (Band 5.5–6)</h3>
<p>❌ Confusing sentence structure: The second sentence is overly long and hard to follow.</p>
<p>❌ Linking devices are basic or missing: Use clearer transitions like “This figure fell further in the following years…” or “However, a minor rise was seen in 2012…”</p>
<p>✅ Attempts paragraphing and sequencing — but needs clearer flow.</p>
</section>
<section id="lexical-resource-band-6" class="level3" data-number="0.0.2">
<h3 data-number="0.0.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lexical-resource-band-6"><span class="header-section-number">0.0.2</span> Lexical Resource (Band 6)</h3>
<p>✅ Good use of terms like “steadily,” “considerably,” “slight decrease,” “mild climb.”</p>
<p>❌ Repetition of words like “dropped” and “decreased” — try synonyms: declined, fell, dipped, reduced, diminished.</p>
<p>❌ “Of new house built” → should be “in the number of new houses built.”</p>
</section>
<section id="grammatical-range-and-accuracy-band-55.5" class="level3" data-number="0.0.3">
<h3 data-number="0.0.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="grammatical-range-and-accuracy-band-55.5"><span class="header-section-number">0.0.3</span> Grammatical Range and Accuracy (Band 5–5.5)</h3>
<p>❌ “450 000 and about 450 000 in 2006 to 450000 and 200000 in 2008, respectively with the south and the west” → very awkward and grammatically confusing.</p>
<p>❌ Misuse of “respectively with” → it should be: “…450,000 and 200,000 in 2008, for the south and the west, respectively.”</p>
<p>❌ “300000 and 150 000 of new house built” → ❌ incorrect structure. Should be:</p>
<p>✅ “300,000 and 150,000 new houses built”</p>
</section>
<section id="rewritten-version-band-7.5-8-model" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Rewritten Version (Band 7.5-8 model)</h1>
<p>The number of new residential constructions in the South and the West dropped steadily between 2006 and 2012. In 2006, approximately 900,000 new houses were built in the South, while the West recorded about 450,000. These figures fell significantly by 2008, reaching 450,000 and 200,000 respectively. Between 2008 and 2010, the decline continued, though more gradually, with the numbers dropping to 300,000 in the South and 150,000 in the West. However, by 2012, there was a slight increase, with around 310,00 homes constructed in the South and 160,000 in the West.</p>
</section>
<section id="higher-band-version" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Higher band version</h1>
<p>Between 2006 and 2012, the number of new residential constructions in both the South and the West declined overall, though with minor fluctuations. In 2006, the South recorded approximately 900,000 new homes, while the West saw about half that figure at 450,000. By 2008, these numbers had dropped significantly to 450,000 in the South and 200,000 in the West. The downward trend continued more gradually over the next two years, reaching 300,000 and 150,00 respectively by 2010. However, 2012 saw a slight recovery, with new constructions rising modestly to around 310,000 in the South and 160,000 in the West.</p>
<hr>
<p>The number of visitors to Dover increases overall throughout the year. In Spring, Dover recorded approximately 5,000 tourists. The Summer experiences a sharp climb to two times the figure of the before season. The upward trend continues more gradually over the next two seasons, reaching 15,000 in Autumn before having a peak at 25,000 in Winter.</p>
<section id="coherence-cohesion-band-5.56-1" class="level3" data-number="2.0.1">
<h3 data-number="2.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="coherence-cohesion-band-5.56-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.1</span> Coherence &amp; Cohesion (Band 5.5–6)</h3>
<p>✅ You attempt a logical sequence: Spring → Summer → Autumn → Winter.</p>
<p>❌ However, some sentence transitions are unnatural or slightly unclear.</p>
<p>❌ Use of linking phrases like “before having a peak” is awkward and unidiomatic.</p>
</section>
<section id="lexical-resource-band-6-1" class="level3" data-number="2.0.2">
<h3 data-number="2.0.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lexical-resource-band-6-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.2</span> Lexical Resource (Band 6)</h3>
<p>✅ Good attempt with words like “sharp climb,” “upward trend”</p>
<p>❌ “two times the figure of the before season” → awkward and incorrect. Better:</p>
<p>✅ “twice the number recorded in the previous season.”</p>
<p>❌ “experiences a sharp climb” → Summer can’t “experience” something.</p>
<p>✅ Use: “There was a sharp rise in summer…” or “The number increased sharply in summer.”</p>
</section>
<section id="grammatical-range-accuracy-band-55.5" class="level3" data-number="2.0.3">
<h3 data-number="2.0.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="grammatical-range-accuracy-band-55.5"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.3</span> Grammatical Range &amp; Accuracy (Band 5–5.5)</h3>
<p>❌ “The Summer experiences” → incorrect article usage. Should be:</p>
<p>✅ “In summer, the number rose sharply…”</p>
<p>❌ “before having a peak” → ungrammatical. Try:</p>
<p>✅ “before peaking at 25,000 in winter.”</p>
<p>✅ You attempted complex structures, but several were awkward or incorrect.</p>
<p>Sample:</p>
<p>The number of visitors to Dover increased overall throughout the year. In Spring, the town welcomed approximately 5,000 tourists. This figure doubled in summer, rising sharply to 10,000. The upward trend continued at a more moderate pace, reaching 15,000 in autumn, before peaking at 25,000 in winter.</p>
<hr>
<p>Engineering was the dominant choice for male students, comprising 45% of their total enrollment, more than twice the proportion of females in the same field (20%). In contrast, only 10% of men choose Humanities, while this subject attracted 30% of women, three times higher. Similarly, Education accounted for 35% of female enrollment, compared to just 20% of men.</p>
<p>🔍 Detailed Analysis</p>
<p>🟦 1. Task Achievement (Band 7–8)</p>
<p>✅ You cover key features and specific numbers.</p>
<p>✅ You make comparisons between male and female enrollment.</p>
<p>❌ Minor inconsistency in the final sentence — it’s Education that had 35% of women and 20% of men, which you got right, but the word “just” is too informal here.</p>
<p>🟨 2. Coherence &amp; Cohesion (Band 7)</p>
<p>✅ Clear overall structure and logical flow: from Engineering → Humanities → Education.</p>
<p>❌ “three times higher” is vague. It’s better to say: “three times the proportion” or “threefold that of men.”</p>
<p>❌ Avoid “similarly” unless the comparison is parallel — Education and Humanities are different in structure.</p>
<p>🟥 3. Lexical Resource (Band 7)</p>
<p>✅ Good use of: comprising, proportion, attracted, accounted for.</p>
<p>❌ Could vary with more formal phrases like:</p>
<p>“enrolled in” instead of “choose”</p>
<p>“constituted” instead of “accounted for”</p>
<p>🟩 4. Grammatical Range &amp; Accuracy (Band 7)</p>
<p>✅ Mostly correct grammar and comparatives.</p>
<p>❌ “Choose” → should be past tense: chose (as you’re describing a chart, not a general truth)</p>
<p>❌ Minor article omission: “more than twice the proportion…”</p>
<p>Rewrite: Engineering was the most popular subject among male students, accounting for 45% of their total enrollment, which was more than twice the proportion of females in the same field (20%). In contrast, only 10% of men chose Humanities, compared to 30% of women - three times the male figure. Likewise, Education attracted 35% of female students, while just 20% of male students enrolled in this subject.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/task 1/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>compendium</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/compendium/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Part of Speech: Noun</p>
<section id="meaning" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Meaning</h1>
<p>A concise collection of detailed information about a particular subject - Often in book, report, or list form - Usually covers essential facts, summaries, or highlights</p>
<section id="synonyms" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="synonyms"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Synonyms</h2>
<ul>
<li>Summary</li>
<li>Digest</li>
<li>Overview</li>
<li>Compilation</li>
<li>Handbook</li>
<li>Guide</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="examples-in-sentences" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Examples in Sentences</h1>
<section id="general-use" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="general-use"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> General use:</h2>
<p>The museum published a <strong>compendium</strong> of artifacts from ancient Egypt.</p>
<p>This book is a useful <strong>compendium</strong> of medical knowledge for new students.</p>
</section>
<section id="formal-academic-use" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="formal-academic-use"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Formal / Academic Use:</h2>
<p>The government released a <strong>compendium</strong> of economic statistics for the past decade.</p>
<p>His thesis began with a <strong>compendium</strong> of theories related to social inequality.</p>
</section>
<section id="common-collocations" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="common-collocations"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Common collocations:</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 31%">
<col style="width: 68%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Collocation</th>
<th>Example</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>a compendium of facts</td>
<td>The report offers a compendium of facts about childhood nutrition</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>a valuable compendium</td>
<td>This guide is a valuable compendium for language learners.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>publish / compile a compendium</td>
<td>The agency compiled a compendium of safety regulations.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="in-writing-task-2" class="level2" data-number="2.4">
<h2 data-number="2.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-writing-task-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.4</span> In Writing task 2</h2>
<p>While many students rely on online sources, a well-organized <strong>compendium</strong> of academic materials can offer more structured and reliable content for research.</p>
<p>The report functions as a <strong>compendium</strong> of global climate change data, providing policymakers with a clear overview of the current challenges.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/compendium/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Type of sentences</title>
  <dc:creator>Kim Hung Bui</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/sentences-type/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In <strong>IELTS Writing Task 1 (Academic)</strong>, using a <strong>range of sentence types</strong> is crucial for achieving a <strong>Band 7 or higher</strong> in <strong>Grammatical Range and Accuracy</strong>.</p>
<p>Here’s a list of <strong>sentence types you should use</strong>, with <strong>examples</strong> tailored to data description:</p>
<section id="kinds-of-sentences-according-to-structure" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Kinds of sentences according to structure</h1>
<section id="simple-sentences" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="simple-sentences"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Simple Sentences</h2>
<p>Used to state clear facts. Simple Sentences have one subject and one finite verb.</p>
<ul>
<li>Structure: Subject + verb + object</li>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>Internet access rose in all income groups.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="compound-sentences" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compound-sentences"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> Compound Sentences</h2>
<p>Connect two related ideas using coordinating conjunctions (and, but, or, so, yet). When two independent clauses are joined by <strong>for, and, nor, but, or, yet, so</strong> (FANBOYS), we <strong>must use a comma</strong> before the conjunction. Those clauses can be connected by a semicolon (;)</p>
<ul>
<li>Structure: Independent clause + conjunction + independent clause.</li>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>She told a folk tale, <strong>and</strong> we all listened to her.</li>
<li>He does not speak our language, yet see seems to understand what we say.</li>
<li>Low-income households saw growth, but they remained behind other groups.</li>
<li>We moved to Florida in 1978; we stayed only five years <strong>and</strong> then returned to Ohio.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Compound sentences can be reduced by removing the subject and verb in the second clause if they are the same as in the first clause.</p>
<ul>
<li>We ask him now or (we) wait until tomorrow.</li>
<li>He is sitting and (he is) listening to me.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="complex-sentences" class="level2" data-number="1.3">
<h2 data-number="1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="complex-sentences"><span class="header-section-number">1.3</span> Complex Sentences</h2>
<p>Used to show relationships such as cause, contrast, or time. A complex sentence is made up of: - One independent clause (main clause) - One or more dependent clauses (subordinate clauses)</p>
<p>The main clause can stand alone as a complete sentence.</p>
<p>The subordinate clause cannot stand alone-it depends on the main clause to complete its meaning.</p>
<p>Structure:</p>
<p>[Main Clause] + [Subordinate Clause]</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>[Subordinate Clause], [Main Clause]</p>
<ul>
<li>Examples:
<ul>
<li>Because she was tired, she went to bed early.
<ul>
<li>“she went to bed early” = main clause</li>
<li>“Because she was tired” = subordinate clause (reason)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>I stayed at home <strong>although</strong> it was sunny.
<ul>
<li>“I stay at home” = main clause</li>
<li>“although it was sunny” = subordinate clause (contrast)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>When the movie ended, we left the cinema
<ul>
<li>“we left the cinema” = main clause</li>
<li>“When the movie ended” = subordinate clause (time)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Although the figures increased, the gap between groups remained wide.</li>
<li>As time progressed, internet access became more common.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<section id="type-of-subordinate-clauses" class="level3" data-number="1.3.1">
<h3 data-number="1.3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="type-of-subordinate-clauses"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.1</span> Type of Subordinate Clauses</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Type</strong></th>
<th><strong>Function</strong></th>
<th><strong>Example</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Adverbial</td>
<td>Shows time, reason, condition…</td>
<td><em>If it rains</em>, we’ll cancel the picnic.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Adjective</td>
<td>Modifies a noun</td>
<td>The book <em>that you gave me</em> is interesting.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Noun</td>
<td>Acts as a subject/object</td>
<td><em>What he said</em> surprised everyone.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="common-subordinating-conjunctions" class="level3" data-number="1.3.2">
<h3 data-number="1.3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="common-subordinating-conjunctions"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.2</span> Common Subordinating Conjunctions</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Type</strong></th>
<th><strong>Examples</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Time</td>
<td>when, while, after, before, until</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Reason</td>
<td>because, since, as</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Condition</td>
<td>if, unless, provided that</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Contrast</td>
<td>although, even though, whereas</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Purpose</td>
<td>so that, in order that</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Using comma
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Use a <strong>comma</strong> if the subordinate clause comes first.
<ul>
<li><em>Although it was late</em>, they continued working</li>
</ul></li>
<li>No comma if the main clause comes first:
<ul>
<li>They continued working _although it was late</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="complex--compound-sentences" class="level2" data-number="1.4">
<h2 data-number="1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="complex--compound-sentences"><span class="header-section-number">1.4</span> Complex- Compound Sentences</h2>
</section>
</section>
<section id="passive-voice" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Passive Voice</h1>
<p>Useful for focusing on what happened rather than who did it (common in process/task descriptions).</p>
<ul>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>A steady increase was observed in all three income categories. # Comparative Sentences Used to highlight differences or similarities.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>The high-income group had nearly twice the access as the middle-income group in 2005.</li>
<li>Internet usage in low-income households was much lower than in the other two groups. # Superlative Sentences Used to emphasize the highest or lowest point in the data.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>The high-income group had the highest internet access throughout the period.</li>
<li>The smallest increase was seen in the middle-income group between 2015 and 2020. # Trend Description Sentences Used to describe change over time.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Examples:
<ul>
<li>The figure rose steadily from 35% to 82%.</li>
<li>There was a sharp increase in internet access between 2010 and 2015.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="quantifying-and-grouping-sentences" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Quantifying and Grouping Sentences</h1>
<p>Useful when describing portions of categories.</p>
<ul>
<li>Examples:
<ul>
<li>Over half of the middle-income households had internet access by 2015.</li>
<li>Only a small fraction of low-income households were online in 2005.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="exercise" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Exercise:</h1>
<ol type="1">
<li>Her father would not consent to her living a alone in a big city. The phrase “her living a alone in a big city” is a gerund phrase acting as the <strong>object</strong> of the verb “consent”. It’s <strong>not</strong> a separate clause with a subject and verb.</li>
<li></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>grammar</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/sentences-type/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introduction and overview</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/introduction-overview/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="how-to-write" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> How to write</h1>
<section id="synonyms" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="synonyms"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Synonyms</h2>
<p>Use this dictionary while practicing IELTS Writing Task 1 to improve vocabulary variety and precision. Ideal for all chart types: bar, pie, line, table, map, and process.</p>
<section id="verbs-for-show-display" class="level3" data-number="1.1.1">
<h3 data-number="1.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="verbs-for-show-display"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.1</span> Verbs for “Show” / “Display”</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 92%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Common Word</th>
<th>Synonyms / Variants</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>show</td>
<td>illustrate, depict, present, demonstrate, display, represent, exhibit, outline, provide information about, give data on, compare, highlight</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="nounsverbs-for-change" class="level3" data-number="1.1.2">
<h3 data-number="1.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nounsverbs-for-change"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.2</span> 2. Nouns/Verbs for “Change”</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 50%">
<col style="width: 50%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Type</th>
<th>Synonyms</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>increase (noun)</td>
<td>growth, rise, climb, surge, upswing, escalation</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>increase (verb)</td>
<td>rise, grow, climb, go up, surge, escalate, shoot up</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>decrease (noun)</td>
<td>drop, fall, decline, reduction, downturn, dip, decrease</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>decrease (verb)</td>
<td>fall, drop, decline, decrease, plummet, go down, shrink, dip</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="synonyms-for-proportion-percentage" class="level3" data-number="1.1.3">
<h3 data-number="1.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="synonyms-for-proportion-percentage"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.3</span> 3. Synonyms for “Proportion / Percentage”</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 56%">
<col style="width: 43%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Common Word</th>
<th>Synonyms</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>proportion</td>
<td>share, fraction, segment, slice (pie charts), distribution, ratio</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>percentage</td>
<td>rate, level, portion, figure</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>small</td>
<td>minor, limited, modest, negligible</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>large</td>
<td>major, significant, considerable, substantial</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="synonyms-for-types-sources-categories" class="level3" data-number="1.1.4">
<h3 data-number="1.1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="synonyms-for-types-sources-categories"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.4</span> 4. Synonyms for “Types / Sources / Categories”</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Common Word</th>
<th>Synonyms</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>sources</td>
<td>types, kinds, categories, forms, classes, groups</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>kinds</td>
<td>categories, sorts, varieties, classifications</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="synonyms-for-people-groups-users" class="level3" data-number="1.1.5">
<h3 data-number="1.1.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="synonyms-for-people-groups-users"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.5</span> Synonyms for “People / Groups / Users”</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 56%">
<col style="width: 43%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Common Word</th>
<th>Synonyms</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>people</td>
<td>individuals, users, participants, members of the public, citizens</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>men</td>
<td>males, male individuals</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>women</td>
<td>females, female individuals</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>users</td>
<td>consumers, participants, clients, visitors</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="synonyms-for-place-region-country" class="level3" data-number="1.1.6">
<h3 data-number="1.1.6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="synonyms-for-place-region-country"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.6</span> Synonyms for “Place / Region / Country”</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Common Word</th>
<th>Synonyms</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>place</td>
<td>area, region, location, zone, territory</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>country</td>
<td>nation, state</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="verbs-for-time-trends" class="level3" data-number="1.1.7">
<h3 data-number="1.1.7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="verbs-for-time-trends"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.7</span> Verbs for Time &amp; Trends</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 60%">
<col style="width: 40%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Phrase</th>
<th>Alternatives</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>remained steady</td>
<td>stayed constant, was stable, showed little change, levelled off</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>fluctuated</td>
<td>varied, shifted, was inconsistent, experienced ups and downs</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>peaked</td>
<td>reached a peak, hit the highest point, soared to a maximum</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>bottomed out</td>
<td>fell to a low point, reached the lowest level, dipped to its minimum</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="describing-time-periods" class="level3" data-number="1.1.8">
<h3 data-number="1.1.8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="describing-time-periods"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.8</span> Describing Time Periods</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 46%">
<col style="width: 53%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Phrase</th>
<th>Synonyms / Alternatives</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>in 2000</td>
<td>in the year 2000, during 2000</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>between 2000 and 2020</td>
<td>from 2000 to 2020, over the 20-year period</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>over time</td>
<td>over the years, across the period, throughout the timeline</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="synonyms-for-number-amount-quantity" class="level3" data-number="1.1.9">
<h3 data-number="1.1.9" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="synonyms-for-number-amount-quantity"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.9</span> Synonyms for “Number / Amount / Quantity”</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 56%">
<col style="width: 43%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Common Word</th>
<th>Synonyms</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>number</td>
<td>figure, total, count, value</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>amount</td>
<td>volume, extent, level, quantity, load</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>a lot of</td>
<td>many, numerous, a high number of, a significant number of</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>a few</td>
<td>some, several, a small number of, a limited amount of</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="task-specific-vocabulary" class="level3" data-number="1.1.10">
<h3 data-number="1.1.10" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="task-specific-vocabulary"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.10</span> Task-Specific Vocabulary</h3>
</section>
<section id="line-graphs" class="level3" data-number="1.1.11">
<h3 data-number="1.1.11" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="line-graphs"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.11</span> 📈 Line Graphs</h3>
<ul>
<li>increased gradually → rose steadily</li>
<li>dropped sharply → declined dramatically</li>
<li>fluctuated slightly → experienced minor variations</li>
<li>showed an upward trend → followed a rising pattern</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="bar-charts" class="level3" data-number="1.1.12">
<h3 data-number="1.1.12" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bar-charts"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.12</span> 📊 Bar Charts</h3>
<ul>
<li>highest value → peak, top point, maximum</li>
<li>lowest value → minimum, bottom value</li>
<li>category → group, classification, segment</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="pie-charts" class="level3" data-number="1.1.13">
<h3 data-number="1.1.13" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pie-charts"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.13</span> 🥧 Pie Charts</h3>
<ul>
<li>slice → segment, portion, share, fraction</li>
<li>largest share → dominant proportion, biggest segment</li>
<li>equally distributed → evenly divided, shared equally</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="maps" class="level3" data-number="1.1.14">
<h3 data-number="1.1.14" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="maps"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.14</span> 🗺️ Maps</h3>
<ul>
<li>built → constructed, developed, established</li>
<li>removed → demolished, cleared, replaced</li>
<li>added → introduced, expanded, inserted</li>
<li>turned into → converted into, transformed into</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="process-diagrams" class="level3" data-number="1.1.15">
<h3 data-number="1.1.15" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="process-diagrams"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.15</span> ⚙️ Process Diagrams</h3>
<ul>
<li>step → stage, phase, level</li>
<li>begin → commence, initiate, start with</li>
<li>end → finish, conclude, result in</li>
<li>goes through → undergoes, passes through, transitions through</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="academic-vocabulary" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="academic-vocabulary"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> Academic vocabulary</h2>
<section id="understand-meaning-use" class="level3" data-number="1.2.1">
<h3 data-number="1.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="understand-meaning-use"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.1</span> Understand Meaning &amp; Use</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 28%">
<col style="width: 54%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Phrase</th>
<th>Meaning</th>
<th>Example Sentence</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>strong preference</strong></td>
<td>clearly like one thing more than others</td>
<td><em>Male students showed a strong preference for engineering.</em></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>more inclined toward</strong></td>
<td>tend to choose or favor something</td>
<td><em>Female students were more inclined toward education.</em></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>relatively balanced</strong></td>
<td>nearly equal or similar</td>
<td><em>Participation in social sciences was relatively balanced between genders.</em></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="make-your-own-sentences" class="level3" data-number="1.2.2">
<h3 data-number="1.2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="make-your-own-sentences"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.2</span> Make Your Own Sentences</h3>
<ul>
<li><em>I have a strong preference for studying at night rather than in the morning.</em></li>
<li><em>Teenagers today are more inclined toward using smartphones for entertainment.</em></li>
<li><em>The use of bicycles and cars in this city is relatively balanced</em>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="practice" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Practice</h1>
<section id="rewrite-introduction" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rewrite-introduction"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Rewrite Introduction</h2>
<section id="rewrite" class="level3" data-number="2.1.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rewrite"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.1</span> Rewrite</h3>
<p><em>The table shows how many hours people of different age use internet for fun and for work each week.</em> My answer: The table illustrates the number of hours people of various ages use the internet for leisure and for professional each week.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Explanation</th>
<th>Correction</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“for professional”</strong></td>
<td>“Professional” is an adjective. You need a <strong>noun</strong> here.</td>
<td>Use <strong>“for work”</strong> or <strong>“for professional purposes”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“people of various ages”</strong></td>
<td>Good, but can be made more natural.</td>
<td>Try <strong>“people in different age groups”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“use the internet”</strong></td>
<td>Fine, but could be made more academic.</td>
<td>Try <strong>“spend online”</strong> or <strong>“use the internet for…”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Word order</strong></td>
<td>Ending on “each week” is okay, but it reads better earlier.</td>
<td>Rearrange for fluency.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The table illustrates the number of hours per week that people in different age groups spend online for leisure and work-related activities. Or: The table provides data on the weekly hours spent online by people of various age group, categorized by leisure and professional purposes.</p>
<p>Rewrite: The bar chart shows the percentage of households in four different income levels that had internet access in 2010 and 2020. I write: The bar chart illustrates the distribution of households in four various income levels that had internet access in 2010 and 2020.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 50%">
<col style="width: 50%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Correction</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“four various”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Redundant. Use either “four” or “various” — not both. → ✅ “four different” or just “four”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“distribution of households”</strong></td>
<td>✅ Okay, but could be clearer — this chart shows <strong>percentages</strong>, not the count or physical distribution. Try <strong>“percentage of households”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Grammar and flow</strong></td>
<td>Sentence is understandable but can be more formal and concise</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The bar chart illustrates the percentage of households across four income levels that had access to the internet in 2010 and 2020. Or: The bar chart compares the proportion of households with internet access in four income groups for the years 2010 and 2020.</p>
</section>
<section id="rewrite-1" class="level3" data-number="2.1.2">
<h3 data-number="2.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rewrite-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.2</span> Rewrite</h3>
<p><em>The line graph shows the number of international students enrolled in Canadian universities between 2005 and 2020, broken down by region of origin.</em></p>
<p>The line graph illustrates how many international students enrolled in Canadian universities between 2005 and 2020, categorize by area of origin.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Explanation</th>
<th>Correction</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“how many international students”</strong></td>
<td>Okay, but more formal: <strong>“the number of international students”</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“categorize”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Wrong form → should be <strong>“categorized”</strong> (past participle in passive structure)</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“area of origin”</strong></td>
<td>Acceptable, but <strong>“region of origin”</strong> or <strong>“by region”</strong> is more common in academic writing</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Flow</strong></td>
<td>Combine ideas more smoothly with a formal tone</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The line graph illustrates the number of international students enrolled in Canadian universities from 2005 to 2020, categorized by region of origin. Or: The line graph presents data on international student enrollment in Canadian universities over a 15-year period, broken down by region of origin.</p>
</section>
<section id="rewrite-2" class="level3" data-number="2.1.3">
<h3 data-number="2.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rewrite-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.3</span> Rewrite</h3>
<p><em>The pie charts show the proportion of energy produced from five different sources in a European country in 1980 and 2020.</em> I write: The pie charts illustrate the percentage of energy made from five different sources in a European country in 1980 and 2020.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Explanation</th>
<th>Fix</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“energy made from”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Informal/awkward for Task 1. Use <strong>“produced from”</strong> or <strong>“generated by”</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“in a European country”</strong></td>
<td>✅ This is fine and accurate</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“five different sources”</strong></td>
<td>✅ Good — “five sources” is enough, but “different” is okay for emphasis</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The pie charts illustrate the proportion of energy generated from five sources in a European country in the years 1980 and 2020. Or: The two pie charts compare the share of energy production by five distinct sources in a European country in 1980 and 2020.</p>
</section>
<section id="rewrite-3" class="level3" data-number="2.1.4">
<h3 data-number="2.1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rewrite-3"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.4</span> Rewrite</h3>
<p><em>The table displays the average monthly income (in USD) for workers in three different sectors in five countries.</em> I write: The table illustrates the salary of workers in three different sectors in five countries.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 69%">
<col style="width: 9%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Comment</th>
<th>Suggested Fix</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“illustrates”</strong></td>
<td>✅ Good verb for visuals</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“the salary”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Slightly vague → “salary” is better expressed as <strong>“average monthly income”</strong> to match the task</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“three different sectors”</strong></td>
<td>✅ Fine, though “various sectors” or “economic sectors” may be more formal</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“in five countries”</strong></td>
<td>✅ Good — you could also say <strong>“across five countries”</strong> for variety</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The table illustrates the average monthly income of workers <strong>across three sectors</strong> in five different countries. Or: The table presents data on the <strong>average monthly earnings</strong> of <strong>employees</strong> in three occupational sectors across five countries.</p>
</section>
<section id="rewrite-4" class="level3" data-number="2.1.5">
<h3 data-number="2.1.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rewrite-4"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.5</span> Rewrite</h3>
<p><em>The line graph shows the percentage of the population aged 65 and over in Japan, Sweden, and the USA from 1940 to 2040.</em> I write: The line graph illustrates the proportion of the people who over 65 and over in Japan, Sweden, and the US between 1940 and 2040.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Explanation</th>
<th>Fix</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“the people who over 65 and over”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Grammar mistake. You need: “people <strong>aged 65 and over</strong>”</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“the proportion of the people”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Too wordy. Use <strong>“the proportion of people”</strong> (no “the” before “people”)</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“US” vs “USA”</strong></td>
<td>✅ Both are fine. Choose one and stay consistent</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“between 1940 and 2040”</strong></td>
<td>✅ Correct and clear</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The line graph illustrates the proportion of people aged 65 and over in Japan, Sweden, and the USA between 1940 and 2040. Or: The line graph compares the percentage of the population aged 65 and above in Japan, Sweden, and the United States from 1940 to 2040.</p>
<p>I write overview:</p>
<p>While the number of USA senior citizen is slightly increase in throughout the period, that figure of Sweden and Japan are reduce on that time.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Explanation</th>
<th>Correction</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“number of USA senior citizen”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Wrong form: should be <strong>“percentage of senior citizens in the USA”</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“is slightly increase”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Incorrect verb form: should be <strong>“increases slightly”</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“are reduce”</strong></td>
<td>❌ Incorrect verb form again: should be <strong>“decline”</strong>, but actually this is <strong>factually wrong</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Trend accuracy</strong></td>
<td>❌ In fact, Japan and Sweden both <strong>increase overall</strong>, not decrease</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: Overall, the proportion of elderly people increased in all three countries throughout the period, with Japan showing the most dramatic growth after 2020. Or: In general, all three countries experienced a rise in the percentage of people aged 65 and above, with Japan’s elderly population rising sharply after 2020. ## Overview</p>
<p>An overview I write: Overall, it is clear that people spend the time on the internet for professional purposes most in their 20s, while their time for online leisure is largest when teens.</p>
<p>Better:</p>
<p>Overall, it is clear that internet use for work peaks among people in their 20s, while leisure-related usage is highest among teenagers.</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Avoid exact figures</strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Focus on trends, not facts</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Use <strong>comparative language</strong>: <em>most common</em>, <em>highest</em>, <em>dominant</em>, <em>peak</em>, etc.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="full-paragraph-1" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-paragraph-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Full paragraph 1</h2>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/introduction-overview/Pasted image 20250625093819.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>My write: The bar chart illustrates the number of people who spend time in Dover and Troy in 4 seasons. From an overall perspective, Dover has more people visiting in the two end seasons of the year, while Troy experiences a tourist trend in summer and fall.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 45%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Problem</th>
<th>Suggestion</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“who spend time”</strong></td>
<td>Slightly vague — use more formal and precise phrasing</td>
<td>“who visited” or “who traveled to”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“in 4 seasons”</strong></td>
<td>Informal and unclear</td>
<td>“across the four seasons” or “during spring, summer, autumn, and winter”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“two end seasons of the year”</strong></td>
<td>Unnatural phrasing</td>
<td>Use: “in winter and autumn” or “in the colder seasons”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“tourist trend”</strong></td>
<td>Vague expression</td>
<td>Use: “a peak in tourist numbers” or “more visitors”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The bar chart illustrates the number of tourists who traveled to Dover and Troy during the four seasons. Overall, Dover attracted more visitors in the colder seasons, while Troy saw higher tourist numbers in summer and autumn.</p>
<p>To express the upward seasonal trend of Dover tourism: - The number of visitors to Dover increases steadily from spring to winter. - Dover experienced a consistent rise in tourist numbers throughout the year. - In Dover, visitor numbers gradually grew across the seasons, peaking in winter. - Tourism in Dover followed an upward trend, with each season attracting more visitors than the previous one.</p>
<p>To overview: Overall, Dover experienced a steady increase in visitor numbers from spring to winter, while Troy attracted the most tourists during the summer and autumn seasons.</p>
<p><em>The pie charts below show enrollment in different fields of study at a particular university.</em></p>
<p><em>Summarise the information by selecting and reporting the main features, and make comparisons where relevant.</em> <img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/introduction-overview/Pasted image 20250625100948.png" class="img-fluid">The pie charts illustrate the proportion of enrollment in various field of study at Clydesdale university categorized by gender. From an overall perspective, Men keen on engineering and social sciences, while women students like to study education and humanities.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 16%">
<col style="width: 43%">
<col style="width: 39%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Issue</th>
<th>Problem</th>
<th>Suggested Fix</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“various field of study”</strong></td>
<td>Grammar: “field” → plural form</td>
<td>“various <strong>fields</strong> of study”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“at Clydesdale university”</strong></td>
<td>Capitalization</td>
<td>“Clydesdale <strong>University</strong>”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“Men keen on…”</strong></td>
<td>Missing verb and informal</td>
<td>“<strong>Men are more likely to enroll in</strong> engineering and social sciences”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>“like to study”</strong></td>
<td>Informal</td>
<td>“<strong>tend to choose</strong>” or “<strong>prefer to study</strong>” is more academic</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>“women students”</strong></td>
<td>OK, but better phrased as “<strong>female students</strong>” or just “<strong>women</strong>” in context</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The pie charts illustrate the proportion of students enrolled in various fields of study at Clydesdale University, categorized by gender. Overall, male students were more likely to choose engineering and social sciences, while female students tend to prefer education and humanities. Or: The two pie charts illustrate the percentage of male and female students enrolled in four academic fields - Social Sciences, Humanities, Education, and Engineering - at Clydesdale University. Overall, male students showed a <strong>strong preference</strong> for Engineering, while female students were <strong>more inclined toward</strong> Humanities and education. Notably, Social science was the only field with <strong>relatively balanced participation</strong> between genders.</p>
<p>The table below shows the number of hours per week people of different ages spend using the internet for different types of activities.</p>
<p>Summarize the information by selecting and reporting the main features, and make comparisons where relevant. Hours per week spent on the internet, by age</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>teens</th>
<th>20s</th>
<th>30s</th>
<th>40s</th>
<th>50s</th>
<th>60s+</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>studying/working</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>leisure activities</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>my write: The table illustrates the hour per week people of various age range online for professional and leisure purposes. From an overall perspective, people spend their online time for professional soar up in 20s and decline while the figure of leisures activities down in their 40s.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 15%">
<col style="width: 35%">
<col style="width: 49%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Issue</strong></th>
<th><strong>Error</strong></th>
<th><strong>Suggested Fix</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Word form</td>
<td>“the hour per week”</td>
<td>Use plural: <strong>“the number of hours per week”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Word choice / grammar</td>
<td>“people of various age range”</td>
<td>Use: <strong>“people in various age groups”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Missing verb</td>
<td>“people… online for professional and leisure purposes”</td>
<td>Add: <strong>“spend time online for professional and leisure purposes”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Word choice / expression</td>
<td>“soar up in 20s”</td>
<td>Use academic tone: <strong>“peaks in their 20s”</strong> or <strong>“is highest in their 20s”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Verb form</td>
<td>“the figure of leisures activities down”</td>
<td>Correct form: <strong>“leisure activity time decreases”</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Plural error</td>
<td>“leisures activities”</td>
<td>Use: <strong>“leisure activities”</strong> (uncountable noun)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Clarity</td>
<td>Sentence structure (2nd sentence unclear and rushed)</td>
<td>Split into two clear comparisons with linking phrases</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Better: The table illustrates the number of hours per week that people in different age groups using the internet for professional and leisure purposes. Overall, internet use for professional reasons peaks in the 20s and declines with age, while time spent on leisure activities falls in middle age but rises again in older groups. Other: The table displays the average number of hours per week that people across six age groups spend using the internet for two main purposes: studying/working and leisure activities. Overall, internet use for studying or working peaks in the 20s age group and gradually declines with age, while leisure-related usage remains more stable across age group, with only moderate variation. Notably, teenagers spend more time online for leisure than for academic or work purposes, in contrast to all other all groups.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 50%">
<col style="width: 50%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Criterion</strong></th>
<th><strong>Strength</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Task Achievement</strong></td>
<td>✅ Fully covers the main trends without listing data. Clearly highlights a notable contrast (teens vs.&nbsp;others).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Coherence &amp; Cohesion</strong></td>
<td>✅ Well-organized with smooth transitions (<em>“Overall,” “Notably,” “in contrast”</em>)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Lexical Resource</strong></td>
<td>✅ Sophisticated phrases: <em>“remains more stable,” “moderate variation,” “peaks,” “gradually declines”</em></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Grammar Range</strong></td>
<td>✅ Great range: passive, adverbs of degree (<em>“gradually,” “more stable”</em>) and parallel structures</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>“Internet use for studying or working” → could be rephrased as “professional or academic purposes” in future writing for variation.</p>
<p>“Moderate variation” → you could vary this with “slight fluctuation” or “subtle differences”.</p>
<p>Rockingham, transportation</p>
<p>2005 work at home 10%, walk 5%, bicycle 5%, bus 15%, carpool 25%, car (alone) 50%. 2015 work at home 15%, walk 5%, bicycle 10%, bus 15%, carpool 20%, car (alone) 50%.</p>
<p>The pie chart illustrates the proportion of six types of transportation to work of employees in Rockingham in 2005 and 2015. Overall, although the decline in 2015, cars is still the highest proportion type of vehicle to work in two times, while bicycle and people work from home are likely increase.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 13%">
<col style="width: 32%">
<col style="width: 54%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Issue</strong></th>
<th><strong>Error</strong></th>
<th><strong>Suggested Fix</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Article usage</td>
<td>“the pie chart” (okay) but can be plural for 2 years</td>
<td>“<strong>The pie charts illustrate</strong>…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Phrasing</td>
<td>“transportation to work of employees”</td>
<td>“<strong>commuting methods used by employees</strong>” or “<strong>transportation methods for commuting</strong>”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Grammar</td>
<td>“although the decline in 2015” (fragment)</td>
<td>“<strong>Although there was a decline in 2015</strong>,”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Subject-verb agreement</td>
<td>“cars is”</td>
<td>“<strong>cars remain</strong>” or “<strong>the use of cars remains</strong>”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Clarity</td>
<td>“the highest proportion type of vehicle”</td>
<td>“<strong>the most common mode of transportation</strong>”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Expression</td>
<td>“in two times” (unnatural)</td>
<td>“<strong>in both years</strong>”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Verb form</td>
<td>“are likely increase”</td>
<td>“<strong>increased</strong>” or “<strong>saw an increase</strong>”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Fix</p>
<pre><code>The pie charts illustrate the proportion of six types of transportation method for commuting in Rockingham in 2005 and 2015.
Overall, although there was a decline in 2015, the use of cars remains the most common mode of transportation in both years. Meanwhile, the proportions of bicycle use and working from home increased. </code></pre>
<p>Other The two pie charts illustrate how employees in Rockingham commuted to work using six different transport methods in 2005 and 2015. Overall, although the proportion of people commuting by car alone remained the highest in both years, its usage declined slightly in 2015. At the same time, bicycle use and working from home became more common, while walking and bus usage remained stable.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Purpose</th>
<th>Phrase Examples</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Introduction</td>
<td>“The chart illustrates…” / “The graph presents…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Overview intro</td>
<td>“Overall,” / “In general,” / “It is clear that…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Showing contrast</td>
<td>“While…” / “Although…” / “By contrast…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Highlight trend</td>
<td>“…remained the most popular” / “…saw a rise in…”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>“The chart below shows the percentage of households in different income groups that had internet access in a European country between 2005 and 2020.”</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Year</th>
<th>Low Income</th>
<th>Middle Income</th>
<th>High Income</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2005</td>
<td>10%</td>
<td>40%</td>
<td>75%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2010</td>
<td>25%</td>
<td>60%</td>
<td>90%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>2015</td>
<td>40%</td>
<td>75%</td>
<td>95%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2020</td>
<td>60%</td>
<td>85%</td>
<td>98%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/introduction-overview/Pasted image 20250626225143.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>My write The chart illustrates the proportion of households various income group that had access to internet in a European country in 3 categories between 2005 and 2020. Overall, all those income group saw a increase in internet access. Meanwhile, Low Income group still have relatively low percentage of internet access comparing to middle income and high income.</p>
<p>People from highest income class began the period with already high percentage internet access, with 75% in 2005. After High Income class’s internet access saw a significant rose to 90% in 2010, their use of internet increased steadily to 95% in 2015 after end up with 98% in 2020.</p>
<p>The percentage of middle income’s internet access begin the period with 4 times the figure of low income people, with 40% and 10% respectively. The period from 2010 and 2015 experienced the rapidly growth from 60% to 75% of middle income and 25% to 40% of low income. Otherwise, in the end of the period, the proportion of middle income class using internet steadily went up to 85%, while that figure of low income group soared up to 60%.</p>
</section>
<section id="overall-band-score-6.0" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overall-band-score-6.0"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> 🟩 <strong>Overall Band Score: 6.0</strong></h2>
</section>
<section id="coherence-and-cohesion-6.0" class="level2" data-number="2.4">
<h2 data-number="2.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="coherence-and-cohesion-6.0"><span class="header-section-number">2.4</span> 🟨 <strong>Coherence and Cohesion: 6.0</strong></h2>
<section id="analysis" class="level3" data-number="2.4.1">
<h3 data-number="2.4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis"><span class="header-section-number">2.4.1</span> ✅ Analysis:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>☑ Structure your answers in logical paragraphs</p></li>
<li><p>☑ One main idea per paragraph</p></li>
<li><p>☑ Include an introduction and conclusion <em>(short summary provided at the beginning)</em></p></li>
<li><p>☑ Support main points with an explanation and then an example <em>(some explanation is there but lacking clarity)</em></p></li>
<li><p>☑ Use cohesive linking words accurately and appropriately *(e.g., “overall”, “meanwhile”, “otherwise”)</p></li>
<li><p>❌ Vary your linking phrases using synonyms <em>(very limited linking variety)</em></p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Feedback:</strong><br>
The response is logically organized, but transitions like “otherwise” and “meanwhile” are sometimes used awkwardly. Some comparisons are a bit unclear due to sentence structure.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="lexical-resource-6.0" class="level2" data-number="2.5">
<h2 data-number="2.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lexical-resource-6.0"><span class="header-section-number">2.5</span> 🟨 <strong>Lexical Resource: 6.0</strong></h2>
<section id="analysis-1" class="level3" data-number="2.5.1">
<h3 data-number="2.5.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.5.1</span> ✅ Analysis:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>☑ Try to vary your vocabulary using accurate synonyms</p></li>
<li><p>? Use less common question-specific words that accurately convey meaning</p></li>
<li><p>❌ Check your work for spelling and word formation mistakes</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Feedback:</strong><br>
Some vocabulary is appropriate (“proportion”, “income group”, “steadily”), but others are repetitive or awkward (“soared up to”, “rapidly growth” → should be “rapid growth”). Use more precise and formal words like <em>“saw a sharp rise”</em> instead of “soared up”.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="grammatical-range-and-accuracy-5.5" class="level2" data-number="2.6">
<h2 data-number="2.6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="grammatical-range-and-accuracy-5.5"><span class="header-section-number">2.6</span> 🟨 <strong>Grammatical Range and Accuracy: 5.5</strong></h2>
<section id="analysis-2" class="level3" data-number="2.6.1">
<h3 data-number="2.6.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.6.1</span> ✅ Analysis:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>☑ Use a variety of complex and simple sentences</p></li>
<li><p>❌ Check your writing for errors</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Feedback:</strong><br>
The essay contains <strong>numerous grammatical errors</strong> that affect clarity:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>“saw a increase” → “saw an increase”</p></li>
<li><p>“various income group” → “various income groups”</p></li>
<li><p>“internet access begin” → “internet access began”</p></li>
<li><p>“rose to 90%… end up with 98%” → “and ended up at 98%”</p></li>
<li><p>Article and plural noun errors appear frequently.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Use more complex sentence structures and correct verb tenses.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="task-achievement-6.0" class="level2" data-number="2.7">
<h2 data-number="2.7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="task-achievement-6.0"><span class="header-section-number">2.7</span> 🟨 <strong>Task Achievement: 6.0</strong></h2>
<section id="analysis-3" class="level3" data-number="2.7.1">
<h3 data-number="2.7.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-3"><span class="header-section-number">2.7.1</span> ✅ Analysis:</h3>
<ul>
<li><p>☑ Answer all parts of the question</p></li>
<li><p>☑ Present relevant ideas</p></li>
<li><p>? Fully explain these ideas</p></li>
<li><p>? Support ideas with relevant, specific examples</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Feedback:</strong><br>
The response covers all key points and compares groups, but some <strong>comparisons lack clarity</strong> and <strong>phrasing is occasionally confusing</strong>. Numbers are mostly used well, though a few sentences are hard to follow.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="suggestions-to-improve" class="level2" data-number="2.8">
<h2 data-number="2.8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="suggestions-to-improve"><span class="header-section-number">2.8</span> 🔹 <strong>Suggestions to Improve:</strong></h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Work on grammatical accuracy—especially <strong>articles</strong>, <strong>plural nouns</strong>, and <strong>verb forms</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p>Use more precise academic phrases:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Instead of: “soared up to 60%” → say “rose significantly to 60%”</p></li>
<li><p>Instead of: “with already high percentage internet access” → “already had a high level of internet access”</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Vary your linking phrases:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>“In comparison”</p></li>
<li><p>“Similarly”</p></li>
<li><p>“By contrast”</p></li>
<li><p>“Over the period”</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="high-band-vocabulary-from-this-topic" class="level2" data-number="2.9">
<h2 data-number="2.9" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="high-band-vocabulary-from-this-topic"><span class="header-section-number">2.9</span> ✅ <strong>High-Band Vocabulary from This Topic:</strong></h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Proportion of households</p></li>
<li><p>Income brackets (or income groups)</p></li>
<li><p>Internet penetration</p></li>
<li><p>Rose steadily / increased significantly</p></li>
<li><p>Remained relatively low / high</p></li>
<li><p>Witnessed growth</p></li>
<li><p>Peaked at / bottomed out at</p></li>
<li><p>Closing gap between groups</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Better: The table illustrates the percentage of households with internet access across the income groups-low, middle, and high-in a European country from 2005 to 2020.</p>
<p>Overall, internet access increased in all income categories over the 15-year period. However, households in the high-income group consistently had the highest access, while low-income households remained significantly behind.</p>
<p>In 2005, 80% of high-income households had internet access, compared to 35% of middle-income and only 5% of low-income households. By 2010, these figures rose to 92%, 55%, and 15% respectively, with the gap between groups still substantial.</p>
<p>The most notable growth occurred between 2010 and 2020. High-income households saw a steady rise, reaching 99% by the end of the period. Middle-income homes increased from 55% to 82%, while the low-income group experienced the most dramatic rise-from just 15% in 2010 to 45% in 2020. Despite this improvement, internet access remained significantly lower for the lowest income group.</p>
<p>The table shows the proportion of households with access to the internet across the income groups-low, middle, and high- in a European country from 2005 to 2020.</p>
<p>From an overall perspective, internet access increased in all income classes over the 15-year period. Meanwhile, the high-income group households consistently had the highest access, while low-income households remained significantly behind.</p>
<p>In 2005, internet access was already high among the top income group, with 80% of households connected. This figure increased steadily to 92% in 2010, then to 97% in 2015, before reaching 99% in 2020. –Otherwise–In contrast, the middle- and low-income groups began the period at 35% and 5%, respectively, highlighting a significant digital divide at the beginning.</p>
<p>Over the 15-year period, both middle- and low-income groups saw significant growth in internet access. For middle-income households, the figure rose from 35% in 2005 to 55% in 2010, then jumped to 70% in 2015, and reached 82% by 2020. Although low-income households also showed improvement-from just 5% in 2005 to 45% in 2020-their access remained considerably lower than the other groups throughout the period.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/introduction-overview/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IELTS synonyms - phrases by topic</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/synonyms/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="people-gender" class="level2" data-number="1">

<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Word</th>
<th>Synonyms / Phrases</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>men</td>
<td>males, male passengers, male visitors</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>women</td>
<td>females, female passengers, female users</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>people</td>
<td>individuals, users, participants, members of the public</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>passengers</td>
<td>riders, commuters, travelers</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="time-expressions" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-expressions"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> 2. Time Expressions</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Word</th>
<th>Synonyms / Alternatives</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>weekdays</td>
<td>during the week, on working days</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>weekends</td>
<td>Saturday and Sunday, non-working days</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>during the week</td>
<td>over the course of the week, on weekdays</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>spend time</td>
<td>allocate time, dedicate time, devote time</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="quantity-number" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quantity-number"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> 3. Quantity / Number</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Word</th>
<th>Synonyms / Expressions</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>the number of</td>
<td>the amount of, the volume of, the total of</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>how many</td>
<td>the quantity of, the total number of</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>various</td>
<td>different, diverse, a range of</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="types-categories" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-categories"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> 4. Types / Categories</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Word</th>
<th>Synonyms / Phrases</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>different types</td>
<td>various kinds, categories, groups</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>kind</td>
<td>category, type, form, variation</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>area</td>
<td>region, zone, sector, location, district</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="regions-locations" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="regions-locations"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> 5. Regions / Locations</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Word</th>
<th>Synonyms / Phrases</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>region</td>
<td>area, district, locality, zone</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>build</td>
<td>construct, develop, establish</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>in 2/3/4/5</td>
<td>in second/third/fourth/fifth region/zone</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="common-verbs-for-data" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="common-verbs-for-data"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> 6. Common Verbs for Data</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Word</th>
<th>Synonyms / IELTS usage</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>visit</td>
<td>travel to, go to, attend</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>use</td>
<td>access, make use of, take advantage of</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>ride</td>
<td>board, commute by, travel on</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>spend time</td>
<td>engage in, be involved in, dedicate time to</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="grammar-word-form-notes" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="grammar-word-form-notes"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Grammar / Word Form Notes</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>“The number of”</strong> + plural noun → <strong>singular verb</strong>
<ul>
<li><em>The number of passengers <strong>is</strong> increasing.</em></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>“A number of”</strong> + plural noun → <strong>plural verb</strong>
<ul>
<li><em>A number of people <strong>are</strong> waiting.</em></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Use <strong>“during”</strong> + noun phrase:
<ul>
<li><em>during the week</em>, <em>during the evening</em>, <em>during the morning rush hour</em></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/synonyms/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>University Enrollment</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/uni-enroll/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>The pie charts below show enrollment in different fields of study at a particular university.</em></p>
<p><em>Summarise the information by selecting and reporting the main features, and make comparisons where relevant.</em> <img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/uni-enroll/Pasted image 20250625100948.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The two pie charts illustrate the percentage of male and female students enrolled in four academic fields - Social Sciences, Humanities, Education, and Engineering - at Clydesdale University. Overall, male students showed a strong preference for Engineering, while female students were more inclined toward Humanities and education. Social science was the only field with relatively balanced participation between genders.</p>
<p>Engineering was the dominant choices for male students, comprising 45% of their total enrollment, more than twice the proportion of females in the same field (20%). In constrast, only 10% of men chose Humanities, while this subject attracted 30% of women - three times higher. Similarly, Education accounted for 35% of female enrollment, compared to just 20% for men.</p>
<p>The only discipline where the gender gap was moderate was Social Sciences. While a quarter of men were enrolled in this field, women followed closely behind at 15%. Although a difference exists, this subject showed the least contrast in gender representation.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/uni-enroll/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>stumble</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/stumble/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="meanings-of-stumble" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Meanings of stumble</h1>
<section id="to-trip-or-momentarily-lose-balance-while-walking" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="to-trip-or-momentarily-lose-balance-while-walking"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> To trip or momentarily lose balance while walking</h2>
<p>Physical/ Literal use - Meaning: To hit your foot against something and nearly fall. - Example: - She <strong>stumbled</strong> on the uneven pavement and almost fell. - I was walking in the dark and <strong>stumbled over</strong> a rock.</p>
</section>
<section id="to-make-a-mistake-or-pause-while-speaking-or-reading" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="to-make-a-mistake-or-pause-while-speaking-or-reading"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> To make a mistake or pause while speaking or reading</h2>
<p>Speaking / Communication use - Meaning: To speak with hesitation or errors - Examples: - He <strong>stumbled over</strong> his words during the presentation. - I <strong>stumbled</strong> when trying to pronounce that complex name.</p>
</section>
<section id="to-encounter-a-problem-or-difficulty" class="level2" data-number="1.3">
<h2 data-number="1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="to-encounter-a-problem-or-difficulty"><span class="header-section-number">1.3</span> To encounter a problem or difficulty</h2>
<p>Metaphorical / General use - Meaning: To experience a temporary failure or obstacle. - Example: - Their business plan <strong>stumbled</strong> at the funding stage. - She <strong>stumbled</strong> in her first attempt but learned from it.</p>
</section>
<section id="to-find-something-by-chance" class="level2" data-number="1.4">
<h2 data-number="1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="to-find-something-by-chance"><span class="header-section-number">1.4</span> To find something by chance</h2>
<p>Discovery / Unexpected use - Meaning: To come across something accidentally - Common form: stumble upon / stumble across - Example: - I <strong>stumbled upon</strong> an old photo album in the attic. - He <strong>stumbled across</strong> a great little cafe while walking downtown.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-mistake-or-slip-up-as-a-noun" class="level2" data-number="1.5">
<h2 data-number="1.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-mistake-or-slip-up-as-a-noun"><span class="header-section-number">1.5</span> A mistake or slip-up (as a noun)</h2>
<p>Noun form - Meaning: A small error or setback - Example: - It was just a minor <strong>stumble</strong> - she quickly recovered. - His early <strong>stumbles</strong> didn’t stop him from succeeding. # Common collocations:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Phrase / Collocation</th>
<th>Meaning or Use</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>stumble upon an idea</td>
<td>Discover unexpectedly</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>stumble through a speech</td>
<td>Struggle while speaking</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>a stumble in performance</td>
<td>A drop or dip in quality</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>stumble across a solution</td>
<td>Accidentally find an answer</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>stumble over my words</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
</section>
<section id="other-example-use-in-ielts-exam" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Other example use in IELTS Exam</h1>
<section id="speaking" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speaking"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Speaking</h2>
<section id="have-you-ever-given-a-public-speech" class="level3" data-number="2.1.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="have-you-ever-given-a-public-speech"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.1</span> Have you ever given a public speech ?</h3>
<p>Yes, I gave a short speech at my friend’s wedding last year. I was nervous, and I <strong>stumbled over</strong> my words a few times at the beginning, but once I relaxed, it went quite well.</p>
</section>
<section id="describe-a-time-you-made-a-mistake-but-learned-something-from-it." class="level3" data-number="2.1.2">
<h3 data-number="2.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="describe-a-time-you-made-a-mistake-but-learned-something-from-it."><span class="header-section-number">2.1.2</span> Describe a time you made a mistake but learned something from it.</h3>
<p>A few years ago, I tried to start a small online business. At first, I didn’t know much about marketing, so I made some poor decisions. It was definitely a <strong>stumble</strong>, especially when I ran out of budget. But I learned a lot about planning and now I’m much more confident when launching something new.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-is-failure-important-in-personal-development" class="level3" data-number="2.1.3">
<h3 data-number="2.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-is-failure-important-in-personal-development"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.3</span> Why is failure important in personal development?</h3>
<p>I think failure teaches us more than success sometimes. Every <strong>stumble</strong> helps us understand what went wrong and how we can improve. It also builds resilience, which is important in both academic and professional life</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="writing" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="writing"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Writing</h2>
<section id="some-people-believe-that-mistakes-are-essential-for-learning.-to-what-extent-do-you-agree" class="level3" data-number="2.2.1">
<h3 data-number="2.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="some-people-believe-that-mistakes-are-essential-for-learning.-to-what-extent-do-you-agree"><span class="header-section-number">2.2.1</span> Some people believe that mistakes are essential for learning. To what extent do you agree?</h3>
<p>Whiles mistakes may seem discouraging at first, each <strong>stumbles</strong> can lead to growth, as it highlights areas that require further attention and improvement.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-role-of-discovery-and-exploration-in-education." class="level3" data-number="2.2.2">
<h3 data-number="2.2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-role-of-discovery-and-exploration-in-education."><span class="header-section-number">2.2.2</span> The role of discovery and exploration in education.</h3>
<p>Many breakthrough in science and innovation occur when individuals <strong>stumble upon</strong> new ideas while exploring unrelated topics, showing that curiosity can lead to unexpected learning.</p>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/stumble/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Listening practice - mistake log</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/listening-practice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="cambridge-ielts-13---listening-test-3" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Cambridge IELTS 13 - listening test 3</h1>
<ul>
<li>Date: 27/06/2025</li>
<li>Total Score: 35/40</li>
</ul>
<section id="ielts-listening-breakdown-full-report" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ielts-listening-breakdown-full-report"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> IELTS Listening Breakdown – Full Report</h2>
<section id="table-1-section-1-personal-information-inquiry" class="level3" data-number="1.1.1">
<h3 data-number="1.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-1-section-1-personal-information-inquiry"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.1</span> 📘 Table 1: Section 1 – Personal Information Inquiry</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 21%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Question Type</strong></th>
<th><strong>Correct</strong></th>
<th><strong>Incorrect</strong></th>
<th><strong>Skipped</strong></th>
<th><strong>Accuracy</strong></th>
<th><strong>Question Numbers</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Note/Form Completion</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100.00%</td>
<td>1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Asking for Information (Listening Theme)</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100.00%</td>
<td>1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Total</strong></td>
<td><strong>10</strong></td>
<td><strong>0</strong></td>
<td><strong>0</strong></td>
<td><strong>100.00%</strong></td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="table-2-section-2-public-speech-directions" class="level3" data-number="1.1.2">
<h3 data-number="1.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-2-section-2-public-speech-directions"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.2</span> 📗 Table 2: Section 2 – Public Speech &amp; Directions</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 34%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 21%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Question Type</strong></th>
<th><strong>Correct</strong></th>
<th><strong>Incorrect</strong></th>
<th><strong>Skipped</strong></th>
<th><strong>Accuracy</strong></th>
<th><strong>Question Numbers</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Matching</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100.00%</td>
<td>11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Multiple Choice</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>75.00%</td>
<td>17, 18, 19, 20</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Giving a Speech at an Event (Listening Theme)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>90.00%</td>
<td>11–20</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Total</strong></td>
<td><strong>9</strong></td>
<td><strong>1</strong></td>
<td><strong>0</strong></td>
<td><strong>90.00%</strong></td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="table-3-section-3-academic-assignments" class="level3" data-number="1.1.3">
<h3 data-number="1.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-3-section-3-academic-assignments"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.3</span> 📙 Table 3: Section 3 – Academic Assignments</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 34%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 21%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Question Type</strong></th>
<th><strong>Correct</strong></th>
<th><strong>Incorrect</strong></th>
<th><strong>Skipped</strong></th>
<th><strong>Accuracy</strong></th>
<th><strong>Question Numbers</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Matching</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>66.67%</td>
<td>25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Multiple Choice</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>50.00%</td>
<td>21, 22, 23, 24</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Assignments (Listening Theme)</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>60.00%</td>
<td>21–30</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Total</strong></td>
<td><strong>6</strong></td>
<td><strong>4</strong></td>
<td><strong>0</strong></td>
<td><strong>60.00%</strong></td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="table-4-section-4-academic-lecture-on-animals" class="level3" data-number="1.1.4">
<h3 data-number="1.1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-4-section-4-academic-lecture-on-animals"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.4</span> 📕 Table 4: Section 4 – Academic Lecture on Animals</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 28%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 13%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 23%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Question Type</strong></th>
<th><strong>Correct</strong></th>
<th><strong>Incorrect</strong></th>
<th><strong>Skipped</strong></th>
<th><strong>Accuracy</strong></th>
<th><strong>Question Numbers</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Note/Form Completion</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100.00%</td>
<td>31–40</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Topic: Animals</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100.00%</td>
<td>31–40</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Total</strong></td>
<td><strong>10</strong></td>
<td><strong>0</strong></td>
<td><strong>0</strong></td>
<td><strong>100.00%</strong></td>
<td>—</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
</section>
<section id="listening-test-breakdown" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="listening-test-breakdown"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> Listening Test Breakdown</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 30%">
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 14%">
<col style="width: 14%">
<col style="width: 11%">
<col style="width: 17%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Question Type</strong></th>
<th><strong>Correct Answers</strong></th>
<th><strong>Incorrect Answers</strong></th>
<th><strong>Skipped Questions</strong></th>
<th><strong>Accuracy Rate</strong></th>
<th><strong>Wrong Question Numbers</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Multiple Choice</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>62.50%</td>
<td>18, 22, 23</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Note/Form Completion</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100.00%</td>
<td>1–10, 31–40</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Asking for Information (Listening Theme)</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100.00%</td>
<td>1–10</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Assignments (Listening Theme)</td>
<td>6</td>
<td>4</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>60.00%</td>
<td>22, 23, 28, 30</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Animals (Topic-Based)</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>100.00%</td>
<td>31–40</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Matching</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>2</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>83.33%</td>
<td>28, 30</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Giving a Speech at an Event (Listening Theme)</td>
<td>9</td>
<td>1</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>90.00%</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="mistake-log" class="level2" data-number="1.3">
<h2 data-number="1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mistake-log"><span class="header-section-number">1.3</span> Mistake Log</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 0%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 5%">
<col style="width: 40%">
<col style="width: 44%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Q#</th>
<th>Your Answer</th>
<th>Correct Answer</th>
<th>Why You Missed It (Distractor/Paraphrase/Speed/etc.)</th>
<th>Transcript Phrase</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>17</td>
<td>C - too much effort</td>
<td>B - loss of confidence,</td>
<td>You matched the idea of effort to the <strong>first point</strong>, but missed that the speaker is actually talking about <strong>losing belief</strong> and <strong>giving up hope</strong> — that’s about confidence, not effort.<br></td>
<td>“I think people lose interest when they <strong>don’t think they’re making enough progress</strong>. That’s when they <strong>give up hope</strong> and stop believing they’ll ever achieve their goals.<br><br></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>18</td>
<td>E - feeling less successful than others</td>
<td>C - too much effort required</td>
<td>You misread the second part. The speaker says it takes “a lot of determination and hard work” – this clearly points to “too much effort”, not comparing oneself to others.</td>
<td>Also, what people sometimes don’t realize when they <strong>start is that it takes a lot of determination and hard work</strong> to keep training week after week, and lots of people <strong>don’t have that kind of commitment</strong>.”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>23</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>28</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>30</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Q17 – “…when they don’t think they’re making enough progress…give up hope…stop believing…” - these phrases are all about <strong>losing confidence or motivation</strong>. - Correct answer: B - loss of confidence Q18 – “…takes a lot of determination and hard work…lots of people don’t have that kind of commitment.” - this is about the <strong>effort and long-term dedication</strong> needed. - Correct answer C - too much effort required. 💡 Why You Missed It:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>You swapped the ideas: You took “hard work” and applied it to Q17, but that part comes second.</p></li>
<li><p>In IELTS MCQs, the order of the ideas usually matches the order of the questions.</p></li>
<li><p>You may have guessed based on vocabulary, not on exact function and meaning.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Loss of confidence - lose hope too much effort required - too hard to continue feeling less successful than others - comparing yourself to another</p>
<section id="common-paraphrases-for-multiple-choice-options" class="level3" data-number="1.3.1">
<h3 data-number="1.3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="common-paraphrases-for-multiple-choice-options"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.1</span> Common Paraphrases for Multiple-Choice Options</h3>
<section id="a.-lack-of-time" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a.-lack-of-time">🅰️ A. Lack of Time</h4>
<p><strong>🔑 Key Concept:</strong> Not enough time available to do something regularly</p>
<p><strong>🟢 Common Paraphrases in Listening:</strong> - “Don’t have time to…” - “Too busy with work/studies” - “Not enough hours in the day” - “Schedule is too full” - “No free time / hardly any time” - “It’s hard to fit it into my routine”</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="b.-loss-of-confidence" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="b.-loss-of-confidence">🅱️ B. Loss of Confidence</h4>
<p><strong>🔑 Key Concept:</strong> Losing belief in your ability to succeed</p>
<p><strong>🟢 Common Paraphrases:</strong> - “Don’t believe they can do it anymore” - “Gave up hope” - “Think they’ll never succeed” - “Felt like a failure” - “Didn’t trust themselves” - “Started to doubt whether it was possible”</p>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="c.-too-much-effort-required" class="level3" data-number="1.3.2">
<h3 data-number="1.3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="c.-too-much-effort-required"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.2</span> 🅲 C. Too Much Effort Required</h3>
<p><strong>🔑 Key Concept:</strong> It’s too hard or tiring to continue</p>
<p><strong>🟢 Common Paraphrases:</strong> - “Takes a lot of hard work” - “Physically demanding / exhausting” - “You have to push yourself every day” - “It’s tough to keep going” - “Requires a lot of determination and discipline” - “People underestimate how much energy it takes”</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="d.-high-costs" class="level3" data-number="1.3.3">
<h3 data-number="1.3.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="d.-high-costs"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.3</span> 🅳 D. High Costs</h3>
<p><strong>🔑 Key Concept:</strong> Too expensive to afford</p>
<p><strong>🟢 Common Paraphrases:</strong> - “It’s quite pricey” - “Costs too much money” - “Couldn’t afford it” - “Membership fees are high” - “Didn’t have the budget for it” - “Financially, it wasn’t sustainable”</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="e.-feeling-less-successful-than-others" class="level3" data-number="1.3.4">
<h3 data-number="1.3.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="e.-feeling-less-successful-than-others"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.4</span> 🅴 E. Feeling Less Successful Than Others</h3>
<p><strong>🔑 Key Concept:</strong> Comparing yourself to others and feeling inadequate</p>
<p><strong>🟢 Common Paraphrases:</strong> - “Others were doing better” - “Felt like I was falling behind” - “Everyone else seemed more advanced” - “Compared myself to others” - “Didn’t progress as quickly as my peers” - “I looked around and saw I wasn’t improving like them”</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="tip-for-listening" class="level3" data-number="1.3.5">
<h3 data-number="1.3.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tip-for-listening"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.5</span> 🔁 Tip for Listening</h3>
<p>When you’re preparing for multiple-choice questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Underline <strong>keywords</strong> in the options.</li>
<li>Anticipate the type of <strong>language or emotion</strong> they might use.</li>
<li>Remember they often <strong>paraphrase the idea</strong>—not the exact words.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="vocab-and-structures" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Vocab and Structures</h1>
<section id="recording-1" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recording-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Recording 1</h2>
<section id="vocabulary-and-phrases-spoken-english" class="level3" data-number="2.1.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vocabulary-and-phrases-spoken-english"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.1</span> Vocabulary and Phrases (Spoken English)</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Word / Phrase</th>
<th>Meaning / Usage</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>not too expensive</strong></td>
<td>Informal way to say “affordable”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>you should be able to…</strong></td>
<td>Suggestion / mild certainty</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>that sounds alright</strong></td>
<td>Agreeing with a suggestion</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>I’ll definitely have a look</strong></td>
<td>Informal – plan to check something out</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>transport links</strong></td>
<td>Connectivity by public transport</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>go by bike</strong></td>
<td>Travel using a bicycle</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>a nightmare</strong></td>
<td>Very difficult or frustrating situation</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>hardly any</strong></td>
<td>Almost none</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>one or two days a week</strong></td>
<td>Common expression for occasional work</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>it’s weekends that are a problem</strong></td>
<td>Emphasizing contrast / exception</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>a brand new</strong></td>
<td>Recently built or opened</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>open a couple of months</strong></td>
<td>Very recent time frame</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>one of the best in the country</strong></td>
<td>Strong positive opinion</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>I’ve been going to him for years</strong></td>
<td>Continuous habit over time</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>I really appreciate that</strong></td>
<td>Polite way to express gratitude</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>you can’t miss it</strong></td>
<td>It’s easy to find</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="sentences-structures" class="level3" data-number="2.1.2">
<h3 data-number="2.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sentences-structures"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.2</span> Sentences Structures</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 36%">
<col style="width: 63%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Structure Type</th>
<th>Example from Transcript</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Present Perfect</strong></td>
<td>“It has only been open a couple of months.”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Suggestion / Possibility</strong></td>
<td>“You should be able to get something reasonable…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Time Phrases</strong></td>
<td>“One or two days a week”, “after 5.30”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Conditionals</strong></td>
<td>“If you’re interested…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Past Habit</strong></td>
<td>“I’ve been going to him for years.”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Softened Suggestions</strong></td>
<td>“I could meet you if you like…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Emphasis with contrast</strong></td>
<td>“It’s weekends that are a problem.”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Future Plans</strong></td>
<td>“I’ll text you next week then.”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="turning-them-into-speaking" class="level3" data-number="2.1.3">
<h3 data-number="2.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="turning-them-into-speaking"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.3</span> Turning them into speaking</h3>
<section id="do-you-often-use-public-transport" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-often-use-public-transport">Do you often use public transport</h4>
<p>Not really. I usually go by bike because it’s quicker and more convenient for me. I’m lucky - my office isn’t far from where I live, so I hardly ever need to use buses or trains. But when I do, I’d say the transport links in my area are decent.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-enjoy-shopping-in-your-local-area" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-enjoy-shopping-in-your-local-area">Do you enjoy shopping in your local area?</h4>
<p>Yes, I do! There’s a brand new shopping mall that opened just a couple of months ago. It’s not too expensive either, so I can usually find something reasonable. I’ve definitely been going there more often lately.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-often-do-you-travel-for-work-or-study" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-often-do-you-travel-for-work-or-study">How often do you travel for work or study?</h4>
<p>These days, I only need to go into the city one or two days a week. Most of the time I work from home. I really appreciate that flexibility - it saves me time and money.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-like-your-neighborhood" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-like-your-neighborhood">Do you like your neighborhood?</h4>
<p>Yes, I really like it. It’s a quite area with good transport links and a lovely park nearby. The school here is one of the best in the country, and we also have a great hospital. I’ve been living here for a few years, and I’ve never had any problems.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-like-going-to-the-cinema" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-like-going-to-the-cinema">Do you like going to the cinema?</h4>
<p>Absolutely. There’s a brand new cinema in the city center - it’s only bene open a couple of months. I’ll definitely have a look this weekend. A friend told me it’s really modern and comfortable.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-often-meet-friends-in-your-free-time" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-often-meet-friends-in-your-free-time">Do you often meet friends in your free time?</h4>
<p>I try to. If they’re free after work, I could meet them for dinner or coffee. Thursday is usually better for me because I finish early. Really appreciate any time I get to catch up with them.</p>
</section>
<section id="describe-a-place-in-your-local-area-that-you-like-to-visit." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="describe-a-place-in-your-local-area-that-you-like-to-visit.">Describe a place in your local area that you like to visit.</h4>
<p>You should say: - what the place is - where it is located - how often you go there - and explain why you enjoy going there</p>
<p>One place I enjoy visiting in my local area is a small park in the suburb where I live. It’s not a huge park, but it’s peaceful and well-kept, and I’ve been going there for years. The park is just a 10-minutes walk from my home, and it’s next to a lovely little cafe. You can’t miss it - it’s right opposite the new cinema that’s only been open a couple of months. I usually go there after work, maybe one or two days a week, just to unwind.</p>
<p>What I love most is how quiet it is. There’s hardly any traffic around, and it’s never crowded. I go by bike, which is really convenient, and it’s a great way to get a bit of exercise. Sometimes I take a book and it on a bench, or just enjoy walking around.</p>
<p>I think it’s only the best things about my neighborhood. It’s not too expensive to live here, the transport links are good, and places like this park make it even better. I really appreciate having a relaxing spot so close to home.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-think-its-important-to-have-public-places-in-cities" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-think-its-important-to-have-public-places-in-cities">Do you think it’s important to have public places in cities?</h4>
<p>Absolutely. I think public places like parks or community centers are essential in cities. They offer people space to relax and socialize, especially in areas where most people live in apartments. For example, the park near my house isn’t too expensive to maintain, but it really adds value to the neighborhood. I’ve been going there for years, and it’s always full of life - families, joggers, even students reading under the trees.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-do-people-prefer-to-go-to-parks-rather-than-shopping-centers" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-do-people-prefer-to-go-to-parks-rather-than-shopping-centers">Why do people prefer to go to parks rather than shopping centers?</h4>
<p>I think it depends on what they’re looking for. Parks are quiet and peaceful, and they’re usually free, while shopping centers can be noisy and crowded. A lot of people are put off by the idea of spending money every time they go out, so they prefer to visit a park instead. Personally, I go by bike to my local park - it’s great exercise and doesn’t cost a thing. You should be able to enjoy your free time without spending a lot.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-the-benefits-of-having-local-amenities-close-to-home" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-the-benefits-of-having-local-amenities-close-to-home">What are the benefits of having local amenities close to home?</h4>
<p>There are so many benefits. First, it saves time. If there’s a good school or a hospital nearby, that’s one less thing to worry about. For instance, in my area, we have one of the best hospitals in the country, and I really appreciate having it so close. There’s also a brand new cinema that’s only been open for a couple of months. It’s nice to have everything within walking distance - you can definitely tell that people feel more connected to their community.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-has-the-use-of-public-spaces-changed-in-recent-years" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-has-the-use-of-public-spaces-changed-in-recent-years">How has the use of public spaces changed in recent years?</h4>
<p>I think people are using public spaces more now, especially after the pandemic. There’s more focus on outdoor activities, mental health, and work-life balance. A lot of people work from home one or two days a week now, so they have more time to enjoy places like parks or cafes. It’s also become more common for local councils to invest in public areas because they’ve realized how much people value them.</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="recording-2" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recording-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Recording 2</h2>
<section id="vocabulary-and-phrases" class="level3" data-number="2.2.1">
<h3 data-number="2.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vocabulary-and-phrases"><span class="header-section-number">2.2.1</span> Vocabulary and Phrases</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 51%">
<col style="width: 48%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Vocabulary / Phrase</th>
<th>Meaning / Use Case</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>put off by the idea</strong></td>
<td>discouraged or uninterested because of something</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>fit a visit into your day</strong></td>
<td>schedule time for something</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>get crowded</strong></td>
<td>become full of people</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>relatively short space of time</strong></td>
<td>not very long; short period</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>accessible form of exercise</strong></td>
<td>easy to start or do for most people</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>doesn’t come cheap</strong></td>
<td>expensive</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>do it at any time of day or night</strong></td>
<td>very flexible timing</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>indoor pool / any time of year</strong></td>
<td>convenience, regardless of season</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>can be quite boring or solitary</strong></td>
<td>not social or exciting</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>provided the conditions are right</strong></td>
<td>if the weather/environment is suitable</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>fanatics go out in wind and rain</strong></td>
<td>only very extreme people do it in bad weather</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>healthy mind and body</strong></td>
<td>physical + mental benefit</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>less chance of hurting yourself</strong></td>
<td>safer option</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>significant costs involved</strong></td>
<td>quite expensive</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>encourage you to achieve your goals</strong></td>
<td>motivational language</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>do yourself permanent damage</strong></td>
<td>warning phrase – health risk</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>give up hope / stop believing</strong></td>
<td>emotional burnout or loss of motivation</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>takes a lot of determination</strong></td>
<td>mentally demanding</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>don’t have that kind of commitment</strong></td>
<td>not mentally strong or consistent</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>set manageable goals</strong></td>
<td>practical, realistic planning</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>give yourself a treat</strong></td>
<td>reward-based motivation strategy</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>don’t get too upset if you experience setbacks</strong></td>
<td>mental toughness advice</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="structures" class="level3" data-number="2.2.2">
<h3 data-number="2.2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="structures"><span class="header-section-number">2.2.2</span> Structures</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 50%">
<col style="width: 50%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Structure Type</th>
<th>Example from Transcript</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Conditionals</strong></td>
<td>“Only fanatics go out in the wind and rain.”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Passive Voice</strong></td>
<td>“That’s when they <strong>give up hope</strong> and <strong>stop believing</strong>…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Relative Clauses</strong></td>
<td>“…which helps you make the right decision for you.”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Imperatives</strong></td>
<td>“Don’t join a gym unless…” / “Set manageable goals.”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Contrast Clauses</strong></td>
<td>“But make sure you get the right shoes.” / “On the other hand…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Cause and Effect</strong></td>
<td>“That’s probably because…” / “That’s when they give up…”</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Soft Warnings &amp; Advice</strong></td>
<td>“It can be surprisingly challenging…” / “You could do yourself harm…”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="turning-them-into-speaking-1" class="level3" data-number="2.2.3">
<h3 data-number="2.2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="turning-them-into-speaking-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.2.3</span> Turning them into Speaking</h3>
<section id="do-you-do-any-physical-exercise" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-do-any-physical-exercise">Do you do any physical exercise ?</h4>
<p>Yes, I try to stay active. I used to go to the gym, but honestly, fitting a visit into my busy day was a bit difficult. These days, I prefer cycling in the park. It’s fun, and being out in the fresh air really helps me relax. I also enjoy in because it keeps me fit without feeling like a chore.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-prefer-indoor-or-outdoor-activities" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-prefer-indoor-or-outdoor-activities">Do you prefer indoor or outdoor activities?</h4>
<p>I definitely prefer outdoor activities. I find going for a run or a bike ride much more enjoyable than being stuck in a gym. The fresh air and scenery make it feel less like exercise. But I”ll admit - if the weather’s bad, I skip it. Only real fanatics go out in the wind and rain!</p>
</section>
<section id="what-do-you-think-about-personal-trainers" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-do-you-think-about-personal-trainers">What do you think about personal trainers?</h4>
<p>I think they can be really helpful, especially for beginners. Having someone there to encourage you can help you achieve your goals can really boost motivation. The only downside is the cost - personal trainers can be expensive, and not everyone can afford that.</p>
</section>
<section id="describe-a-physical-activity-you-enjoy." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="describe-a-physical-activity-you-enjoy.">Describe a physical activity you enjoy.</h4>
<p>*You should say:</p>
<p>what the activity is</p>
<p>where and when you do it</p>
<p>who you do it with</p>
<p>and explain why you enjoy it.*</p>
<p>One physical activity I really enjoy is swimming. I usually go to an indoor pool near my house, which means I can swim any time of year regardless of the weather. I often go after work, and sometimes my friend joins me.</p>
<p>What I like most about swimming is that it’s great for building fitness, but it’s also quite gentle on the body. It works all the muscles without putting too much strain on the joints. That said, it can be a bit solitary - you can’t exactly have a chat while swimming laps!</p>
<p>Still, I find it really relaxing and satisfying. It clears my mind and keeps me in shape. I’ve also set some small goals for myself, like increasing how many laps I can do, which helps me stay motivated.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-do-some-people-enjoy-physical-exercise-more-than-others" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-do-some-people-enjoy-physical-exercise-more-than-others">Why do some people enjoy physical exercise more than others?</h4>
<p>I think it depends on their personality and past experience. Some people enjoy exercise because they’ve built a habit and can see the progress they’re making, which keeps them motivated. Others might find it hard because they don’t feel any improvement at first, so they lost interest and give up. Also, if someone isn’t very flexible or physically confident, even simple exercises like yoga can feel surprisingly challenging.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-think-people-today-get-enough-physical-activity" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-think-people-today-get-enough-physical-activity">Do you think people today get enough physical activity?</h4>
<p>Honestly, I don’t think most people do. Many lead very busy lives, and fitting a workout into their schedule can be tough. Even if they join a gym, they often stop going after a few weeks. It takes a lot of determination and commitment to keep exercising regularly, especially if you’re not seeing immediate results.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-can-people-do-to-stay-motivated-to-exercise-regularly" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-can-people-do-to-stay-motivated-to-exercise-regularly">What can people do to stay motivated to exercise regularly?</h4>
<p>One effective way is to set manageable goals. If people aim too high at the beginning, they might feel overwhelmed and give up. Having flexible targets, rewarding yourself when you reach a goal, or even exercising with a friend can make it more enjoyable and sustainable. Getting a personal trainer can also help, but that comes with a significant cost.</p>
</section>
<section id="is-it-better-to-do-exercise-indoors-or-outdoors" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="is-it-better-to-do-exercise-indoors-or-outdoors">Is it better to do exercise indoors or outdoors?</h4>
<p>It depends on personal preference. Some people enjoy running or cycling outdoors because it gives them a sense of freedom and they get to enjoy the fresh air. Others prefer the gym or indoor pools where the environment is controlled, especially during bad weather. Personally, I find outdoor exercise more refreshing, as long as the conditions are right - I’m definitely not a fan of running in the rain.</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="recording-3" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recording-3"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Recording 3</h2>
<section id="vocabulary-and-phrases-1" class="level3" data-number="2.3.1">
<h3 data-number="2.3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vocabulary-and-phrases-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.3.1</span> Vocabulary and Phrases</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 36%">
<col style="width: 63%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Phrase or Word</th>
<th>Meaning / Use</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>range of natural dyes</strong></td>
<td>Various types of plant-based colouring agents</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>to colour fabrics</strong></td>
<td>To dye materials like cotton or wool</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>I’ve always been interested in…</strong></td>
<td>Expressing a long-term personal interest</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>amazing colours</strong></td>
<td>Strong, impressive colours (spoken emphasis)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>follow it up</strong></td>
<td>Investigate something further / pursue it</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>specialises in</strong></td>
<td>Focuses on (used for institutions or experts)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>practical investigation</strong></td>
<td>Hands-on experiment (academic project term)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>couldn’t decide on my variables</strong></td>
<td>Unclear about what to test in an experiment</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>was going to… but then…</strong></td>
<td>Change of plan (very common in IELTS!)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>ready-made natural dyes</strong></td>
<td>Pre-prepared dyes (vs.&nbsp;homemade)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>just a matter of…</strong></td>
<td>Suggesting something will be simple or small</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>a whole pile of…</strong></td>
<td>Informal phrase for a large amount</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>abandoned that idea</strong></td>
<td>Gave up / decided not to continue with something</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>cost a fortune</strong></td>
<td>Very expensive</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>I can see why…</strong></td>
<td>Logical conclusion based on what’s been said</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>affect the fabric</strong></td>
<td>Damage or influence material quality</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>disappointing</strong></td>
<td>Expressing an unsatisfactory outcome</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>extremely dangerous if ingested</strong></td>
<td>Strong health warning — formal tone</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>used in dishes like curry</strong></td>
<td>Common usage example — everyday context</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>not permanent as a dye</strong></td>
<td>Temporary colouring effect</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>only fanatics go out in…</strong></td>
<td>Exaggerated way to describe extreme enthusiasts (from earlier)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="sentence-structures-and-grammar" class="level3" data-number="2.3.2">
<h3 data-number="2.3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sentence-structures-and-grammar"><span class="header-section-number">2.3.2</span> Sentence Structures and Grammar</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Structure Type</th>
<th>Example from Transcript</th>
<th>IELTS Use</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Present Perfect Continuous</strong></td>
<td><em>“I’ve been looking at…”</em></td>
<td>Ongoing recent research</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Past Perfect</strong></td>
<td><em>“I’d thought it’d just be a matter of…”</em></td>
<td>Expectations vs.&nbsp;reality</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Past Simple Narrative</strong></td>
<td><em>“I went to a carpet shop…”</em></td>
<td>Recounting past events</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Passive Voice</strong></td>
<td><em>“It can be extremely dangerous if ingested.”</em></td>
<td>Formal warnings</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Contrast / Change of Plan</strong></td>
<td><em>“I was going to… but then I decided to…”</em></td>
<td>Highlighting adjustment</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Relative Clause</strong></td>
<td><em>“…a book about a botanic garden that specialises in…”</em></td>
<td>Describing specific nouns</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Result Expression</strong></td>
<td><em>“…the wool ended up just a sort of watery cream shade.”</em></td>
<td>Showing unexpected outcome</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Causative Expression</strong></td>
<td><em>“I didn’t have time to start crushing up insects…”</em></td>
<td>Explaining reason</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Hedging / Tentative Language</strong></td>
<td><em>“Maybe not, but…” / “I’d thought…” / “I can see why…”</em></td>
<td>Academic tone, not overconfident</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Listing Ideas</strong></td>
<td><em>“Cotton, wool and nylon…” / “Some that weren’t natural…”</em></td>
<td>Useful for organizing in Speaking and Writing</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="turning-them-into-speaking-2" class="level3" data-number="2.3.3">
<h3 data-number="2.3.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="turning-them-into-speaking-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.3.3</span> Turning them into speaking</h3>
<section id="do-you-enjoy-working-on-creative-projects" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-enjoy-working-on-creative-projects">Do you enjoy working on creative projects ?</h4>
<p>Yes, I’ve always been interested in creative things, especially anything to do with colour. A while ago, I did a project where I experimented with natural dyes to colour fabrics like cotton and wool. It was quite hands-on - a real practical investigation - and even thought i was time-consuming, I found it fascinating.</p>
</section>
<section id="have-you-ever-made-something-by-hand" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="have-you-ever-made-something-by-hand">Have you ever made something by hand?</h4>
<p>Actually, yes. I once made some natural dyes myself as part of a textile design project. I thought it would just be a matter of using a teaspoon or so, but I ended up needing a whole pile of beetroot just to get a bit of colour. It took longer than I expected, but i was worth it.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-enjoy-doing-experiments" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-enjoy-doing-experiments">Do you enjoy doing experiments?</h4>
<p>I do, especially when there’s a creative element involved. I remember doing an experiment with different types of fabric - like cotton, wool, and nylon - to see how they reacted to natural and artificial dyes. I’d been going to test just one fibre at first, but then I decided to include more for comparison.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-often-try-new-things" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-often-try-new-things">Do you often try new things?</h4>
<p>Yes, I like following up on things that catch my interest. For example, I once visited an exhibition and saw a display of colorful textiles, which inspired me to research natural dyes. I even found a great book about a botanic garden that specialises in dye-producing plants.</p>
</section>
<section id="are-you-interested-in-art-of-design" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="are-you-interested-in-art-of-design">Are you interested in art of design?</h4>
<p>Definitely. I love anything visual. I once studied a dye called Tyrian purple, which was worn in ancient times by royalty because it was so rare. I didn’t use it in my project, though - it would’ve cost a fortune.</p>
</section>
<section id="describe-a-project-or-piece-of-work-you-did-either-at-school-or-at-home." class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="describe-a-project-or-piece-of-work-you-did-either-at-school-or-at-home.">Describe a project or piece of work you did, either at school or at home.</h4>
<p>You should say: - what the project was</p>
<ul>
<li><p>why you did it</p></li>
<li><p>how you did it</p></li>
<li><p>and explain how you felt about doing it</p></li>
</ul>
<p>One of the most interesting projects I’ve ever done was a textile design assignment during my final year at university. I’ve always been interested in colour and design, so I chose to focus on how natural dyes could be used to color fabrics like cotton and wool. The idea actually came from a carpet shop I visited years ago when I was on holiday with my family in Turkey. I still remember all the amazing colours, and it really stuck with me. Later, I visited exhibition at a museum, and that gave me even more ideas. I decided to follow it up for my project. The project included a practical investigation, which meant I had to prepare and test various dyes on different types of fabric - cotton, wool, and nylon. At first, I was going to use just one fibre, but I changed my mind so I could make some comparisons. I used both ready-made dyes and homemade ones. For example, I tried using beetroot, but it was more difficult than I thought. I had to chop up a whole pile of it just to get a little bit of dye, and even then, the colour wasn’t as strong as I’d hoped. It ended up being a kind of watery cream shade on the wool, which was disappointing. Despite the challenges, I really enjoyed doing the project. It was creative, and I learned a lot - not just about fabrics, but also about how to plan and carry out an investigation. It took longer than I expected, but I felt proud of the final results.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-think-students-learn-more-from-doing-projects-or-from-traditional-classes" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-think-students-learn-more-from-doing-projects-or-from-traditional-classes">Do you think students learn more from doing projects or from traditional classes?</h4>
<p>I believe students often learn more from doing hands-on projects. When they’re actively involved in a practical investigation, like testing variables or creating something from scratch, they tend to remember the experience better. For example, when I made my own natural dyes for a design project, I ended up learning much more than I would have by just reading about the process in a textbook. It encourages creativity and independent thinking.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-kind-of-projects-are-most-beneficial-for-young-people" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-kind-of-projects-are-most-beneficial-for-young-people">What kind of projects are most beneficial for young people ?</h4>
<p>I think the most useful projects are the ones that combine creativity and real-world skills. For instance, projects that involve planning, researching, or experimenting with different materials can teach valuable problem-solving skills. If young people can follow up on something they’re genuinely interested in-whether it’s science, design, or business - they’re more likely to stay motivated and take ownership of their learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="should-schools-focus-more-on-academic-subjects-or-creative-activities" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="should-schools-focus-more-on-academic-subjects-or-creative-activities">Should schools focus more on academic subjects or creative activities?</h4>
<p>Ideally, there should be a balance. Academic subjects are important, of course, but creative activities help students develop other types of intelligence- like emotional awareness, visual thinking, or innovation. In my opinion, creative projects like art, music, or even textile design allow students to express themselves and discover talents they might not explore in regular academic classes.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-challenges-do-people-face-when-working-on-creative-projects" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-challenges-do-people-face-when-working-on-creative-projects">What challenges do people face when working on creative projects?</h4>
<p>One big challenge is time. Creative projects often take longer than expected. I remember thinking that dyeing fabric with natural ingredients would be simple, but I ended up needing a whole pile of beetroot just to get a weak color. Another issue is uncertainty-you don’t always know what the outcome will be. That can be discouraging if things don’t go as planned, especially if the materials cost a fortune.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-do-some-people-give-up-on-creative-hobbies-or-projects" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-do-some-people-give-up-on-creative-hobbies-or-projects">Why do some people give up on creative hobbies or projects?</h4>
<p>Many people stop because they don’t see quick results. It takes a lot of commitment and patience to stick with something that doesn’t turn out perfectly the first time. Some might also abandon their projects if they lack proper guidance. For instance, without a good mentor or tutor, it’s easy to feel lost. Also, creative work can be expensive-materials, tools, or even time investment can be hard to maintain. ## Recording 4</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="vocabulary-and-phrases-2" class="level3" data-number="2.3.4">
<h3 data-number="2.3.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vocabulary-and-phrases-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.3.4</span> Vocabulary and Phrases</h3>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 39%">
<col style="width: 60%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Word / Phrase</th>
<th>Meaning / Usage</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>dozing under rocks</strong></td>
<td>Lightly sleeping in a warm, sheltered place</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>quite common</strong></td>
<td>Frequently found or seen in a region</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>distinctive</strong></td>
<td>Easily recognizable; unique or unusual</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>in contrast with</strong></td>
<td>Used to show a clear difference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>varied diet</strong></td>
<td>A diet including different types of food</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>crush beetles and snail shells</strong></td>
<td>Shows strong jaw strength (functional ability)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>predators</strong></td>
<td>Animals that hunt or attack others</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>man-made threat</strong></td>
<td>Dangers caused by humans (e.g.&nbsp;traffic, pollution)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>methods of navigation</strong></td>
<td>Ways an animal finds its direction or location</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>territory</strong></td>
<td>Area an animal considers its home</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>monogamous</strong></td>
<td>Having one mate at a time; forming long-term pair bonds</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>returning to the same partner</strong></td>
<td>Behavior of repeating a relationship over time</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>protecting their young</strong></td>
<td>Looking after or defending their offspring</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>no evidence to support that idea</strong></td>
<td>No data or proof to confirm a theory</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>give the female protection</strong></td>
<td>Defensive behavior in mating context</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>collecting data by tracking</strong></td>
<td>Research method using technology to follow subjects</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>fixed this onto their tails</strong></td>
<td>Describes how GPS units were attached</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>far fewer meetings than expected</strong></td>
<td>Research result that showed less interaction</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>hypothesis</strong></td>
<td>A theory or idea not yet proven</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>self-preservation</strong></td>
<td>Behavior intended to avoid harm or danger</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/listening-practice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Muse - Musing</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/muse/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="muse" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Muse</h1>
<p>Part of speech: - Noun - Verb</p>
<section id="meaning" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meaning"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Meaning</h2>
<section id="noun-a-source-of-inspiration" class="level3" data-number="1.1.1">
<h3 data-number="1.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="noun-a-source-of-inspiration"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.1</span> [Noun] A source of inspiration</h3>
<p>Common in artistic or creative contexts - Meaning: A person, idea, or thing that inspires creativity or thought - Example: - The painter said his wife was his <strong>muse</strong>. - Nature has always been a powerful <strong>muse</strong> for poets.</p>
</section>
<section id="verb-to-think-deeply-or-reflect-often-slowly-or-dreamily" class="level3" data-number="1.1.2">
<h3 data-number="1.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="verb-to-think-deeply-or-reflect-often-slowly-or-dreamily"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.2</span> [Verb] To think deeply or reflect (often slowly or dreamily)</h3>
<p>Use in formal or poetic English - Meaning: To reflect or ponder thoughtfully, often without speaking - Example: - She <strong>mused</strong> about what life might be like in a different country. - He sat quietly, <strong>musing</strong> on the meaning of the poem.</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="musing" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Musing</h1>
<p>Part of speech: - Noun - Adjective (<em>less common, literary</em>) - Present participle of “muse” (Verb)</p>
<section id="meaning-1" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meaning-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Meaning</h2>
<section id="noun-a-period-or-act-of-deep-thought" class="level3" data-number="2.1.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="noun-a-period-or-act-of-deep-thought"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.1</span> [Noun] A period or act of deep thought</h3>
<ul>
<li>Meaning: Thoughtful reflection or meditation</li>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>Her quiet musings were interrupted by the phone ringing.</li>
<li>The article was full of philosophical <strong>musings</strong> on happiness.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="verb-present-participle-reflecting-deeply" class="level3" data-number="2.1.2">
<h3 data-number="2.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="verb-present-participle-reflecting-deeply"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.2</span> [Verb: Present Participle] Reflecting deeply</h3>
<ul>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>He was <strong>musing</strong> about how different things might have been.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adjective-literary-dreamily-thoughtful" class="level3" data-number="2.1.3">
<h3 data-number="2.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjective-literary-dreamily-thoughtful"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.3</span> [Adjective: Literary] Dreamily thoughtful</h3>
<ul>
<li>Example:
<ul>
<li>She had a musing expression as she stared out the window.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="common-collocations" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Common Collocations</h1>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 30%">
<col style="width: 70%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Phrase</th>
<th>Usage example</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>muse about/ over/ on</td>
<td>She mused about the meaning of life.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>a poetic muse</td>
<td>He found his poetic muse in the mountains</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>philosophical musings</td>
<td>The book is filled with his philosophical musings</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="example-in-ielts-exam" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Example in IELTS exam</h1>
<section id="speaking" class="level2" data-number="4.1">
<h2 data-number="4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speaking"><span class="header-section-number">4.1</span> Speaking</h2>
<section id="do-you-enjoy-spending-time-alone" class="level3" data-number="4.1.1">
<h3 data-number="4.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-enjoy-spending-time-alone"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.1</span> Do you enjoy spending time alone?</h3>
<p>(Using muse as a verb) Yes, I do enjoy time alone, especially when I can sit quietly and <strong>muse about</strong> different ideas. It helps me reflect on my goals and sometimes come up with creative solutions or even new plans for the future.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-ever-write-a-diary-or-journals" class="level3" data-number="4.1.2">
<h3 data-number="4.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-ever-write-a-diary-or-journals"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.2</span> Do you ever write a diary or journals?</h3>
<p>(Using muse as a noun) Yes, I write in a journal regularly. It’s mostly filled with personal thoughts and random <strong>musings</strong> about life, people I meet, or even things I read. I find it helps me process my emotions and clears my mind.</p>
</section>
<section id="some-people-believe-that-creativity-is-as-important-as-academic-skills." class="level3" data-number="4.1.3">
<h3 data-number="4.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="some-people-believe-that-creativity-is-as-important-as-academic-skills."><span class="header-section-number">4.1.3</span> Some people believe that creativity is as important as academic skills.</h3>
<p>Many creative breakthroughs begin with quiet <strong>musings</strong>, as people reflect deeply before arriving at unique ideas.</p>
</section>
<section id="modern-life-is-often-too-fast-paced-for-personal-reflection" class="level3" data-number="4.1.4">
<h3 data-number="4.1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modern-life-is-often-too-fast-paced-for-personal-reflection"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.4</span> Modern life is often too fast-paced for personal reflection</h3>
<p>In today’s busy world, people rarely have the time to <strong>muse on</strong> their own experiences, which may reduce self-awareness and emotional clarity.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-people-today-spend-enough-time-thinking-deeply" class="level3" data-number="4.1.5">
<h3 data-number="4.1.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-people-today-spend-enough-time-thinking-deeply"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.5</span> Do people today spend enough time thinking deeply?</h3>
<p>Honestly, I don’t think so. Life today is fast-paced, and people are often distracted by social media or constant notifications. Deep thinking requires space and silence, and most people rarely take time to just sit and <strong>muse about</strong> important questions or life decisions. I think that kind of reflection is crucial for personal growth.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-do-some-people-enjoy-writing-journals-or-personal-blogs" class="level3" data-number="4.1.6">
<h3 data-number="4.1.6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-do-some-people-enjoy-writing-journals-or-personal-blogs"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.6</span> Why do some people enjoy writing journals or personal blogs?</h3>
<p>I think it’s partly because writing helps people process their thoughts. For many, a journal is a private place to record their <strong>musings</strong> about daily life or future goals. It’s also a way to make sense of emotions. Even blogs, which are more public, often start from personal reflection.</p>
</section>
<section id="is-creativity-important-in-education" class="level3" data-number="4.1.7">
<h3 data-number="4.1.7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="is-creativity-important-in-education"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.7</span> Is creativity important in education?</h3>
<p>Definitely. While academic skills are essential, creativity allows students to explore ideas in original ways. Some of the best innovations come from people who took time to <strong>muse on</strong> a problem from a different perspective. Encouraging students to think creatively also makes learning more meaningful.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-think-quiet-time-is-necessary-for-creativity" class="level3" data-number="4.1.8">
<h3 data-number="4.1.8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-think-quiet-time-is-necessary-for-creativity"><span class="header-section-number">4.1.8</span> Do you think quiet time is necessary for creativity?</h3>
<p>Yes, I believe it’s vital. Creative thinking often comes from calm, undistracted moments - those quiet times when you’re not actively working, but your mind is still turning over ideas. Many artists or writers have said their best thoughts came during moments of <strong>musing</strong>, like walking alone or staring out the window.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="writing" class="level2" data-number="4.2">
<h2 data-number="4.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="writing"><span class="header-section-number">4.2</span> Writing</h2>
<section id="some-people-believe-that-reflection-and-mindfulness-are-essential-in-modern-life" class="level3" data-number="4.2.1">
<h3 data-number="4.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="some-people-believe-that-reflection-and-mindfulness-are-essential-in-modern-life"><span class="header-section-number">4.2.1</span> Some people believe that reflection and mindfulness are essential in modern life</h3>
<p>In a world driven by speed and productivity, people rarely pause to <strong>muse on</strong> their choices, which many result in decisions made without deeper understanding or emotional clarity.</p>
<ul>
<li>While some may view self-reflection as unproductive, others argue that quiet <strong>musings</strong> often lead to innovative ideas or better emotional regulation.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="do-you-agree-or-disagree-that-creativity-is-more-important-than-knowledge-in-education" class="level3" data-number="4.2.2">
<h3 data-number="4.2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-agree-or-disagree-that-creativity-is-more-important-than-knowledge-in-education"><span class="header-section-number">4.2.2</span> Do you agree or disagree that creativity is more important than knowledge in education?</h3>
<p>While knowledge forms the foundation of academic success, creativity enables students to apply that knowledge in meaningful ways. In fact, many great inventions and solutions have come from individuals who took time to <strong>muse on</strong> a problem from a new angle, rather than simply recalling facts. Moreover, encouraging students to record their <strong>musings</strong> in journals or through art can foster emotional intelligence and personal growth - qualities that are just as vital as academic skills in today’s world.</p>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/muse/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Number of tourism in season</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/tourism/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>The bar graph below show the number of tourists visiting two different cities by season. Summarize the information by selecting and reporting the main features, and make comparison where relevant.</em></p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/tourism/Pasted image 20250625093819.png" class="img-fluid"> The bar chart compares the number of tourists (in thousands) who visited two cities, Dover and Troy, across the four seasons: Spring, Summer, Autumn, and Winter.</p>
<p>Overall, Dover saw a steady increase in tourist numbers throughout the year, peaking in winter, while Troy experienced the opposite trend, with numbers peaking in summer and then sharply declining by winter. The two cities demonstrated contrasting seasonal patterns in tourism.</p>
<p>In spring, both cities received a similar number of tourists, with Dover attracting 5,000 and Troy slightly fewer at 4,800. However, during the summer months, Troy saw a dramatic surge to 23,000 visitors, more than double Dover’s figures of 10,000. In autumn, while Troy has a slight decrease to 20,000 visitors, Dover hosts increasingly to 15,000 visitors.</p>
<p>In contrast, winter brought a complete reversal in patterns. Dover’s tourist numbers peaked at 25,000, while Troy experienced a steep decline, drawing only 5,000 visitors - the lowest for the year. This stark contrast highlights Dover’s strong winter appeal and Troy’s reliance on summer tourism.</p>
<section id="vocabulary-list-for-task-1" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Vocabulary list for Task 1</h1>
<section id="describing-trends" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="describing-trends"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> 1. Describing Trends</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Increasing</th>
<th>Decreasing</th>
<th>Stable / Fluctuating</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>rise / increase</td>
<td>fall / decrease</td>
<td>remain steady / stable</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>grow / climb</td>
<td>drop / decline</td>
<td>fluctuate</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>soar / surge</td>
<td>plummet / plunge</td>
<td>level off / flatten out</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>peak</td>
<td>bottom out</td>
<td>vary / shift slightly</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Examples:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The number <strong>rose steadily</strong> from 10 to 25.</li>
<li>It <strong>plummeted sharply</strong> in winter.</li>
<li>Figures <strong>remained stable</strong> during spring.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="comparative-language" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparative-language"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> 2. Comparative Language</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 50%">
<col style="width: 50%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Phrase</th>
<th>Example</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>more than double</td>
<td>Troy attracted <strong>more than double</strong> Dover’s tourists in summer.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>slightly higher/lower</td>
<td>Dover’s figure was <strong>slightly higher</strong> than Troy’s in spring.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>significantly greater</td>
<td>Troy had <strong>significantly more</strong> tourists in summer.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>nearly equal / similar</td>
<td>Both cities had <strong>similar</strong> numbers in spring.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>in contrast / whereas</td>
<td>Dover increased, <strong>whereas</strong> Troy declined.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="time-sequence" class="level2" data-number="1.3">
<h2 data-number="1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-sequence"><span class="header-section-number">1.3</span> 3. Time &amp; Sequence</h2>
<ul>
<li>In spring/summer/autumn/winter</li>
<li>Over the course of the year.</li>
<li>During the first/second half of the year.</li>
<li>From … to … / Between … and …</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="key-nouns-phrases" class="level2" data-number="1.4">
<h2 data-number="1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-nouns-phrases"><span class="header-section-number">1.4</span> 4. Key nouns &amp; Phrases</h2>
<ul>
<li>number of tourists</li>
<li>amount / proportion / percentage / figure / total</li>
<li>seasonal variation / opposite pattern / steady increase</li>
<li>city / destination / location</li>
<li>peak / low point / turning point</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="grammar-tips-for-task-1" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Grammar Tips for Task 1</h1>
<section id="use-the-correct-tense" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="use-the-correct-tense"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> 1. Use the Correct Tense</h2>
<ul>
<li>Use <strong>past simple</strong> if dates are in the past: “The number increased in 2020.”</li>
<li>Use <strong>present simple</strong> if there’s <strong>no time reference</strong> (e.g.&nbsp;in a bar chart without years): “Dover receives more tourists in winter than Troy”</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="passive-voice" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="passive-voice"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Passive Voice</h2>
<p>Use passive voice describing what the graph shows: - “The chart illustrates the number of tourists visiting two cities.” - “A steady increase is observed in Dover”.</p>
</section>
<section id="comparative-and-superlative-forms" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparative-and-superlative-forms"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Comparative and Superlative Forms</h2>
<ul>
<li>Troy had <strong>more tourists</strong> than Dover.</li>
<li>Winter was the <strong>the most popular</strong> season in Dover.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="vary-sentence-structures" class="level2" data-number="2.4">
<h2 data-number="2.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vary-sentence-structures"><span class="header-section-number">2.4</span> Vary Sentence Structures</h2>
<ul>
<li>Complex sentences:
<ul>
<li>“Although Troy peaked in summer, Dover reached its highest point in winter”</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Compound sentences:
<ul>
<li>“Troy saw a surge in summer, and this was followed by a sharp decline”.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/tourism/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Internet use among various age groups.</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/internet/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The table below shows the number of hours per week people of different ages spend usin the internet for different types of activities.</p>
<p>Summarize the information by selecting and reporting the main features, and make comparisons where relevant.</p>
<p>Hours per week spent on the internet, by age</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>teens</th>
<th>20s</th>
<th>30s</th>
<th>40s</th>
<th>50s</th>
<th>60s+</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>studying/working</td>
<td>15</td>
<td>50</td>
<td>45</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>17</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>leisure activities</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>18</td>
<td>17</td>
<td>10</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>18</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The table displays the average number of hours per week that people across six age groups spend using the internet for two main purposes: studying/working and leisure activities.</p>
<p>Overall, internet use for studying or working peaks in the 20s age group and gradually declines with age, while leisure-related usage remains more stable across age groups, with only moderate variation. Notably, teenagers spend more time online for leisure than for academic or work purposes, in contrast to all other age groups.</p>
<p>Young adult in their 20s spend the most time using the internet for professional or educational purposes, averaging 50 hours per week. This figure slightly decreases among those in their 30s and 40s, to 45 and 40 hours respectively, and remains at the same level for users in their 50s. Teenagers, by contrast, spend only 15 hours weekly on study or work online, while the figure drops significantly to 17 hours for users aged 60 and above.</p>
<p>In terms of leisure activities, teenagers report the highest usage at 20 hours per week. Adults in their 20s and 30s follow closely behind, with 18 and 17 hours, respectively. Usage declines further among those in their 40s and 50s, reaching 10 and 11 hours. Interestingly, leisure usage increases again among seniors (60+), who spend 18 hours per week- more than any group except teenagers.</p>
<section id="vocabulary-breakdown" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Vocabulary breakdown</h1>
<section id="describing-trends-patterns" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="describing-trends-patterns"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Describing trends &amp; patterns</h2>
<ul>
<li>Peaks in / peaks at
<ul>
<li>“Internet use … <em>peaks in</em> the 20s age group”</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Gradually declines
<ul>
<li>“and <em>gradually declines</em> with age”</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Remain stable/ remains at the same level
<ul>
<li>“… <em>remain at the same level</em> for users in their 50s”</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Moderate variation
<ul>
<li>“with only <em>moderate variation</em>” ## Comparative and Superlative Structures</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The most time
<ul>
<li>“… spend <em>the most time</em> using the internet…”</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Only moderate variation / slightly decrease
<ul>
<li>“<em>slightly decreases</em> among those in theirs 30s and 40s”.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Highest usage / more than any group
<ul>
<li>“who spend 18 hours per week - <em>more than any group</em> except teenagers.” ## Task 1 - Specific Phrases</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Averaging [x] hours per week “averaging 50 hour per week”</li>
<li>In terms of [category] “In terms of leisure activities, teenagers report the highest usage.”</li>
<li>By contrast / interestingly Used to introduce comparison or a surprising point.</li>
<li>Report / spend / use Verbs appropriate for describing behavior.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="grammar-notes" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Grammar notes</h1>
<section id="tense-use-present-simple" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tense-use-present-simple"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Tense use: Present simple</h2>
<p>Task 1 uses <strong>present simple</strong> when the data is a general description (no time reference like “in 2010”) “Teenagers <strong>spend</strong> more time…” “Usage <strong>declines</strong> among those …” “Adults <strong>follow</strong> closely behind…”</p>
</section>
<section id="complex-sentences" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="complex-sentences"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Complex Sentences</h2>
<p>Use subordinate clauses with conjunctions for higher-level grammar: - “While” -&gt; contrast: “… <em>while</em> the figure drops significantly for users aged 60 and above.” - “in contrast to” -&gt; comparision “…<em>in contrast to</em> all other age groups.”</p>
</section>
<section id="noun-phrases-for-precision" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="noun-phrases-for-precision"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Noun Phrases for Precision</h2>
<p>“Internet use for studying or working” “users in their 50s” “those in their 30s and 40s”</p>
<p>These help condense information and show grammatical control.</p>
</section>
<section id="passive-abstract-construction" class="level2" data-number="2.4">
<h2 data-number="2.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="passive-abstract-construction"><span class="header-section-number">2.4</span> Passive &amp; Abstract Construction</h2>
<p>While not used heavily in this task, phrases like: “This figure <strong>is observed to decline</strong>” “The trend <strong>can be explained by</strong> …”</p>
<p>… can be used sparingly for variety if the data justifies it.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>speaking</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/internet/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IELTS essay template</title>
  <dc:creator>Your name</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/ielts-essay-template/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="opinion-essay-template" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Opinion essay template</h1>
<section id="paragraph-1---introduction" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paragraph-1---introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Paragraph 1 - Introduction</h2>
<p>Goal: Introduce the topic, paraphrase the question, clearly state your opinion, and outline the essay.</p>
<section id="background-sentence-paraphrase-the-topic" class="level3" data-number="1.1.1">
<h3 data-number="1.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="background-sentence-paraphrase-the-topic"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.1</span> Background sentence (paraphrase the topic):</h3>
<p>In recent years, the issue of [main idea from the prompt] has sparked considerable debate.</p>
</section>
<section id="specific-issue-or-controversy" class="level3" data-number="1.1.2">
<h3 data-number="1.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="specific-issue-or-controversy"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.2</span> Specific issue or controversy:</h3>
<p>Some people argue that [first side of the argument], while others believe that [second side].</p>
</section>
<section id="clear-thesis-statement-your-opinion" class="level3" data-number="1.1.3">
<h3 data-number="1.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="clear-thesis-statement-your-opinion"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.3</span> Clear thesis statement (your opinion):</h3>
<p>Personally, I [completely/somewhat] agree/disagree with the idea that [restate the statement using your view].</p>
</section>
<section id="outline-what-the-essay-will-cover" class="level3" data-number="1.1.4">
<h3 data-number="1.1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="outline-what-the-essay-will-cover"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.4</span> Outline what the essay will cover:</h3>
<p>This essay will outline the reasons for my opinion, supported by relevant examples.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="paragraph-2---first-main-reason-supporting-your-opinion" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paragraph-2---first-main-reason-supporting-your-opinion"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> Paragraph 2 - First Main Reason Supporting Your Opinion</h2>
<p>Goal: Present a strong reason why you agree/disagree. Explain and give an example.</p>
<section id="topic-sentence-main-idea" class="level3" data-number="1.2.1">
<h3 data-number="1.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="topic-sentence-main-idea"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.1</span> Topic sentence (main idea):</h3>
<p>The reason why I [agree/disagree] is that [state your key reason clearly].</p>
</section>
<section id="explanation" class="level3" data-number="1.2.2">
<h3 data-number="1.2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="explanation"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.2</span> Explanation</h3>
<p>This means that [explain how this reason supports your view in more detail].</p>
</section>
<section id="example-real-or-hypothetical" class="level3" data-number="1.2.3">
<h3 data-number="1.2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="example-real-or-hypothetical"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.3</span> Example (real or hypothetical)</h3>
<p>For example, a study by [source] found that [specific example or case that illustrates your point].</p>
</section>
<section id="analysis" class="level3" data-number="1.2.4">
<h3 data-number="1.2.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.4</span> Analysis</h3>
<p>This demonstrates that [connect the example to your thesis].</p>
<p><strong>Optional: Summary sentence</strong></p>
<p>Therefore, this point strongly supports the idea that [reaffirm your opinion].</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="paragraph-3---second-main-reason-supporting-your-opinion." class="level2" data-number="1.3">
<h2 data-number="1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paragraph-3---second-main-reason-supporting-your-opinion."><span class="header-section-number">1.3</span> Paragraph 3 - Second Main Reason Supporting Your Opinion.</h2>
<p>Goal: Add a second major supporting idea, with an example and analysis.</p>
<section id="topic-sentence-second-idea" class="level3" data-number="1.3.1">
<h3 data-number="1.3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="topic-sentence-second-idea"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.1</span> Topic sentence (second idea):</h3>
<p>Another compelling reason why I [agree/disagree] is that [state your second reason].</p>
</section>
<section id="explanation-1" class="level3" data-number="1.3.2">
<h3 data-number="1.3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="explanation-1"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.2</span> Explanation</h3>
<p>In other words, [elaborate with further logic or mechanism behind the idea].</p>
</section>
<section id="example" class="level3" data-number="1.3.3">
<h3 data-number="1.3.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="example"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.3</span> Example</h3>
<p>A good example of this can be seen in [another study, real-life situation, or statistic].</p>
</section>
<section id="analysis-1" class="level3" data-number="1.3.4">
<h3 data-number="1.3.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-1"><span class="header-section-number">1.3.4</span> Analysis</h3>
<p>As a result, this proves that [link back to your thesis or reinforce your stance].</p>
<p><strong>Optional: address a counterargument (optional for higher band)</strong> While some might argue that [mention opposing point], I believe this concern is outweighed by [your rebuttal].</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="paragraph-4---conclusion" class="level2" data-number="1.4">
<h2 data-number="1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="paragraph-4---conclusion"><span class="header-section-number">1.4</span> Paragraph 4 - Conclusion</h2>
<p>Goal: Summarize your main points and firmly restate your position.</p>
<section id="summarize-key-arguments" class="level3" data-number="1.4.1">
<h3 data-number="1.4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summarize-key-arguments"><span class="header-section-number">1.4.1</span> Summarize key arguments</h3>
<p>In summary, both [reason 1] and [reason 2] illustrate why I believe that [restate viewpoint].</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="strong-closing-sentence-restate-opinion-with-impact" class="level2" data-number="1.5">
<h2 data-number="1.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strong-closing-sentence-restate-opinion-with-impact"><span class="header-section-number">1.5</span> Strong closing sentence (restate opinion with impact):</h2>
<p>For these reasons, I am convinced that [reaffirm your opinion], and I believe this view is crucial for [optional implication].</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="useful-language-for-opinion-essays." class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Useful Language for Opinion Essays.</h1>
<section id="agreedisagree-phrases" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="agreedisagree-phrases"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Agree/Disagree Phrases:</h2>
<ul>
<li>I strongly agree with the idea that …</li>
<li>I completely disagree because …</li>
<li>I believe that …</li>
<li>From my perspective …</li>
<li>It is my firm conviction that … ## Linkers &amp; Transitions:</li>
<li>Firstly / Secondly / Finally</li>
<li>In addition / Moreover / Furthermore</li>
<li>For example / For instance</li>
<li>As a result / Therefore / Thus</li>
<li>On the other hand (if addressing an opposing view)</li>
<li>In conclusion / To sum up</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="discussion-essay-template" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Discussion Essay Template</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>“Discuss both views and give your own opinion.”</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="introduction" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Introduction</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Paraphrase the question</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>People often hold differing opinions about [topic].</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Introduce both views</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>Some believe that [view A], whereas others feel that [view B].</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Thesis (your opinion)</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>I acknowledge both perspectives, but I side with [view A / view B / a balanced view] because…</em></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="body-paragraph-1-view-a" class="level2" data-number="3.2">
<h2 data-number="3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="body-paragraph-1-view-a"><span class="header-section-number">3.2</span> Body Paragraph 1 – View A</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Topic sentence</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>Proponents of [view A] argue that…</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explanation</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>This stems from the fact that…</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Example or evidence</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>For instance, [study/case/example] shows that…</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Link back to question</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>Thus, supporters claim that [restate benefit of view A].</em></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="body-paragraph-2-view-b-and-your-opinion" class="level2" data-number="3.3">
<h2 data-number="3.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="body-paragraph-2-view-b-and-your-opinion"><span class="header-section-number">3.3</span> Body Paragraph 2 – View B (and your opinion)</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Topic sentence</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>On the other hand, opponents argue that…</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explanation</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>They believe this because…</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Example or evidence</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>For example, [real‐world scenario] illustrates that…</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Your stance / mini‑counter</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>While this point has merit, I maintain that…</em></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2" data-number="3.4">
<h2 data-number="3.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><span class="header-section-number">3.4</span> Conclusion</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Summarise both views</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>In summary, [view A] offers… whereas [view B] highlights…</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Restate your opinion clearly</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>Overall, I believe that [reaffirm your position] because…</em><br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>(Optional) Future or recommendation</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. <em>Moving forward, policymakers/individuals should…</em></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<section id="useful-linking-words" class="level3" data-number="3.4.1">
<h3 data-number="3.4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="useful-linking-words"><span class="header-section-number">3.4.1</span> Useful Linking Words</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>To introduce view A:</strong> <em>Firstly, Moreover, In addition</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>To introduce view B:</strong> <em>However, On the other hand, Conversely</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>To conclude:</strong> <em>In conclusion, To sum up, Overall</em></li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="advantages-disadvantages-essay-template" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Advantages &amp; Disadvantages Essay Template</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>“Do the advantages outweigh the disadvantages?”</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="introduction-1" class="level2" data-number="4.1">
<h2 data-number="4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-1"><span class="header-section-number">4.1</span> Introduction</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Paraphrase the question</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“In recent years, the issue of [topic] has attracted significant attention.”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>State that there are both advantages and disadvantages</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“This development brings certain benefits, but it also has drawbacks.”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Thesis (your overall evaluation)</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“In my view, the advantages outweigh the disadvantages.”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="body-paragraph-1-advantages" class="level2" data-number="4.2">
<h2 data-number="4.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="body-paragraph-1-advantages"><span class="header-section-number">4.2</span> Body Paragraph 1 – Advantages</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Topic sentence (first advantage)</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“One major advantage is that [state advantage].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explanation</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“This means that [explain how or why this is beneficial].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Example</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“For instance, [real or hypothetical example].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Result or implication</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“As a result, [describe positive outcome].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>(Optionally add a second advantage using the same structure.)</p>
</section>
<section id="body-paragraph-2-disadvantages" class="level2" data-number="4.3">
<h2 data-number="4.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="body-paragraph-2-disadvantages"><span class="header-section-number">4.3</span> Body Paragraph 2 – Disadvantages</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Topic sentence (first disadvantage)</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“On the other hand, a significant disadvantage is that [state disadvantage].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explanation</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“This leads to [explain how or why this is problematic].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Example</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“For example, [real or hypothetical example].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Result or implication</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“Consequently, [describe negative outcome].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>(Optionally add a second disadvantage using the same structure.)</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-1" class="level2" data-number="4.4">
<h2 data-number="4.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-1"><span class="header-section-number">4.4</span> Conclusion</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Summarise advantages and disadvantages</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“In conclusion, although there are clear drawbacks such as [briefly restate disadvantage], the benefits of [briefly restate advantage] are more significant.”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Restate your evaluation</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“Therefore, I believe that the advantages outweigh the disadvantages in this case.”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>(Optional) Recommendation or final thought</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“To maximize the positives, [suggest a policy or measure].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="linking-words-phrases" class="level2" data-number="4.5">
<h2 data-number="4.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linking-words-phrases"><span class="header-section-number">4.5</span> Linking Words &amp; Phrases</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Introducing advantages:</strong> Firstly, In addition, Moreover<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Introducing disadvantages:</strong> However, On the other hand, Conversely<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Concluding:</strong> In conclusion, To sum up, Overall</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="problem-solution-essay-template" class="level1" data-number="5">
<h1 data-number="5"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Problem &amp; Solution Essay Template</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>“What are the problems associated with [topic] and what solutions can be proposed?”</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="introduction-2" class="level2" data-number="5.1">
<h2 data-number="5.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-2"><span class="header-section-number">5.1</span> Introduction</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Paraphrase the question</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“In recent years, [topic] has become a growing concern.”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>State that there are problems and that you will propose solutions</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“This essay will examine the main problems and suggest possible solutions.”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="body-paragraph-1-problems" class="level2" data-number="5.2">
<h2 data-number="5.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="body-paragraph-1-problems"><span class="header-section-number">5.2</span> Body Paragraph 1 – Problems</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Topic sentence (first problem)</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“One significant problem is that [state problem].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explanation</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“This means that [explain why this is a problem].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Example</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“For example, [real or hypothetical example].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Result or consequence</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“As a result, [describe negative outcome].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>(Optionally add a second problem using the same structure.)</p>
</section>
<section id="body-paragraph-2-solutions" class="level2" data-number="5.3">
<h2 data-number="5.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="body-paragraph-2-solutions"><span class="header-section-number">5.3</span> Body Paragraph 2 – Solutions</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Topic sentence (first solution)</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“To address this issue, one solution is to [state solution].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explanation</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“This would [explain how or why this solution works].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Example</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“For instance, [example of where it has worked or could work].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Benefit or expected outcome</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“Consequently, [describe positive outcome].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>(Optionally add a second solution using the same structure.)</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-2" class="level2" data-number="5.4">
<h2 data-number="5.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-2"><span class="header-section-number">5.4</span> Conclusion</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Summarise the problems and solutions</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“In conclusion, [restate the main problems] can be mitigated by [restate main solutions].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Final evaluative comment</strong>
<ul>
<li>e.g.&nbsp;“If these measures are implemented effectively, [positive final thought].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="linking-words-phrases-1" class="level2" data-number="5.5">
<h2 data-number="5.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linking-words-phrases-1"><span class="header-section-number">5.5</span> Linking Words &amp; Phrases</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Introducing problems:</strong> Firstly, One major issue, Another problem<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Introducing solutions:</strong> To tackle this, One possible solution, Furthermore<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Concluding:</strong> In conclusion, To sum up, Overall</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="direct-questions-essay-template" class="level1" data-number="6">
<h1 data-number="6"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Direct Questions Essay Template</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>“Answer the specific questions asked in the prompt.”</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<section id="introduction-3" class="level2" data-number="6.1">
<h2 data-number="6.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-3"><span class="header-section-number">6.1</span> Introduction</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Paraphrase the prompt</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “The issue of [topic] raises several key questions.”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>List the questions you will address</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “This essay will examine [Question 1] and [Question 2], before offering a conclusion.”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="body-paragraph-1-answer-to-question-1" class="level2" data-number="6.2">
<h2 data-number="6.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="body-paragraph-1-answer-to-question-1"><span class="header-section-number">6.2</span> Body Paragraph 1 – Answer to Question 1</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Topic sentence</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “First, regarding [Question 1], [state your main answer].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explanation</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “This is because [elaborate on your answer].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Example or evidence</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “For instance, [real or hypothetical example].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Link back</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “Therefore, [restate how this answers Question&nbsp;1].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="body-paragraph-2-answer-to-question-2" class="level2" data-number="6.3">
<h2 data-number="6.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="body-paragraph-2-answer-to-question-2"><span class="header-section-number">6.3</span> Body Paragraph 2 – Answer to Question 2</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Topic sentence</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “Second, when considering [Question 2], [state your main answer].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Explanation</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “This means that [elaborate on your answer].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Example or evidence</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “For example, [real or hypothetical example].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Link back</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “Thus, [restate how this answers Question&nbsp;2].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="optional-body-paragraph-3-answer-to-question-3" class="level2" data-number="6.4">
<h2 data-number="6.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="optional-body-paragraph-3-answer-to-question-3"><span class="header-section-number">6.4</span> (Optional) Body Paragraph 3 – Answer to Question 3</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>If a third question is asked</strong>, repeat the same structure.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-3" class="level2" data-number="6.5">
<h2 data-number="6.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-3"><span class="header-section-number">6.5</span> Conclusion</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Summarise your answers</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “In conclusion, [briefly restate answer to Question&nbsp;1] and [briefly restate answer to Question&nbsp;2].”<br>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Final thought (optional)</strong>
<ul>
<li>E.g. “Overall, addressing these issues will require [brief recommendation or implication].”</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="linking-words-phrases-2" class="level2" data-number="6.6">
<h2 data-number="6.6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linking-words-phrases-2"><span class="header-section-number">6.6</span> Linking Words &amp; Phrases</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Introducing answers:</strong> <em>First, Second, Moreover</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Explaining:</strong> <em>This is because, In other words, That is to say</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Examples:</strong> <em>For example, For instance, A good illustration is</em><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Concluding:</strong> <em>In conclusion, To sum up, Overall</em></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/ielts-essay-template/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agriculture</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/essay-agriculture/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>In spite of the advances made in agriculture, many people around the world still go hungry. Why is this the case? What can be done about this problem? Give reasons for your answer and include any relevant examples from your own experience or knowledge. Write at least 250 words.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Recent years have witnessed tremendous developments in agricultural science yet every day people all over the world continue to suffer and even die from hunger. In my opinion, this is because innovations rarely impact the developing world and the best solution for it is to direct humanitarian funding towards these advances.</p>
<p>The main cause of more advanced agricultural methods not reaching the people who need it the most is that the developing world has trouble implementing these methods. There are a number of reasons for this ranging from limited financial resources to poor existing infrastructure to political instability, depending on the country in question. One example of this would be in many African nations, where malnourishment has historically been highest. Countries like the Congo have seen revolution after revolution over the last several decades, which has effectively destabilized the entire country. The universities where students would learn about changes in agriculture are frequently shut down or destroyed. The young people who would become agricultural scientists end up drawn into the conflict as soldiers or victims. Long-term economic neglect means that the government has very limited ability to subsidies farming. These problems are present to varying degrees in countries around the world and offer one possible explanation for the continued prevalence of hunger.</p>
<p>The solution that I believe would be most effective is directing humanitarian funds previously focused on food aid towards education and agriculture. Food aid is a notoriously poor solution because it only offers an immediate solution and warlords often exploit it to support their continued mistreatment of their people. It hurts more than it helps. However, there would be better long-term effects if international organizations and governments redirects that money into helping build better farms, provide more modern equipment, and sending qualified professions to train people in need. There is a TedTalk by a young man in Kenya who built his own windmill out of old bicycle parts and reading a book in the local library. It is large enough to power irrigation channels for the entire village. If more people like him can be found or trained when this will have an impact that lasts for decades and is relatively impervious to the factors preventing agricultural advances from taking root in developing countries.</p>
<p>In conclusion, developing companies face myriad problems that hinder their ability to take advantage of newer agricultural models and we should direct more funding to helping these countries learn more about new farming methods. This is likely to be an important issue in the world as the gap between rich and poor, developed and undeveloped widens while technological progress continues its indifferent march forward.</p>
<section id="key-academic-vocabulary" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Key Academic Vocabulary</h1>
<p>Nouns/nominalisations: developments, innovations, humanitarian funding, infrastructure, instability, malnourishment, subsidies, exploitation, irrigation, prevalence, technological progress</p>
<p>Verbs: suffer, destabilize, implement, exploit, redirect, power, widen</p>
<p>Adjectives/adverbs: tremendous, advanced, limited, poor, political, historical(ly), immediate, long-term, modern, qualified, relative(ly), impervious, indifferent</p>
</section>
<section id="linking-signposting-phrases" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Linking &amp; Signposting Phrases</h1>
<p>Contrast: yet, however, but</p>
<p>Cause/Reason: because, depending on, due to</p>
<p>Example: one example (of this) would be</p>
<p>Condition: if…, then…</p>
<p>Addition/Sequence: and, also</p>
<p>Conclusion: in conclusion</p>
</section>
<section id="grammar-structures" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Grammar Structures</h1>
<p>Complex sentences with multiple clauses:</p>
<p>“There are a number of reasons for this ranging from X to Y…”</p>
<p>“The universities where students would learn… are frequently shut down.”</p>
<p>Relative clauses: “countries where…”, “…methods that…”</p>
<p>Conditionals (first): “If more people like him can be found…, this will have an impact.”</p>
<p>Passive voice: “are frequently shut down or destroyed.”</p>
<p>Nominalisation to pack information: “the continued prevalence of hunger.”</p>
</section>
<section id="sentence-building-techniques" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Sentence-building Techniques</h1>
<p>Topic sentence → elaboration → example in each body paragraph</p>
<p>Balance of simple/simple-compound sentences (“However, there would be better long-term effects…” vs.&nbsp;“It is large enough to power irrigation channels for the entire village.”)</p>
<p>Abstract–Concrete pairing: stating a general problem then giving a vivid, specific case (Congo revolutions; Kenyan windmill).</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>cause and solution</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/essay-agriculture/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IELTS Cambridge 16 Essay - Driverless Vehicles</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/driverless-vehicles/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>In the future all cars, buses and trucks will be driverless. The only people travelling inside these vehicles will be passengers.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Do you think the advantages of driverless vehicles outweigh the disadvantages?</strong></p>
<p>A future filled with driverless vehicles is an inevitability. In my opinion, though there are concomitant moral risks, the practical import for health such a seismic shift will be positive on the whole.</p>
<p>Critics of this trend suggest that machines should not be responsible for the potential loss of human life. This argument rests on the fact when there is an accident involving humans, it is possible to either assess blame and assign punishment or accept that human error played a role. In contrast, an individual severely injured as the result of a collision caused by a machine may justly feel that all human autonomy and free will is absent from their fate. This is analogous to a natural disaster with the crucial distinction being that humanity has engineered the situation. It is human nature to prefer to control a situation rather than surrender the outcome to an autonomous machine.</p>
<p>Proponents of automated vehicles, on the other hand, argue the tangible ramifications concerning public safety. The evidence overwhelmingly suggests that driverless vehicles cause fewer accidents than humans. The reason for this is that humans are prone to errors related to fatigue, distractions such as smartphones, and, in some cases, altered states. Machines might experience the occasional technical error, however, they are far more consistent by comparison. In fact, the few accidents that have occurred with automated vehicles were the fault of human drivers. If all cars were driverless, this would enabled a greater</p>
<hr>
<p>In the coming years, it is predicted that all vehicles, including cars, buses, and trucks, will operate autonomously without human drivers. While this development may raise some concerns, I firmly believe that the advantages of driverless transportation far outweigh the disadvantages.</p>
<p>One major advantage of autonomous vehicles is improved road safety. The majority of traffic accidents today are caused by human error, including distracted driving, fatigue, and impaired judgment. Driverless vehicles, on the other hand, rely on advanced sensors, algorithms, and machine learning, which allow them to make precise decisions and maintain constant awareness of their surroundings, can process vast amount of data in real time and react faster than any human driver. This can greatly reduce accidents, save lives, and lower the burden on healthcare systems. In addition, driverless technology could improve traffic flow and reduce congestion by enabling vehicles to communicate and coordinate more efficiency.</p>
<p>However, this transformation is not without drawbacks. A major concern is job loss among professional drivers, including taxi drivers, truckers, and bus operators. The widespread adoption of autonomous vehicles could lead to large-scale unemployment in these sectors. Moreover, ethical challenges arise in situations where a vehicle must choose between two harmful outcomes, raising questions about how machines should be programmed to make such decisions.</p>
<p>Despite these issues, I believe that the long-term benefits are more compelling. The reduction in traffic accidents, the potential for greater mobility for elderly and disabled individuals, and the increase in productivity for commuters are all powerful advantages. With proactive government policies, including retraining programs and strong ethical guidelines for AI systems, the negative impacts can be mitigated.</p>
<p>In conclusion, although there are valid concerns about the rise of driverless vehicles, particularly regarding employment and ethics, the positive impacts on safety, efficiency, and accessibility make this a highly promising development. Therefore, I believe the advantages clearly outweight the disadvantages.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>advantage disadvantage</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/driverless-vehicles/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>IELTS Essay- Line Chart Social Center</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/line-chart-social-center/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/line-chart-social-center/Pasted image 20250602163817.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>David Lang essay:</p>
<p>The line chart details participants according to activity at a social center in the Australian city of Melbourne from 2000 to 2020. Looking from an overall perspective, it is readily apparent that participants for all activities increased to varying degrees except in terms of martial arts and amateur drama. Film club was by far the most popular activity throughout, though table tennis demonstrated the strongest growth.</p>
<p>In 2000, 64 individuals participated in the film club, a figure that dipped to 60 in 2010 and then more than recovered to finish the period at 65. The trend for martial arts was similarly stable with a beginning data point of 38, a high of 39 in 2010, and a final figure of 37.</p>
<p>The remaining activities started the period lower with 27 participants for amateur drama, 18 for table tennis, and 0 for musical performances (unavailable at the time). Over the next 10 years, amateur dramatics commenced a decline that would end at just 5 by 2020, while table tennis underwent the inverse transformation, peaking at 52 by the same year. Musical performances were only an option starting in 2005, with participants growing and leveling off to just under 20 by the end of the period.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>time</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/line-chart-social-center/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Task 1 Recycle paper</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-recycle-paper/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-recycle-paper/Pasted image 20250419165220.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>David Lang</p>
<p>The diagram details how recycled paper is made. Looking from an overall perspective, it is readily apparent that the process involves three main stages beginning with initial collection and transportation, followed by cleaning and processing, and lastly the rolling of the final product. The process is entirely man-made.</p>
<p>In order to produce recycled paper, used paper is first sourced and transported by conveyor belt to a processing plant. The used paper is then made into unfiltered pulp by using water and various chemicals. The pulp must then be filtered with water being removed.</p>
<p>After filtering is complete, the filtered paper pulp is sent by a tube to a container with water and soap to be further cleaned. Air is pumped into the container and ink is removed. There is then an additional cleaning with water and chemicals before the final rolling states commence. To create useable recycled paper rolls, the cleaned and filtered pulp is placed on a conveyor belt where heated rollers flatten the paper and remove excess water.</p>
<p>Chat GPT</p>
<ul>
<li>Overall process: cyclical but shown in a linear step-by-step format.</li>
<li>Number of stages: 4 main stages - making pulp, filtering, cleaning, and making paper.</li>
<li>Raw material: Used paper.</li>
<li>End product: Recycled paper rolls.</li>
<li>Materials/chemicals used: Water</li>
<li>Key step:</li>
</ul>
<ol type="1">
<li>Used paper transported on a conveyor belt.</li>
<li>Mixed with water and chemicals - pulp.</li>
<li>Filtered to remove larger impurities.</li>
<li>Cleaned using soap, air, water -&gt; removes ink.</li>
<li>Final cleaned pulp used to make paper -&gt; heated rollers + drying.</li>
</ol>
<p>Useful vocab: - Recycled materials - Industrial process - Mechanical separation - De-inking - Environmental sustainability</p>
<p>The diagram illustrates the step-by-step process involved in the production of recycled paper from used paper materials. The procedure consists of four main stages, starting with the creation of pulp and culminating in the manufacture of new paper rolls.</p>
<p>In the first stage, used paper is placed on a conveyor belt and carried to a machine where it is mixed with water and chemicals. This mixture breaks the paper down into unfiltered pulp. The pulp then moves to the next stage where is it filtered. This step removes large unwanted materials, leaving behind filtered pulp.</p>
<p>In the third stage, the filtered pulp is cleaned using water, soap, and air. This helps separate and remove ink from the pulp. Water and additional chemicals are also added to enhance the cleaning process. As a result, the pulp becomes cleaner and suitable for making new paper.</p>
<p>Finally, the cleaned pulp is transferred onto a conveyor belt and passed through heated rollers. These rollers press and dry the material, forming sheets of recycled paper, which are then rolled up for reuse.</p>
<section id="environment" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="environment"><strong>Environment</strong></h4>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>How are environmental problems dealt with in your country? In my country, environmental issues are taken seriously, but there’s still a long way to go. The government has made some rules about pollution and waste, and there are programs to plant more trees. But I think sometimes the laws are not enforced strictly, and people still throw garbage in the wrong places. In my country, environmental problems are addressed through a combination of legislation and public awareness campaigns. For instance, the government has introduced stricter regulations on industrial emissions and waste disposal. However, enforcement remains inconsistent, and public participation <strong>is not as widespread as it could be</strong>, which limits the overall effectiveness of these measures.</p></li>
<li><p>What can be done to make people recycle more often? I think if people know more about the benefits of recycling, they might do it more. Also, the government can give rewards or discounts to people who recycle. Putting more recycling bins around cities would help too. To encourage more frequent recycling, a combination of education and incentives could be effective. Public awareness campaigns can highlight the environmental and economic benefits of recycling, while practical steps- like providing more accessible recycling bins and offering financial incentives - can make the habit easier to adopt. Legislation that mandates in households and businesses could also play a significant role.</p></li>
<li><p>What is the most pressing environmental problem? In my opinion, the biggest problem is air pollution, especially in big cities. The air quality is really bad because of cars and factories. It affects people’s health, and it’s hard to fix quickly. Arguably, climate change is the most urgent environmental issue we face today. It not only exacerbates other problems like extreme weather and rising sea levels but also poses serious threats to biodiversity and food security. While localized issues like air pollution are severe, climate change has a truly global impact that requires immediate and coordinated action.</p></li>
<li><p>Is recycling a common practice in your country? Recycling is becoming more common, but it’s not something everyone does. Some people separate their trash at home, but many still throw everything together. It depends a lot on where you live - cities usually have more systems in place. Recycling is practiced in many parts of the country, particularly in urban areas where infrastructure is more developed. However, it’s far from universal. While some individuals and communities are highly conscientious, others lack access to proper facilities or are simply unaware of how to recycle effectively. So, it’s growing, but still inconsistent.</p></li>
<li><p>Are governments or individuals more responsible? I think both are responsible. The government needs to make good rules and make people follow the, but individuals also need to care about the environment and take action. It’s a shared responsibility. While both governents and individuals play vital roles, I believe governents bear greater responsibility due to their ability to enact policies, regulate industries, and invest in sustainable infrastructure. That said, individual behavior is equally crucial, as collective action often stes fro personal choices. Ideally, both should work hand in hand to address environental issues effectively.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>process</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/english-recycle-paper/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
