<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Kim Hung&#39;s ThinkStack</title>
<link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>My Personal Website</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Lesson 10: DEVELOPING THINKING and PLANNING SKILLS</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-10/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="getting-ideas---developing-thinking-skills" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Getting ideas - developing thinking skills</h1>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-10/CleanShot 2025-09-27 at 23.38.43@2x.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>List theme, and find ideas in each theme</p>
<p>The best way to have good ideas is to have lots of ideas an throw away the bad ones</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-10/CleanShot 2025-09-27 at 23.38.33@2x.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-10/CleanShot 2025-09-27 at 23.40.21@2x.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-10/CleanShot 2025-09-27 at 23.40.36@2x.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-10/CleanShot 2025-09-27 at 23.41.07@2x.png" class="img-fluid"> # Planning</p>
</section>
<section id="a-step-by-step-guide-to-essay-writing" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> A step-by-step guide to essay writing</h1>
<p>Learning a new language can be challenging. While many people are able to do this in their own country, some choose to travel aboard to help with their studies. There are advantages and disadvantages to this.</p>
<p>The disadvantages of doing a language course overseas are significant. Firstly, there is the cost to consider. As well as flights and tuition fees, money is needed for day-to-day expenses, such as food and accommodation. Indeed, it may be too expensive for many. In addition, living away from family and friends can lead to loneliness, and being surrounded by a strange new culture can increase this sense of isolation. Such problems can even be severe enough to interfere with learning, thus defeating the object of the trip.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, these issues can generally be resolved, and there are definite rewards to studying a language in the country where it is the mother tongue. Although it may be expensive, students can get a part-time job to help meet their needs. Through work and school, they can socialize and make friends, and are likely to feel less homesick as a result. Any new culture feels strange at first, but it is also exciting and creates a much richer language learning experience; for example, through being able to enjoy the literature and music of the country. Furthermore, the access to native speaker teachers, and the total immersion in the language means it is possible to reach a far higher level than in your home town. Clearly, there is a lot to be gained from an opportunity like this.</p>
<p>To sum up, although some may struggle to adapt to the new culture and deal with financial issues, those who overcome these problems will undoubtedly be enriched by this invaluable experience. Therefore, in my view, the potential benefits more than make up for any disadvantages.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-10/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Zoo</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-zoo/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Keeping animals in captivity is cruel. There is no reason for zoos to exist in the 21st century.</p>
<p>How far do you agree or disagree with this opinion?</p>
<p>Around the world, people have differing opinions about zoos. Some people believe that keeping animals in captivity is wrong, while others contend that it is necessary and that we need zoos. In this essay, I will explore both of these views, as they each have some merit, before drawing a conclusion.</p>
<p>Proponents of zoos tend to argue that these places are intended to educate the public about animals. They claim that people can go to zoos and become more aware of serious environmental issues, and therefore, zoos are essential in raising awareness of serious issues. For example, children can visit zoos and learn about the majestic elephant, and then adapt their behavior to become more responsible people in the future. However, this argument assumes that all zoos treat their purpose as education, when in fact many zoos are geared towards entertainment, and many people come away from a zoo visit having learned relatively little.</p>
<p>Opponents of zoos claim that it is cruel to keep animals in captivity, and that therefore they belong in the wild. They point to numerous studies that show the suffering experienced by animals in even the best zoos. This is clear from evidence that many large animals require extensive space to roam that is just not available for them in their artificial enclosures, and so they suffer serious psychological and even physical damage. The fact that animals almost always live shorter lives in zoos is further proof of this fact.</p>
<p>In conclusion, although there are some good reasons for the existence of zoos, they probably should not be allowed to continue into the twenty-first century. Despite the positive efforts of some zoos, the suffering experienced by animals in captivity is simply unacceptable.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-zoo/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cutting Tools</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w1-diagram-rock/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The diagram below shows the development of cutting tools in the Stone Age <img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w1-diagram-rock/Pasted image 20250922093627.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The diagram illustrates the evolution of the cutting tool during the period from 1.4 million years ago to 0.8 million years ago in the Stone Age.</p>
<p>It can be seen that a number of upgrades were made in the shape and size of the tool so that it could become a more effective cutting instrument.</p>
<p>1.4 million years ago, the tool was relatively primitive and resembled a natural stone, which suggests that little crafting was done. From the front and side view, Tool A had an oval shape, rough surface and blunt edges, hence presumably the inferior version compared to Tool B.</p>
<p>After 0.6 million years, the tool was upgraded into a spear-shaped instrument with the tip and edges being much sharper. While tool B was 10 centimeters long - the same length as Tool A, the surface of Tool B was crafted to be smoother and the overall width to be larger. Therefore, these features rendered this version more superior in terms of cutting effeciency.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>task-1</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w1-diagram-rock/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lesson 9: ESSAY STRUCTURE: Introduction, Body paragraph, Conclusion</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-9/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="the-introduction" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> The introduction</h1>
<section id="the-introduction-1" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-introduction-1"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> The introduction</h2>
<p>There are no fixed governing what an introduction should look like or how many sentences it should contain. There are some key features to point out</p>
<section id="key-features-of-an-introduction" class="level3" data-number="1.1.1">
<h3 data-number="1.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-features-of-an-introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.1</span> Key features of an introduction</h3>
<p>Our introduction briefly tells the reader what they need to know before reading our argument. It should answer several questions:</p>
<p><em>What is the topic and focus of this essay? (i.e.&nbsp;the context for this essay)</em></p>
<p><em>What is the main issue or point that will be discussed in your essay?</em></p>
<p>Although this is only a short paragraph, there are varying approaches to how to write it, which appear to cause quite a lot of confusion. Because of this, there are some recurring problems. The first three have one common thread: getting started.</p>
</section>
<section id="problem-1---misrepresenting-the-question" class="level3" data-number="1.1.2">
<h3 data-number="1.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-1---misrepresenting-the-question"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.2</span> Problem 1 - Misrepresenting the question</h3>
<p>Many people are so keen to get started in their writing that they quickly skim read the test question. This can mean that they jump to a conclusion about what it means, or misinterpret it, and then misrepresent it in their introduction. The idea in their body paragraphs then move further and further away from the issue raised in the question, compounding the problem. Some candidates identify only the broad general topic within the question and write about this instead of the very specific issue they were asked to discuss.</p>
</section>
<section id="problem-2---making-a-general-statement" class="level3" data-number="1.1.3">
<h3 data-number="1.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-2---making-a-general-statement"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.3</span> Problem 2 - Making a general statement</h3>
<p>Some people tell, ‘<em>I like to begin with a general statement</em>’. The danger here is that these are so general that they do not seem relevant to the issue raised in the question. Others begin their essays in a very rehearsed way that is often not accurate. For example, ‘<em>This is an often debated topic</em>’. Or ‘<em>This is a controversial topic</em>’, when in fact the issue in the question is not a common topic of conversation, or is rather mundane.</p>
</section>
<section id="problem-3---trying-to-use-a-hook" class="level3" data-number="1.1.4">
<h3 data-number="1.1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-3---trying-to-use-a-hook"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.4</span> Problem 3 - Trying to use a ‘hook’</h3>
<p>Some people begin an introduction with a ‘hook’, such as an interesting fact or statistic. Hooks are used by professional writers to grab the attention of the reader. Our examiner does not need to be persuaded to read our answer, and they do not need to be entertained by our writing. Even more importantly, a hook can seem out of place in a formal discursive essay, and they often seem irrelevant to the question.</p>
</section>
<section id="solution-1-read-the-test-question-carefully" class="level3" data-number="1.1.5">
<h3 data-number="1.1.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="solution-1-read-the-test-question-carefully"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.5</span> Solution 1: Read the test question carefully</h3>
<p>Although it is the first paragraph in our essay, our introduction should not be the starting point of our writing; we need to think carefully about the question, then think through and plan our whole argument first. We will never be asked to simply discuss a very broad topic such as ‘pollution’ or ‘technology’, so keep reading until we have fully understood exactly issue we are being asked to write about.</p>
<p>Pay particular attention to the words and phrases in the question that indicate the claim or argument that is being made, because this is what we must respond to in our answer to achieve a good Task response score. Typical words and phrases to look for are:</p>
<p><em>should, should always; should not; would be better; the only way; the best way, etc</em></p>
<p>If there are any words in the question we do not know, read the whole question again more slowly. Skilled test writers try to help us understand words or ideas, either by giving an example, or using paraphrase, so take the time to look for these clues. Look at the following example:</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Some people believe that parents should be responsible for teaching children right from wrong. Others think that schools should also teach children to behave well.</p>
<p>Discuss both these views and give your own opinion.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Some candidates might not know the phrase ‘<em>to teach right from wrong</em>’, so the second sentence paraphrases this idea with ‘<em>teaching children to behave well</em>’, helping to explain it. This is done deliberately at the test writing stage, so make sure we use all of the help that is there in the question.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Don’t quickly skim read the question so that you can start writing as soon as possible. Take the time to read it carefully; identify the issue you must discuss and the argument you must respond to. Look for clues within the question to help you understand the meaning of key ideas.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="solution-2-begin-with-a-general-statement" class="level3" data-number="1.1.6">
<h3 data-number="1.1.6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="solution-2-begin-with-a-general-statement"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.6</span> Solution 2: Begin with a general statement</h3>
<p>Our first sentence should introduce the broad topic and thus set the context for our essay. Although this is quite a general statement, it should still be relevant to the question and to our argument.</p>
<p>Accurately identifying the general topic in the question is an important first step.</p>
</section>
<section id="problem-4---translating-the-words-in-the-question" class="level3" data-number="1.1.7">
<h3 data-number="1.1.7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-4---translating-the-words-in-the-question"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.7</span> Problem 4 - ‘Translating’ the words in the question</h3>
<p>Having set the overall context in our first sentence, the next sentence will introduce the reader to the issue that is going to be discussed. Many people already know that you should avoid copying directly from the question, but then go too far by substituting each word with a synonym.</p>
</section>
<section id="solution" class="level3" data-number="1.1.8">
<h3 data-number="1.1.8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="solution"><span class="header-section-number">1.1.8</span> Solution</h3>
<p>Although it is true that we should not copy large parts of the question, this does not mean you have to avoid <strong>all</strong> of the words, which may have been used because they are the most appropriate or the most natural. For example, ‘<em>Some people</em>’ is the most natural way to talk about an anonymous group; we don’t use ‘<em>Numerous individuals</em>’ or ‘<em>humans</em>’, in the same way. Similarly, ‘<em>teachers</em>’ is a better word to use than ‘<em>educational scholars</em>’ and ‘<em>children</em>’ is more natural than ‘<em>youths</em>’.</p>
<p>Rather than translating the words in the question, aim to <em>interpret</em> the overall meaning as precisely as we can. It can sometimes help to change the statement we are given into a question. This has the additional advantage of making our task clearer.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="identifying-common-themes" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="identifying-common-themes"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> Identifying common themes</h2>
<section id="exercise" class="level3" data-number="1.2.1">
<h3 data-number="1.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercise"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.1</span> Exercise</h3>
<p>Complete the following introduction to our essay question using these words and phrases</p>
<p>at school, grow up, discipline, teach</p>
<p>Discipline is an important part of growing up. Some people believe that children should <em>be taught</em> how to behave at school, while others think this is the job of their parents.</p>
<p>What common themes do you think you might write about in an essay about</p>
<p>one of the 4 general topics in the table below?</p>
<p>Look at the following list of common themes and decide which of the general</p>
<p>topics in the table they match. Write the words and phrases in the appropriate</p>
<p>column.</p>
<p>Common themes:</p>
<p>accommodation, curriculum, doctors, diet, entertainment, exercise, free time,</p>
<p>friends and family, food, going out, hospitals, holidays, medicine, money,</p>
<p>nursing, pressure, resources, socialising, students, study, the arts, teachers,</p>
<p>work</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Education</th>
<th>Life / Living</th>
<th>Health</th>
<th>Entertainment</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>students</td>
<td>accommodation</td>
<td>diet</td>
<td>going out</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>curriculum</td>
<td>free time</td>
<td>doctors</td>
<td>holiday</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>students</td>
<td>friend and family</td>
<td>exercise</td>
<td>socializing</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>study</td>
<td>money</td>
<td>food</td>
<td>the arts</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>teacher</td>
<td>pressure</td>
<td>hospitals</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td></td>
<td>resources</td>
<td>medicine</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>nursing</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Look at the following list of opening sentences taken from essays discussing whether: ‘being a celebrity brings more benefits or more challenges’.</p>
<p>Decide whether the sentences introduce the focus and the general topic of this essay well and identify any problems (You may need to select more than one box). Click on ‘Show answers’ to see my comments.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 1%">
<col style="width: 13%">
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 15%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 23%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>introduces the focus of the essay</th>
<th>introduces the general topic of the essay</th>
<th>introduces the issue raised in the question</th>
<th>translates the question into synonyms</th>
<th>misrepresents the question</th>
<th>a good opening sentence for an introduction to this essay</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>3</td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>4</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>It is true that when ambitious people follows their dreams, they achieve their goals at certain stage.</p></li>
<li><p>It is an undeniable fact that eminent personalities are followed by almost everyone since the days bygone.</p></li>
<li><p>It is argued that stardom does not only beget prosperity but also complications.</p></li>
<li><p>Fame and its impact on the lifestyle of celebrities fascinates many people.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>ANSWER:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 1%">
<col style="width: 13%">
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 15%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 23%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>introduces the focus of the essay</th>
<th>introduces the general topic of the essay</th>
<th>introduces the issue raised in the question</th>
<th>translates the question into synonyms</th>
<th>misrepresents the question</th>
<th>a good opening sentence for an introduction to this essay</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>3</td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>4</td>
<td>x</td>
<td>x</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>x</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>In sentence 1, the focus is not accurate - this is about famous people, not ambitious people. The general topic is not accurate (the topic is the impact that fame has)</p>
<p>In sentence 2, the general topic is not accurate: ‘eminent personalities’ is an attempt to translate the question using synonyms but ‘eminent’ people (people who are important in society) are not the focus of this essay.</p>
<p>Sentence 3 translates the words in the question into synonyms and also introduces the issue rather than the focus and general topic.</p>
<p>Sentence 4 is a good opening sentence - the focus and general topic are clear. As you will see later, the phrase ‘fascinates many people’ introduces a theme that will occur later in the essay. ## Paraphrasing</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="problem-5---making-an-argument-within-your-introduction" class="level2" data-number="1.3">
<h2 data-number="1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-5---making-an-argument-within-your-introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1.3</span> Problem 5 - Making an argument within your introduction</h2>
<p>Solution</p>
<p>If you decide to include a thesis statement in your introduction, you need to:</p>
<p>be fully aware of your position and main argument before writing it</p>
<p>give only a brief overview of your thesis (in one sentence)</p>
<p>make sure your thesis accurately reflects the argument you will make in your body paragraphs</p>
</section>
<section id="problem-6---ending-your-introduction" class="level2" data-number="1.4">
<h2 data-number="1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-6---ending-your-introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1.4</span> Problem 6 - Ending your introduction</h2>
<p>Some candidates finish their introduction with a sentence that paraphrases the final question in the writing task. For example, ‘<em>In this essay I will discuss these two views before giving my own opinion</em>’. This copy the words in the task almost exactly, which is not a good idea. Others draw attention to the writing process in a different way: ‘<em>I will now prove that…</em>’. Again, this is unnecessary - your examiners knows <strong>why</strong> you are writing; In our introduction, they just want to learn <strong>what</strong> you are writing about.</p>
<p>Solution</p>
<p>Don’t paraphrase the question itself, only focus on the topic and the issue that will be discussed. Aim to write in a less personal way - keep the focus on your essay, not on yourself as the writer. For example, it is better to write: ‘<em>This essay will discuss …</em>’ instead of ‘<em>In this essay I will discuss…</em>’</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-body-paragraph" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> The body paragraph</h1>
<p>Your body paragraphs are made up of sentences that connect together to form one unit; each sentence is rather like a small building block that helps create one larger building block within your overall argument. The reader should be able to identify the central topic from your first and last sentences, and this same topic should be reflected in the sentences in between, which each serve to explain and support your main ideas.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-9/CleanShot 2025-09-27 at 22.59.35@2x.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Look at how the first and the last sentences from the band 9 paragraph</p>
<p>Schools</p>
<section id="problem-1---a-lack-of-a-clear-argument-and-clear-central-topic" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-1---a-lack-of-a-clear-argument-and-clear-central-topic"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Problem 1 - A lack of a clear argument and clear central topic</h2>
</section>
<section id="problem-2---long-confusing-sentences" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-2---long-confusing-sentences"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Problem 2 - Long confusing sentences</h2>
<section id="solution-1" class="level3" data-number="2.2.1">
<h3 data-number="2.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="solution-1"><span class="header-section-number">2.2.1</span> Solution</h3>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Think of each sentence in your paragraph as having a clear purpose. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Introducing an argument - (presenting your main central roles)</li>
<li>Giving a reason for believing a conclusion you have reached</li>
<li>Showing an effect (to help support your conclusion)</li>
<li>Explaining or expanding (to clarify your context, a key term, or an idea)</li>
<li>Giving an example (to support your conclusion)</li>
<li>Concluding an argument or paragraph (summing up the main idea and showing how it links to the question)</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="problem-3---one-paragraph-is-more-successful-than-another" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-3---one-paragraph-is-more-successful-than-another"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Problem 3 - One paragraph is more successful than another</h2>
<section id="solution-2" class="level3" data-number="2.3.1">
<h3 data-number="2.3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="solution-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.3.1</span> Solution</h3>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-conclusion" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> The conclusion</h1>
<p>Problems</p>
<p>Make sure to write at least two sentences in your conclusion. The first should summarise the main</p>
<p>ideas in your argument. To help with this, look back at the first and last sentences in each body</p>
<p>paragraph and summarise these. In your final sentence, make sure to answer the question you were</p>
<p>given. In other words, make it clear whether you believe the advantages outweigh the disadvantages;</p>
<p>whether this is a positive or a negative development; or the extent to which you agree or disagree etc.</p>
<p>The biggest problems I see in conclusions are:</p>
<p>conclusions that are too short (often one sentence only)</p>
<p>summarising only one idea rather than the main points in the argument</p>
<p>not answering the question (i.e.&nbsp;not saying to what extent you agree / disagree etc.)</p>
<p>introducing a new idea that has not been discussed or mentioned earlier</p>
<p>Words and phrases should use:</p>
<p><em>To sum up, ; In conclusion, ; Therefore, ; I completely agree / disagree ; In my view, etc</em></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-9/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lesson 8: PARAGRAPH WRITING</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-8/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="progression-and-development-within-an-argument" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Progression and development within an argument</h1>
<p>As we have seen, individual arguments are logically connected through meaning, the effective use of linking words and phrases, and referencing (using a synonym or pronoun). In an earlier example we looked at, one candidate wrote, ‘<em>On the societal level, <u>the results</u> may be catastrophic if this is the case</em>’. This argument can only show clear progression if the reader can easily understand what the terms ‘<em>if this is the case</em>’, and ‘<em>the results</em>’ refer to. If these ideas remain unclear, then the whole argument will also be unclear. Thus, problems with progression are often connected to problems with cohesive devices, and to referencing in particular. These issues need to be controlled <strong>throughout your essay</strong> to achieve band 7 or above.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-8/Pasted image 20250916181359.png" class="img-fluid"> # Addressing Coherence and cohesion problems</p>
<ul>
<li>Use cohesive devices effectively but cohesion between sentences is faulty</li>
<li>does not always use referencing clearly</li>
</ul>
<p>This paragraph shows mixed success in using cohesive devices. Here are some examples where these are managed well</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<ul>
<li>Children spend the largest part of <font color="#245bdb">their day</font></li>
<li><font color="#245bdb">at school, where</font> the teachers can</li>
<li>knowledge that is <font color="#245bdb">not only</font> important for their career, <font color="#245bdb">but that can also</font></li>
<li>in many different ways,<font color="#245bdb"> for instance through</font></li>
<li><font color="#245bdb">Additionally</font>, children become</li>
<li><font color="#245bdb">at school, where</font> often <font color="#245bdb">they</font></li>
<li>dress up like great leaders. <font color="#245bdb">While doing this, they</font></li>
<li><font color="#245bdb">Therefore</font>, the role of</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>Each of these examples is a clear signpost showing how two ideas are connected - this is what cohesion means. However, the use of referencing sometimes causes confusion, making it difficult to follow the ideas</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-8/Pasted image 20250916180552.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-8/Pasted image 20250916180559.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Even though we have fixed the referencing problems, the second sentence in the final exercises shows a further common coherence problem at band 6.5: it contains too many different ideas and so it is difficult to follow</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>While doing this, the students become curious and want to know more about these people, which can encourage the children to emulate their qualities, which consequently become integrated into their own personality.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>This often happens when candidates write overly long, complex sentences.</p>
<p>Rewrite this extract to make it clearer. Try to do the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>split it into 2 or 3 separate sentences</li>
<li>add a cohesive device to make the links clearer (e.g.&nbsp;a linking phrase and / or a reference)</li>
<li>add modal verbs (can, might, may) to make the statements more cautious and less certain (hedging language)</li>
</ul>
<p>While doing this, the students become curious and want to know more about these people. That thinking can encourage the children to emulate their qualities, which consequently become integrated into their own personality.</p>
<p>Weaknesses: Curiosity is not exactly ‘thinking’. A smoother option would be “<em>This curiosity</em>” or “<em>Such interest</em>”</p>
<p>While doing this, the students become curious and want to know more about these people. This curiosity can encourage the students to emulate those qualities, which then become integrated into their own personality.</p>
<p>-&gt;</p>
<p>While doing this, the students <span style="background:#fff88f">may</span> become curious and want to know more about these people, which <span style="background:#fff88f">could</span> encourage the children to emulate their qualities. These positive traits <span style="background:#fff88f">may even</span> become integrated into their personality.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>While doing this, they <span style="background:#fff88f">may</span> become curious and want to know more about these leaders, which <span style="background:#fff88f">could</span> encourage the children to emulate their qualities. These positive traits <span style="background:#fff88f">may even</span> become integrated into their personality.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The examiner must be able to follow your reasoning to give you a score of band 7 or above, the more difficult this is to do, the lower your score. The language you use (referencing, modal verbs, the length of your sentences) can have an impact on the examiner’s ability to follow your argument and understand your conclusions.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="reading-aloud" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reading-aloud"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Reading aloud</h2>
<p>Reading our writing out loud in can helps you to notice repetition more easily. Although we cannot do this in a test situation, practicing like this before our test should help us silently read over our work in a more focused way. We can make inner voice seem ‘louder’ when we want to do this type of final checking.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-lack-of-clear-central-topic" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-lack-of-clear-central-topic"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> A lack of clear central topic</h2>
<p>We have a method for writing a paragraph known as PEEL. The P refer to making a Point, which is then Explained, Expanded, then clearly Links back to the question. The Point and Link also act as a frame for the main idea within the paragraph, and these are a good way to ensure that we ‘present a clear central topic’ (Band 7) - provided, that these sentences accurately reflect the idea within the paragraph. Look at the first and last sentences in our updated paragraph. Do you think that these help to ‘present a clear central topic?’</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Children spend the largest part of their day at school, where the teachers can cultivate their minds and fill them with knowledge that is not only important for their career, but that can also help them grow into wise adults. They can mentor the students in many different ways, for instance through books or group activities, where they can learn to tell right from wrong. In addition, children become engaged in various extra-curricular activities at school, where they are often asked to dress up like great leaders. While doing so, the students may become curious and want to know more about these people, which could encourage the children to emulate their qualities. These positive traits may even become integrated into their own personality. Therefore, the role of schools in instilling good behavior is much more crucial than that of the parent.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="the-first-sentence" class="level3" data-number="1.2.1">
<h3 data-number="1.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-first-sentence"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.1</span> The first sentence</h3>
<p>The first sentence tells us that the central topic in this paragraph will be: ‘<em>school and teachers cultivating the minds of children to fill them with knowledge that is important for their career and helping them grow into wise adults.</em>’ This is too long and complex to be a helpful signpost for the reader, but it also isn’t accurate - the children’s careers are never mentioned again. This sentence would work better as a second sentence, which shows a common problem - the first sentence of the paragraph is missing. The writer’s overall argument in this paragraph seems to be that ‘<em>schools have a lot of influence on children’s behavior</em>’, so this idea would produce a much more appropriate first sentence.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-final-sentence" class="level3" data-number="1.2.2">
<h3 data-number="1.2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-final-sentence"><span class="header-section-number">1.2.2</span> The final sentence</h3>
<p>In the final sentence, the writer makes a good attempt at linking this paragraph to the question. However, it claims that the paragraph shows that ‘<em>the role of schools in instilling good behavior is much more crucial than that of the parent</em>’. This conclusion is not supported by the evidence given here and so remains unclear - the role of parents is not mentioned at all. A more appropriate sentence would be: <em>Therefore, the role of schools in instilling good behavior is a significant one.</em> Revising the first and last sentence so that they accurately reflect the ideas in the paragraph will significantly improve the Coherence and cohesion score here.</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="addressing-task-response-problems" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Addressing Task response problems</h1>
<ul>
<li>Presents a relevant position although conclusions become unclear</li>
<li>Presents relevant main ideas but some are inadequately developed / unclear</li>
</ul>
<p>The argument being made in this paragraph is that ‘<em>schools have a lot of influence on children’s behavior</em>’. This is the main idea or conclusion that needs to be made clear. The ideas within the paragraph need to explain and support this point if we want to present an adequately developed response. Remember, these explanations must help the reader to understand <em>why</em> the writer believes this, and show that it is a valid argument or conclusion.</p>
<section id="practice" class="level3" data-number="2.0.1">
<h3 data-number="2.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.1</span> Practice</h3>
<p>Complete the second column:</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Schools have a lot of influence on children’s behaviour. Children spend the largest part of their day at school, where the teachers can cultivate their minds and fill them with knowledge that is not only important for their career, but that can also help them grow into wise adults. They can mentor the students in many different ways, for instance through books or group activities, where they can learn to tell right from wrong. In addition, children become engaged in various extra-curricular activities at school, where they are often asked to dress up like great leaders. While doing this, the students may become curious and want to know more about these people, which could encourage the children to emulate their qualities. These positive traits may even become integrated into their own personality Therefore, the role of schools in instilling good behaviour is a significant one.</p>
</div>
</div>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 70%">
<col style="width: 29%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Main points or claims</th>
<th>Supporting evidence or explanation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Teachers can mentor children in different ways</td>
<td>for instance through books or group activities</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Through books and group activities children can learn to tell right from wrong</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Children may emulate the qualities and positive traits of famous leaders and so their personality may change</td>
<td>dress up like great leaders</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 40%">
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 42%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Main points or claims</th>
<th>Supporting evidence or explanation</th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Teachers can mentor children in different ways</td>
<td>for instance through books or group activities</td>
<td>This explains <strong>when</strong> it will happen but not <strong>how</strong>.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Through books and group activities children can learn to tell right from wrong</td>
<td>(none)</td>
<td>How will they learn this? What is the connection between books or groups activities and learning right from wrong?</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Children may emulate the qualities and positive traits of famous leaders and so their personality may change</td>
<td>dress up like great leaders</td>
<td>This does not seem very likely. Does putting on different clothes permanently change our personality and behavior?</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The explanation for the last idea (point 3) takes up almost half of the paragraph, yet the argument that children can permanently alter their personality and behavior by temporarily wearing different clothes still does not seem to be a valid one. In contrast, the ideas that are far more relevant to the main idea and the central topic (the role of the teacher in group activities and mentoring) are insufficiently developed or explained and so also remain unclear.</p>
<p>There is a further problem here. The writing task told us to discuss whether schools should be responsible for teaching good behavior, not just parents, but the writer has introduced a theme that is not relevant: children learning how to behave by copying famous leaders.</p>
<p>If the writer had applied critical thinking before writing he would have realized that this idea should be deleted. Instead, by persisting with it, and explaining it over several sentences, he has gradually moved further and further away from the issue in the question. This is what happens when you think as you write, and will occur no matter what your level is. As a result, even with the improvements we have made to language and Coherence and Cohesion, this paragraph still represents band 6 Task response, which helps explain why native speakers also struggle to score band 7 or above.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Schools have a great deal of influence on young children. From the age of five or six, children spend most of their day there, under the guidance of their teachers. Although we tend to think of education in terms of academic knowledge, this is only part of the picture. At school, children learn to make friends and to think independently. Through group activities, teachers can show them how to cooperate with others and play well together. Children quickly learn self-control, and realize that there is a right and wrong way to behave. In fact, if teacher did not correct poor behavior, the result would be a noisy disruptive classroom, where learning is almost impossible. Therefore, schools inevitably play a crucial role in shaping a child’s character.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Structure our paragraphs using <strong>PEEL</strong>. Begin by making a Point, which we then Explain, Expand, and then clearly Link our paragraph and argument back to the question. The Point and Link frame our paragraph. If they accurately reflect the main idea in the paragraph, they will ensure we ‘present a clear central topic’.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="point-to-notice-about-paragraph-structure" class="level3" data-number="2.0.2">
<h3 data-number="2.0.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="point-to-notice-about-paragraph-structure"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.2</span> Point to notice about paragraph structure</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>The first sentence in the paragraph introduces the main idea (the ‘central topic’ here is the influence that schools have on children). The final sentence reaches a conclusion based on the evidence provided within the paragraph, shows how this is linked to the question, and makes our position clear.</li>
<li>We can see P and L in PEEL as overall conclusions about the argument within the paragraph. The first introduces these through a general statement or point, and the final sentence sums up the main argument in the paragraph, and shows that it is answering the question - in other words, why or how this is relevant to the question we have been given.</li>
<li>Each idea between those sentence</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>is relevant both to the question and to the main idea given in the first sentence</li>
<li>helps support and explain the conclusions (P and L)</li>
<li>is clearly connected</li>
<li>is logically organized</li>
</ul>
<p>When we can do something well, we can make it look easy. Do not underestimate the skill required to neatly sum up an argument or main point in this way - do not be fooled into thinking ‘the level here is too low because it is too easy to understand’. Those who believe this continue to write in a way that makes their central ideas, conclusions, and position unclear.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-8/Pasted image 20250922170046.png" class="img-fluid"><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-8/Pasted image 20250922170051.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="point-to-notice" class="level3" data-number="2.0.3">
<h3 data-number="2.0.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="point-to-notice"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.3</span> Point to notice</h3>
<ul>
<li>The grammatical points are not used to boost the Grammatical accuracy and range score but to make the position and argument clear. Each grammar point serves this purpose. Look back at sentence 2 and 3 to see the role that conparatives, and modal verbs play in making the writer’s position verb clear.</li>
<li>The vocabulary used also serves the same purpose. Compare sentence 1 to sentence 4. In sentence 1, the writer is focused on clearly communicating the message - ‘have a great deal of influence on’ conveys the message very clearly while also showing good collocation (i.e.&nbsp;uses the correct combination of words: _have an influence on__). In sentence 4, the writer may have intended to say, ‘<em>Schools have a lot of influence on young children</em>’, but in trying to score Lexical resource points by using ‘high level’ words instead, they lost the clarity that is needed to reach the higher bands.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-8/Pasted image 20250922170453.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Extra practice Go back over previous essays you have written and focus on your body paragraphs. • Look for any pronouns you have used - what do these refer back to? Is this reference clear? • Find the conclusions you made in each argument (your points and claims) and the reasons you gave for believing these (your supporting evidence) and decide if your arguments and conclusions are clear and valid. What changes can you make to help make them clearer? • Look back at the first sentence in each paragraph - does it introduce one clear central topic? • Do your final sentences accurately reflect the evidence you have provided and link back to the question - in other words, do your paragraphs match the PEEL structure? • Is one paragraph more successful at this than another? (This is a common problem and indicates insufficient planning before writing.)| • Rewrite one or two paragraphs for practice when you have time. Make a note of any repeated language problems and grammar points, and make sure to study and practise them. For example, relative clauses, conditional sentences, modal verbs.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-8/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lesson 7: Strengthening Your Argument: Counterarguments</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-7/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="presenting-a-counterargument" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Presenting a counterargument</h1>
<section id="what-is-a-counterargument" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-a-counterargument"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> What is a counterargument?</h2>
<p>Imagine that we have a good job, and we may be promoted soon, but we have been offered a new job in a different country. Before reaching a decision, we would naturally think carefully about all sides of the issue. We would consider the benefits of staying in our current job, as well as the benefits of the new job. We would also consider the disadvantages of both ideas. If someone asked us, ‘<em>What did you decide to do?</em>’ We might say:</p>
<p>‘<em>I’m going to take the job because it’s a really good opportunity. I know you might think that I’ll miss out on getting a promotion, but the pay is better, and I think I’ll learn so much more if I go.</em>’</p>
<p>This speaker is showing that they reached a decision after considering all sides of the issue; they show this by:</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Presenting an argument: <font color="#245bdb">I’m going to take the new job because it’s a really good opportunity.</font></p>
<p>Acknowledging a counterargument: <font color="#d83931">I know you might think that I’ll miss out on getting a promotion.</font></p>
<p>Refuting* the counterargument: <font color="#245bdb">But the pay is better and I think I’ll learn so much more.</font></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Acknowledging the counterargument in this way makes the argument stronger than simply saying: ‘<em>I’ve decided to take the job because it’s a really good opportunity and I will learn a lot in the new job</em>.’ Notice also that, even though they have referred to the counterargument, we still know what this person’s position is - we still know what they have decided to do.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>An argument is made stronger by not only presenting evidence to support our conclusions, but also by considering, and then refuting, the argument that is against, or ‘counter’, to it: the counterargument. Doing this shows that we considered all sides of the issues before reaching our conclusion.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="how-is-this-relevant-to-ielts" class="level2" data-number="1.2">
<h2 data-number="1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-is-this-relevant-to-ielts"><span class="header-section-number">1.2</span> How is this relevant to IELTS?</h2>
<p>The following examples help to see this analogy in terms of some typical writing task 2 questions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Some people think it is better to stay in the same job all your working life. To what extent do you agree or disagree?</li>
<li>Some people think it is better to stay in the same job all your life. Others think it is better to do different jobs throughout your career. Discuss both these views and give your own opinion.</li>
<li>Nowadays, people change jobs more often than in the past. Is this a positive or a negative development?</li>
<li>People are now more likely to have several different jobs throughout their career than in the past. Do the advantages of this outweigh the disadvantages?</li>
</ol>
<p>When responding to each on of these questions, we can present an argument for changing jobs, and discuss the counterargument - the argument for staying in the same job. With questions 2 to 4, we <strong>must</strong> respond by considering both of these sides. Only question 1 is different</p>
</section>
<section id="to-what-extent-do-you-agree-or-disagree-do-you-agree-or-disagree" class="level2" data-number="1.3">
<h2 data-number="1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="to-what-extent-do-you-agree-or-disagree-do-you-agree-or-disagree"><span class="header-section-number">1.3</span> To what extent do you agree or disagree? Do you agree or disagree?</h2>
<p>Only with questions like this, and the General Training equivalent of ‘<em>Do you agree or disagree?</em>’, do we have a choice in the way we respond. With these questions, we can:</p>
<p>A. present an argument that looks at both sides, then reach a conclusion about it</p>
<p>B. present an argument for only the side we agree with</p>
<p>C. present an argument for only the side we agree with, while also mentioning, and refuting, the counterargument.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-7/Pasted image 20250915205135.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>PC said that the approach A’s advantages outweigh the disadvantages, and can be easier to achieve with less practice.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-bad-advice-causes-problems" class="level2" data-number="1.4">
<h2 data-number="1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-bad-advice-causes-problems"><span class="header-section-number">1.4</span> Why bad advice causes problems</h2>
<p>If you write, ‘<em>It is thought</em>’, or ‘<em>It is felt</em>’, then you are not telling the examiner that <u>you</u> think of feel. Similarly, as we will see, the advice to avoid using ‘some’ or ‘some people’ results in candidates presenting what should be a counterargument as though it is an argument they actually believe.</p>
<p>By far the easiest way to present a clear counterargument is to say, ‘<em>Some people may think XYZ, but I think ABC</em>’.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-language-of-counterarguments-conceding-and-refuting" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> The language of counterarguments: conceding and refuting</h1>
<section id="how-should-i-use-a-counterargument" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-should-i-use-a-counterargument"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> How should I use a counterargument?</h2>
<p>When answering, ‘<em>To what extent do you agree or disagree?</em>’ questions, we are often asked how or when to include a counterargument. The examples below show, very briefly, some different ways we can do this. These arguments that might be made in answer to our previous question:</p>
<p><em>Some people think it is better to stay in the same job all your working life.</em></p>
<p><em>To what extent do you agree or disagree?</em></p>
<section id="argument-showing-complete-agreement" class="level3" data-number="2.1.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="argument-showing-complete-agreement"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.1</span> Argument showing complete agreement</h3>
<p>If we completely agree, we might present an argument and counterargument like this:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 29%">
<col style="width: 70%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><font color="#245bdb">My position and argument</font><br></td>
<td><font color="#245bdb">I complete agree because staying in the same job is rewarding, and also increases your chance of promotion.</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><font color="#d83931">The counterargument</font></td>
<td><font color="#d83931">Some people might say it is boring to stay in the same job.</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><font color="#245bdb">Conceding a point</font></td>
<td><font color="#245bdb">It is true that there is less variety.</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><font color="#245bdb">Refuting this point</font></td>
<td><font color="#245bdb">However, I believe changing jobs too often can be unsettling and we may actually learn less.</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Or, we may choose to discuss the counterargument earlier in our essay:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 74%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><font color="#ff0000">The counterargument</font></td>
<td><font color="#ff0000">Some people might say it is boring to stay in the same job.</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><font color="#245bdb">Conceding a point</font></td>
<td><font color="#245bdb">It is true that there is less variety</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><font color="#245bdb">Refuting this point</font></td>
<td><font color="#245bdb">However, I believe changing jobs too often can be unsettling and you may actually learn less</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><font color="#245bdb">My position and argument</font></td>
<td><font color="#245bdb">Therefore, I completely agree, because staying in the same job is not only rewarding but also increases your chance of promotion.</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="argument-showing-complete-disagreement" class="level3" data-number="2.1.2">
<h3 data-number="2.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="argument-showing-complete-disagreement"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.2</span> Argument showing complete disagreement</h3>
<p>If you completely disagree, you might present an argument and counterargument like this</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 24%">
<col style="width: 75%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><font color="#ff0000">My position and argument</font></td>
<td><font color="#ff0000">I completely disagree, because staying in the same job means you become bored and lose motivation.</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><font color="#ff0000">The counterargument</font></td>
<td><font color="#d83931">Some people might say you have a better chance of promotion by staying in the same job. </font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><font color="#245bdb">Conceding a point</font></td>
<td><font color="#245bdb">That may be true for some people</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><font color="#245bdb">Refuting this point</font></td>
<td><font color="#245bdb">However, this is not true for everyone, many people have to apply for higher positions in a different company.</font></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Or this:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 29%">
<col style="width: 70%">
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><font color="#ff0000">The counterargument</font></td>
<td><font color="#ff0000">Some people might say you have a better chance of promotion by staying in the same job.</font></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Conceding a point</td>
<td>That may be true for some people</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Refuting this point</td>
<td>However, this is not true for everyone, many people have to apply for higher positions in a different company</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>My position and argument</td>
<td>Therefore, I completely disagree because staying in the same job means you become bored and lose motivation</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-language-of-counterarguments" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-language-of-counterarguments"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> The language of counterarguments</h2>
</section>
</section>
<section id="dealing-with-problems-in-counterargument" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Dealing with problems in counterargument</h1>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-7/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing Task 2 - Teaching cooking</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-food/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Some people think that students should study the science of food and how to prepare it. Others believe students should spend time on more important subjects. Discuss both views and give your own opinion.</em></p>
<hr>
<p>Some people argue that schools should teach children about food science and cooking, while others believe the curriculum should concentrate only on academic subjects. This essay will examine both perspective before explaining why I believe that teaching food science and cooking is the more beneficial approach.</p>
<p>On the one hand, those who prioritize academic subjects argue that focus on food science or cooking in school is a waste of valuable study time. This is because they suggest that students should devote their time to core academic subjects, such as mathematics and science, which are regarded as more important for future success. For instance, entry to prestigious universities usually depends on high grades in these subjects, rather than in cooking or food science. For this reason, they see little value including cooking or food science in the school curriculum.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it is also believed that learning cooking and food science is essential for young people to become independent adults. In particular, understanding nutrition and learning to cook simple meals can help young people lead healthier lives. For example, students who know how to cook are less likely to rely on fast food when they live away from home. Furthermore, these skills allow them to enjoy a wider variety of meals and to manage their finances more effectively. In fact, students who cook their own meals often spend far less money than those who rely on restaurants or fast food. As a result, these skills prepare young people to live both more healthy and more economically when they become independent.</p>
<p>In conclusion, while some people think schools should focus only on academic subjects, others believe that cooking and food science are equally important. I agree with the latter view, as these skills not only promote healthier lifestyles but also help young people manage their finances and prepare for independent living.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-food/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing Task 2 - Teaching cooking</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-drug-in-poor-countries/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>You should spend about 40 minutes on this task.</p>
<p>Write about the following topic:</p>
<p><strong>Many people in poor countries die from diseases that are curable because they cannot afford the medication required.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Do you believe that drug companies should make their products available at reduced prices in these countries?</strong></p>
<p>Give reasons for your answer and include any relevant examples from your own knowledge and experience.</p>
<p>Write at least 250 words.</p>
<hr>
<p>curable can be made healthy again</p>
<p>ethical connected to beliefs about what is right or wrong</p>
<p>inequality unfair differences in society</p>
<p>immunize to protect a person from a disease by giving them a vaccine</p>
<p>pharmaceutical medicine</p>
<p>profit to make money</p>
<p>responsible having the duty of taking care of someone or something</p>
<p>responsibility the duty of taking care of someone or something</p>
<p>subsidize to give money to somebody to help them pay for something</p>
<p>treat to give medical care to someone</p>
<p>treatment medical care given to someone</p>
<p>vaccine a substance you put in your blood to protect the body from disease</p>
<p>Intro paraphrase the question:</p>
<p>Many people in developing nations die from diseases that could be cured, mainly because medicines are too expensive.</p>
<p>thesis:</p>
<p>While pharmaceutical companies need profit to fund research and development, I believe they should sell their products at reduced prices in poorer countries to reduce inequality and save lives.</p>
<p>Body 1 - drug companies’ side</p>
<p>How do drug companies make money? -&gt; by selling medicines at high prices.</p>
<p>Why are medicines expensive? -&gt; cost of research, clinical trials, and production.</p>
<p>Is this good? Yes, because without profit, they cannot innovate or create new treatments/vaccines.</p>
<p>Example: Development of vaccines (like for COVID-19) required huge investment and profit incentives.</p>
<p>Body 2 - Poor countries’ situation</p>
<p>Can everyone in poor countries afford medicine? No, many live below poverty line.</p>
<p>Why unfair? -&gt; creates inequality; curable disease continue to kill people</p>
<p>Who else can help? Governments, NGOs, international organizations (e.g.&nbsp;WHO) can subsidize or negotiate reduced prices.</p>
<p>Example: Some vaccine programs (e.g.&nbsp;polio immunization) were subsidized globally, saving millions of lives.</p>
<p>Conclusion Summarize: Drug companies must balance profit with responsibility.</p>
<p>Opinion: They should make medicines affordable in poor countries, possibly through reduced prices or subsidies, because human life is more valuable than profit.</p>
<p>Many people in developing nations die from diseases that could be cured, mainly because medicines are too expensive. While pharmaceutical companies need profit to fund research and development, I believe they should sell their products at reduced prices in poorer countries to reduce inequality and save lives.</p>
<p>On the one hand, drug companies argue that their products are expensive because it need enormous resources to make. They must invest large amount of money on development process, such as research, clinical trials, vaccines, which can need several millions dollar and decades to success. Without profit, they would not be able to innovate or develop new treatments, enhance drugs. For example, the development of vaccines during the COVID-19 pandemic cost billions of dollars, and only strong profits made this possible. Therefore, it is understandable that pharmaceutical companies charge high prices in order to recover their investment and continue developing new treatments.</p>
<p>On the other hand, people in poor countries often live below the poverty line, so some drugs have normal price in developed countries but cost a fortune of people in developing countries. This situation creates inequality because curable disease still kill people or destroy their family financial, making their future more hardly. In my opinion, drug companies can should reduce prices or allow governments and charities to subsidize treatments. A good example is the global campaign to immunize children against polio, where vaccines were provided a little or no cost, saving millions of lives. This shows that cooperation and reduced pricing can treat diseases effectively in poorer regions.</p>
<p>In conclusion, although drug companies must make a profit in order to fund research and the development of new medicines, I believe they also have an ethical duty to make essential treatments affordable in poorer countries. By reducing prices or cooperating with international organisations, they can continue to benefit financially while helping to reduce global inequality and save lives.</p>
<hr>
<p>Many&nbsp;individuals&nbsp;in&nbsp;developing&nbsp;countries&nbsp;suffer&nbsp;from&nbsp;preventable&nbsp;diseases&nbsp;due&nbsp;to&nbsp;the&nbsp;prohibitive&nbsp;cost&nbsp;of&nbsp;medication.&nbsp;I&nbsp;strongly&nbsp;believe&nbsp;that&nbsp;pharmaceutical&nbsp;companies&nbsp;should&nbsp;offer&nbsp;their&nbsp;products&nbsp;at&nbsp;reduced&nbsp;prices&nbsp;in&nbsp;these&nbsp;regions,&nbsp;as&nbsp;this&nbsp;approach&nbsp;promotes&nbsp;social&nbsp;equity,&nbsp;public&nbsp;health,&nbsp;and&nbsp;long-term&nbsp;business&nbsp;sustainability.</p>
<p>Lowering&nbsp;drug&nbsp;prices&nbsp;in&nbsp;low-income&nbsp;countries&nbsp;would&nbsp;have&nbsp;a&nbsp;profound&nbsp;impact&nbsp;on&nbsp;public&nbsp;health&nbsp;by&nbsp;making&nbsp;essential&nbsp;medicines&nbsp;more&nbsp;accessible.&nbsp;For&nbsp;instance,&nbsp;affordable&nbsp;malaria&nbsp;treatment&nbsp;could&nbsp;drastically&nbsp;reduce&nbsp;mortality&nbsp;rates&nbsp;in&nbsp;sub-Saharan&nbsp;Africa,&nbsp;where&nbsp;the&nbsp;disease&nbsp;is&nbsp;widespread.&nbsp;Additionally,&nbsp;improved&nbsp;health&nbsp;outcomes&nbsp;contribute&nbsp;to&nbsp;economic&nbsp;growth,&nbsp;as&nbsp;a&nbsp;healthier&nbsp;workforce&nbsp;enhances&nbsp;productivity&nbsp;and&nbsp;reduces&nbsp;the&nbsp;financial&nbsp;burden&nbsp;on&nbsp;national&nbsp;healthcare&nbsp;systems.</p>
<p>Critics&nbsp;argue&nbsp;that&nbsp;lowering&nbsp;drug&nbsp;prices&nbsp;may&nbsp;undermine&nbsp;pharmaceutical&nbsp;companies’&nbsp;ability&nbsp;to&nbsp;fund&nbsp;research&nbsp;and&nbsp;innovation.&nbsp;However,&nbsp;this&nbsp;concern&nbsp;can&nbsp;be&nbsp;addressed&nbsp;through&nbsp;tiered&nbsp;pricing&nbsp;models,&nbsp;where&nbsp;wealthier&nbsp;nations&nbsp;pay&nbsp;higher&nbsp;prices&nbsp;to&nbsp;compensate&nbsp;for&nbsp;lower&nbsp;costs&nbsp;in&nbsp;poorer&nbsp;regions.&nbsp;Moreover,&nbsp;international&nbsp;organizations&nbsp;and&nbsp;governments&nbsp;can&nbsp;provide&nbsp;subsidies&nbsp;or&nbsp;tax&nbsp;incentives&nbsp;to&nbsp;pharmaceutical&nbsp;firms,&nbsp;ensuring&nbsp;profitability&nbsp;without&nbsp;compromising&nbsp;humanitarian&nbsp;efforts.</p>
<p>Beyond&nbsp;the&nbsp;ethical&nbsp;considerations&nbsp;already&nbsp;discussed,&nbsp;affordable&nbsp;medication&nbsp;fosters&nbsp;goodwill&nbsp;and&nbsp;enhances&nbsp;corporate&nbsp;reputation.&nbsp;Companies&nbsp;that&nbsp;engage&nbsp;in&nbsp;socially&nbsp;responsible&nbsp;pricing&nbsp;are&nbsp;likely&nbsp;to&nbsp;gain&nbsp;consumer&nbsp;trust&nbsp;and&nbsp;brand&nbsp;loyalty,&nbsp;which&nbsp;may&nbsp;lead&nbsp;to&nbsp;greater&nbsp;long-term&nbsp;profitability.&nbsp;Furthermore,&nbsp;preventing&nbsp;disease&nbsp;outbreaks&nbsp;in&nbsp;developing&nbsp;nations&nbsp;reduces&nbsp;the&nbsp;risk&nbsp;of&nbsp;global&nbsp;health&nbsp;crises,&nbsp;benefiting&nbsp;the&nbsp;entire&nbsp;world.</p>
<p>In&nbsp;conclusion,&nbsp;making&nbsp;essential&nbsp;medicines&nbsp;more&nbsp;affordable&nbsp;in&nbsp;developing&nbsp;countries&nbsp;is&nbsp;both&nbsp;a&nbsp;moral&nbsp;obligation&nbsp;and&nbsp;a&nbsp;strategic&nbsp;decision&nbsp;that&nbsp;benefits&nbsp;public&nbsp;health,&nbsp;economic&nbsp;stability,&nbsp;and&nbsp;the&nbsp;pharmaceutical&nbsp;industry&nbsp;itself.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-drug-in-poor-countries/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing task 2 - International / local charity</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-charity/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Some people think that charity organizations should only offer help to people of their own country. But others believe that these organizations should give aid to people in great need wherever they live. Discuss both views and give your opinion.</p>
<hr>
<p>Charitable organizations play an important role in supporting those in need, but there is debate about whether their assistance should be limited to people in their own country or extended across borders. While some argue that national responsibility must come first, others believe that aid should be based on human need rather than geography.</p>
<p>There is debate about whether charity organizations should limit their assistance to people in their own country or provide help to those in need regardless of location. While both sides present convincing arguments, I believe charities should not restrict their efforts by national borders.</p>
<p>There is ongoing debate about whether charity organizations should focus only on supporting people in their own country or whether they should extend their help to those in need abroad. While both perspectives have strong arguments, I believe the most effective approach is to provide assistance wherever it is most urgently required.</p>
<p>One reason some people argue that charities should concentrate on their own citizens is the issue of limited resources. Most charities depend on donations, which are rarely enough to address every problem. By focusing on national issues such as poverty, homelessness, or healthcare, these organizations can ensure that urgent needs at home are met. Furthermore, donors may feel more motivated to contribute if they know their money directly benefits their local community, which strengthens long-term support for these charities.</p>
<p>On the other hand, many believe that charity should not be restricted by geography. Natural disasters, famine, or war can create crises where entire populations are at risk, and local governments may lack the capacity to cope. In such circumstances, international charities are often the only organizations able to deliver essential aid like food, medicine, and shelter. Moreover, in today’s interconnected world, problems in one country - such as pandemics or climate change - can easily affect others, making international assistance not only compassions but also practical.</p>
<p>In my view, although it is reasonable for charities to prioritize local issues, they should not limit themselves entirely to national concerns. A balanced approach is most effective: dedicating part of their resources to domestic needs while also responding to international emergencies ensures that help reaches people in the greatest need, regardless of where they live.</p>
<p>In conclusion, while there are clear benefits to focusing on domestic problems, there also compelling reasons for providing international aid. Therefore, I believe charities should aim to strike a balance between supporting their local communities and offering help to people overseas who are facing severe hardship.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-charity/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Writing task 2 - International air travel</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-air-travel/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>International air travel has a negative impact upon the environment and should therefore be restricted. Do you agree or disagree?</p>
<hr>
<p>In recent years, some argue that international air travel should be curtailed due to its detrimental effect on the environment. However, I totally disagree with this idea, as restricting global flights would not only hinder economic growth but also undermine culture exchange.</p>
<p>On the economic front, air transport plays a pivotal role in facilitating tourism and trade, which are indispensable drivers of prosperity. For example, nations such as Thailand or Spain rely heavily on international visitors, and limiting flights would deal a severe blow to their hospitality industries. Moreover, multinational companies depend on global mobility to conduct business, attend meetings, and negotiate contracts. Without air travel, the interconnected nature of the global economy would collapse, creating ripple effects on employment and living standards worldwide.</p>
<p>Equally important is the cultural dimension. Air travel allows people from different continents to meet, share, and foster mutual understanding. This cross-cultural interaction broadens people’s horizons and reduces prejudices, ultimately paving the way for a more harmonious world. If flights were restricted, such opportunities would vanish, leaving societies increasingly insular and intolerant. Although environmental concerns are legitimate, governments should prioritize sustainable aviation technologies such as biofuels and carbon offsetting instead of imposing blanket restrictions on flights.</p>
<p>In conclusion, restricting international air travel would do more harm than good, as it would jeopardize both global economies and cultural connectivity.</p>
<hr>
<p>It is argued that international air travel damages the environment and should therefore be reduced. Although air transport is a source of pollution, I completely disagree that restricting flights is the right solution. This is because global mobility is essential in today’s world, and alternative measures can address the environmental challenges more effectively.</p>
<p>Firstly, limiting international flights would create serious social and economic problems. Air travel allows people to study abroad, expand businesses, and maintain international relationships. Restricting this freedom would not only harm global trade and tourism but also prevent cultural exchange and educational opportunities. For instance, many students depend on international flights to pursue higher education in other countries, which would be impossible if travel were severely limited. Therefore, placing restrictions would have far-reaching negative consequences.</p>
<p>Secondly, environmental issues caused by aviation can be addressed without banning or restricting flights. Governments and airlines are already investing in cleaner technology, such as more fuel-efficient engines and the development of sustainable aviation fuels. In addition, policies such as carbon offsetting and taxes on luxury or frequent travel can encourage responsible flying while still keeping it accessible. These strategies show that it is possible to reduce emissions without restricting international movement.</p>
<p>In conclusion, although air travel contributes to environmental problems, restricting it would cause more harm than good. A better solution is to continue supporting technological improvements and policies that make aviation more sustainable, while still allowing people to enjoy the benefits of international mobility.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w2-air-travel/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Supporting evidence and giving examples</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-6/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="what-is-supporting-evidence" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> What is supporting evidence</h1>
<p>It is important to see the evidence we provide in our essay as the reason we believe something to be true. Supporting evidence helps the reader to understand our main argument and shows our thinking, but attempts to do this cause problems even at Band 7, where candidates may ‘overgeneralize and/or supporting ideas may lack focus’. Only at band 8 are main ideas ‘<em>relevant, extended and supported</em>’ and it is not until band 9 that they are ‘<em>fully extended and well-supported</em>.’ Clearly, providing relevant, focused support for our argument is a high-level skill.</p>
<p>The fact that supporting evidence is not mentioned at band 6 and below is often interpreted to mean that ‘you must include examples to score band 7’. While this is true to a certain extent, the way in which this is done often continues to result in a score of band 6 or 6.5, which shows there is a problem with this advice.</p>
</section>
<section id="common-problems-with-examples" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Common problems with examples</h1>
<section id="problem-1-template-filling-and-invented-examples" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-1-template-filling-and-invented-examples"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Problem 1: Template filling and invented examples</h2>
<p>In most of the band 6 essays, each paragraph contains a separate sentence with an example. There are often invented statistics that sound odd, and they rarely help to explain or support the main idea in the paragraph. Such examples are provided mechanically, often at the very end of the paragraph, as though the writer is thinking, ‘<em>now I need to write an example</em>’, rather than, ‘<em>how can I prove this point?</em>’</p>
<p>The following paragraphs was written by a native speaker. The essays was about helping older workers to get a job. Do you think the example (in bold) supports or explains the main idea?</p>
<p><em>To tackle this long-term problem, governments should provide a corporate tax incentive when they hire experienced people. That is to say that a lower income tax on the profits of companies would allow employers to hire the right people to perform the right job, without the need to lower HR fees. <strong>For example, a similar initiative was launched by the United States government in San Francisco, California, which has resulted in Tesla’s yearly corporate taxes to reduce by 35%.</strong></em></p>
<p>There are some grammatical issues in this essay (native speakers often use patterns common in spoken language), but the main problems are with Coherence and cohesion and Task response: the main ideas are not adequately developed and remain confusing and unclear. How does lower income tax help companies to hire the right people? What is the relevance of lower HR fees? The example provided does not help the reader to understand any of these points, nor why the writer has concluded that ‘governments should provide a corporate tax incentive when they hire experienced staff’.</p>
<p>The second body paragraph also followed the same pattern: two sentences that are not logically connected followed by a very clearly invented example. The writer confirmed that he had been taught to use this same template approach in every essay. As a result, although the last sentence <strong><em>looks</em></strong> like an example, it does not perform the <strong><em>function</em></strong> of an example, because it doesn’t support, or help to explain, any of the previous ideas.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Adding a sentence with an invented example will not provide supporting evidence for our ideas, or persuade the reader to believe them.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="problem-2-examples-that-are-not-examples" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-2-examples-that-are-not-examples"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Problem 2: Examples that are not examples</h2>
<p>In many essays, the examples given are not examples at all - they are often simply a repetition of the previous idea:</p>
<p><em><strong>On the other hand</strong>, if good transportation is provided to the public they will travel by public transport. <strong>For example</strong>, if fast metro trains are provided to people who go to work and students who go to school or colleges in the morning. <strong>In addition</strong>, if there are buses on different routes that cover all the important destinations, such as downtown, hospitals, schools, factories area. <strong>An example of this is</strong>, in London, people prefer to travel by bus because buses are fast and they go to famous places of the city.</em></p>
<p>This paragraph is another good examples of why a template approach will not work: there are cohesive device here (in bold) that have been used as a fixed framework for the paragraph, but they are not logically connected to the ideas in between. As a result, ideas are again presented as ‘examples’ but they do not perform this function: they do not help to explain or support the writer’s points or claims:</p>
<p>We map out these ideas to see the issue more clearly:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 53%">
<col style="width: 46%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Claim</th>
<th>Example given to show this claim reasonable</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>if good transportation is provided to the public they will travel by public transport</td>
<td>if fast metro trains are provided to people who go to work and students who go to school or colleges in the morning</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>if there are buses on different routes that cover all the important destinations, such as downtown, hospitals, schools, factories area</td>
<td>in London, people prefer to travel by buses because buses are fast and they go to famous places of the city</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>As we can see, the examples given do not support the claims being made. This shows that simply writing ‘<em>For example, …</em>’ or ‘<em>An example of this is …</em>’ at the start of a sentence is not enough. The ideas that follows these patterns must provide evidence to support the previous idea, like this:</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>If good public transportation is provided people will use it. <strong>For example, cities like London, Tokyo, and Singapore have excellent underground trains that are filled with people traveling to work, school or college every day. In addition,</strong> if there are buses on different routes that cover important destinations, <strong>such as hospitals and factories, these would also no doubt be used in preference to private cars, reducing traffic as a result.</strong></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>In this version, the connecting phrases are used because they are needed, and because they fit this argument. As a result, they work as effective signposts, helping the reader to follow the development of the argument, and showing how the ideas are connected.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>If you begin with a template of cohesive devices and then attempt to fill in the gaps between them, the result will be band 6 ‘mechanical’ use of these linking words and phrases. Remember - your ideas and your argument must come first.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="problem-3-using-a-trivial-idea-to-support-a-serious-or-extreme-conclusion." class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="problem-3-using-a-trivial-idea-to-support-a-serious-or-extreme-conclusion."><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Problem 3: Using a trivial idea to support a serious or extreme conclusion.</h2>
<p>In lesson 2, she referred to an argument made in an essay discussing whether or not ‘<em>countries are becoming more and more similar because people are likely to buy the same products anywhere in the world</em>’.</p>
<p>In the essay, the writer used the example of a famous Spanish fashion store called Zara:</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Some people may say that this is definitely a positive trend because it helps them save time and money. This is because nowadays it is no longer necessary to buy a plane ticket and spend 5 hours to get to the US to buy a Zara handbag. In my experience, this mindset genuinely reflects human nature since many of us have a tendency to think about our own interests first.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>He went on to the argue that:</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>On the societal level, the results may be catastrophic if this is the case. Perhaps the worst-case scenario is that the global tourism industry may collapse.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>The reasoning in this argument can be summarized as follows:</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This is a positive trend because it saves us time and money (e.g.&nbsp;we no longer need to fly to the US to buy a Zara handbag) = human nature = people think of our own interests first =&gt; the global tourism industry may collapse.</p>
<p>Mapping the ideas in this way shows the lack of logic in reaching this conclusion - the example does not support the conclusion that global tourism may collapse, and it is rather trivial in comparison.</p>
<section id="other-ways-of-supporting-our-ideas" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Other ways of supporting our ideas</h1>
<p>Our main ideas or points are often broad and general, while our supporting evidence is more specific.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>There are several reasons why the government collect taxes. Firstly, the money raised can be used to build new roads or public buildings. Secondly, existing infrastructure, such as schools and hospital, can be updated or repaired. Finally, these funds are needed to pay the salaries of all government workers, including firefighters and the police. Thus, taxes help improve the community while also making it safer.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>The following image shows that we can categorize the ideas in this paragraph as either ‘general ideas’ or ‘supporting evidence’:</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-6/Pasted image 20250915200859.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We can transfer this idea to help in the reading test: for matching headings questions, we need to identify the broader, more general idea within a paragraph or section of the passage.</p>
<section id="practice" class="level3" data-number="3.0.1">
<h3 data-number="3.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice"><span class="header-section-number">3.0.1</span> Practice</h3>
<p>Read through the paragraph and identify two ‘general ideas’ and three examples of ‘specific evidence’. :::{.callout-note} In many big cities, the population exceeds the number of flats and houses available, which means that many people do not have anywhere to live. This causes several problems. Firstly, it can put pressure on local charities, who have to find food and shelter for the homeless. If the government does not step in to help people who are struggling financially, then this puts even more stress on community programs and causes homelessness to rise even further. In addition, a lack of accommodation means that house prices and rents remain very high. Thus, housing problems have an impact on everyone in the community.</p>
</section>
</section>
</div>
</div>
<p>general ideas: many people do not have anywhere to live -&gt; cause several problems</p>
<p>-&gt; housing problems have an impact on everyone in the community</p>
<p>specific evidence:</p>
<p>put pressure on local charities</p>
<p>local charities have to find food and shelter for the homeless</p>
<p>lack of accommodation means that house prices and rents remain very high.</p>
</section>
<section id="points-to-notice" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="points-to-notice"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Points to notice</h2>
<p>In almost every case in these paragraphs, the ideas were supported without using a separate sentence beginning with ‘For example, …’</p>
<p>The supporting evidence is relevant and focused, because of this, it supports the general ideas well.</p>
<p>For variety, we can either begin with the supporting evidence and then draw a conclusion from this:</p>
<p><em>A: These funds are used to pay the salaries of all government workers, including firefighters and the police. <u>Thus</u>, taxes help improve the community while also making it safer.</em></p>
<p>Or we can make the point and then show our evidence for this by giving an example:</p>
<p><em>B: Taxes help improve the community while also making it safer. <u>For example</u>, the funds are used to pay the salaries of government workers such as firefighters and the police.</em></p>
<p>Although we do not need to begin with a sentence with ‘<em>For example</em>’, sometimes, it is both helpful and necessary. Look at these two claims in the previous lesson, and the examples supporting them.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Language note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>In academic writing, or when writing about a serious issue, we often begin by defining key terms. This can help to explain the context for the ideas in our argument. <strong>For example</strong>, if we are writing about the topic of ‘success’, we could begin by defining what this word means to us, or in our culture, which may be different to the examiner’s interpretation of the word.</p>
<p>Sometimes, we rephrase an idea in order to make it clearer. <strong>For example</strong>, in lesson 4, we wrote:</p>
<p>Many cities have more people than houses. This means that many people do not have anywhere to live.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>She used these examples to show that her claims were true, but also to try to persuade us to take her claims seriously; putting each example into a separate sentence also helped to highlight it.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Including an example to make an idea clearer or help to show that the argument and point we are making is a valid one. Finish our paragraphs with a general point rather than with an example.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-6/Pasted image 20250915202615.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Instead of making a point and then giving an example:</p>
<p><em>Point: Taxes help improve the community while also making it safer.</em></p>
<p><em>Example: For example, the funds are used to pay the salaries of government worker such as firefighters and the police.</em></p>
<p>Begin with the example, and then draw a conclusion, or make a point about it, like this:</p>
<p><em>Example: These funds are used to pay the salaries of all government workers, including firefighters and the police.</em></p>
<p><em>Point: Thus, taxes help improve the community while also making it safer.</em></p>
<p>Notice that, here, we present our example <strong>without</strong> using the words ‘<em>For example</em>’, and then begin the next sentence with ‘<strong>Thus, …</strong>’ or ‘<strong>Therefore…</strong>’</p>
<p>Ask these questions to check whether our examples are acting as supporting evidence:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is the example relevant to the main idea of the paragraph and to the essay question?</li>
<li>Does the point we are making follow on logically from our example?</li>
<li>If not, what logical conclusion <em>can</em> we draw from our example? (i.e.&nbsp;What <em>does</em> our example show?) If this is not relevant to our main idea then we should not use it.</li>
<li>Try to decide if our problem is with the main ideas and points we are making, the examples we have used to support them, or a combination of the two.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-6/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Explaining and Clarifying ideas</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-5/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="explaining-an-idea---when-and-how" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Explaining an idea - when and how</h1>
<p>As part of our argument, we may need to give an explanation. We can do this to explain the meaning of a key term, explain the context for our ideas, or explain a complex idea in a simpler way. A question we are often asked is, ‘How do I know when I need to explain an idea?’.</p>
<p>We wrote about the topic of homelessness, and the issues surrounding this topic are generally the same in many parts of the world. However, with other topics, this is often not the case, which is why our ideas sometimes need to be explained further. For example, when writing about eating healthy, one person might make the following argument.</p>
<p><em>It is important to eat fruit every day, because it contains vitamins that help keep us healthy. Therefore, I completely agree with the idea that schools should encourage all children to eat fruit.</em></p>
<p>However, someone with an intolerance to fruit, who gets a severe stomach ache and skin problems after eating it, may write:</p>
<p><em>Eating fruit makes people feel unwell, and it even affects their ability to work. Therefore, I completely disagree with the idea that schools should encourage all children to eat fruit.</em></p>
<p>Anyone without the same intolerance is likely to be confused by the first statement in this argument. Again, language plays a key part: this is not a fact that is generally true for <em>everyone</em>, yet the use of the simple present suggests that it is. Using modal verbs (<em>may, can, etc</em>), as well as words and phrases like ‘<em>sometimes</em>’, ‘<em>for some people</em>’, helps to clarify ideas like this. For example:</p>
<p><em>Eating fruit can make some people feel unwell, and it can even affect their ability to work. Therefore, I completely disagree with the idea that schools should encourage all children to eat fruit.</em></p>
<p>In this version, the writer has presented a fact that logically supports their argument, and helps the reader understand why they hold this position.</p>
<p>Our test question will sometimes do this too:</p>
<p><em>There are now millions of cars on the road in most big cities. Pollution from cars is the most important problem that big cities face today.</em></p>
<p><em>To what extent do you agree or disagree?</em></p>
<p>The first sentence in this writing task presents a fact to support the argument being made in the second sentence - that this type of pollution is ‘<em>the most important</em>’ problem that big cities face.</p>
<section id="fact-and-opinion" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fact-and-opinion"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Fact and opinion</h2>
<p>A fact is something that can be objectively measured and verified, while an argument or opinion cannot. In the test question, we know that the first sentence is a fact because we can verify it by counting the number of cars on the roads. We cannot verify the second statement because it is an opinion; we can only discuss it, and decide whether it is a valid argument or not. This is what our essay must do, which helps to explain why there is no right or wrong answer in task 2.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>KEY IDEA: In writing task 2, you will be presented with an argument that you must discuss and respond to, there is no right or wrong answer. The question will sometimes include a fact that supports the argument being made. You do not need to discuss this fact, but you should not ignore it - it is there to make the context for your essay clear.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="perspective" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Perspective</h1>
<p>It is important to be aware when we are writing about things that are universally, or generally true, and when we are writing about things that are only true for us. This matters for bigger ideas too - our city will not necessarily look the same as my city, and it will not operate by the same rules, which are based on our culture and history. Thus, our ideas on city living, and life in general, will reflect our own background and experiences, and when we are writing, we need to help the reader see these issues from our viewpoint. Perspective matters.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-5/Pasted image 20250904203437.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>To the person in these images, the tree and the house appear large or small, and easy to see or difficult to see, depending on where they are standing, and what is happening around them. This neatly illustrates the meaning of the terms viewpoint, point of view, and position. Thus, a rich person, who has always lived in a luxurious penthouse, will not have the same perspective on city life as a homeless person living in the same city. Similarly, someone with severe food allergies will not see the topic of food and diet in the same way as a person without these problems.</p>
<p>If we live in a city where the justice system is unfair, this will inevitably affect our opinions about this topic, so we need to explain the context for our argument when discussing this issue. If we are writing about traffic problems, and we live in a very busy city like Ho Chi Minh city, we need to help the examiner to see the problem as we see it - from our perspective. We can do this by explaining the context for our dieas</p>
<p><em>Crime and punishment are extremely emotive issues in my country, where …</em></p>
<p><em>The traffic in my city is …, so …</em></p>
<section id="language-note" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="language-note"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Language note</h2>
<p>In academic writing, or when writing about a serious issue, we often begin by defining key terms. This can help to explain the context for the ideas in our argument. For example, if we are writing about the topic of ‘success’, we could begin by defining what this word means to us, or in our culture, which may be different to the examiner’s interpretation of the word.</p>
<p>Sometimes, we rephrase an idea in order to make it clearer. For example:</p>
<p><em>Many cities have more people than houses. This means that many people do not have anywhere to live.</em></p>
<p>In planning, we can use equals sign (=) to represent this:</p>
<p><em>Many cities have more people than houses = many people do not have anywhere to live.</em></p>
<p>Rephrasing the issue in this way help us to show a different way of looking at it; it changed the focus and helped to highlight how this issue affects the people involved. Other phrases that can be used like this are:</p>
<p><em>This means, … which means, … In other words, …</em></p>
<p>Whenever we use these phrases, what follows should be an explanation, or a different way to interpret what we have just said. However, the verb ‘to mean’ can also be used to show a consequence or result of something, like this:</p>
<p><em>Increasing house prices means fewer people can afford to buy a house.</em></p>
<p>When planning, we would use an arrow to show the connection between these ideas:</p>
<p>Increasing house prices -&gt; fewer people can afford to buy a house.</p>
<section id="exercises" class="level3" data-number="2.1.1">
<h3 data-number="2.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises"><span class="header-section-number">2.1.1</span> Exercises</h3>
<p>In the following extracts how are the phrases ‘in other words’ or ‘this means’ being used?</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 61%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 11%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>to explain the meaning of something</th>
<th>to show a different way of looking at something</th>
<th>to show the result or consequence of something</th>
<th>we cannot say because it is being used inaccurately</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>If you have a lot of money you can buy whatever you want, which means that food will never be a problem for you.</td>
<td></td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td><del>ok</del></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>In addition, sharing the cost of education and healthcare would also prevent people from taking it for granted. This means that having to pay for the service is equivalent to being more sincere.</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><del>ok</del></td>
<td>ok</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Local businesses might suffer as they do not have the resources to beat off competition from multinational companies, and they might be eventually put out of work. This not only means a loss of jobs, but also a loss of traditional products, which is cause for even greater concern.</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>The possibility of finding the same shops selling the same variety of items in almost every corner of the world can be alarming. In other words, every country has its own culture with its own particular foods, which allow us to identify it from every other country.</td>
<td></td>
<td><del>ok</del></td>
<td></td>
<td>ok</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>In sentence 1, the writer is showing a different way of looking at the issue of having a lot of money.</p>
<p>In sentence 2, the problem may be one of vocabulary (the word ‘sincere’ is inaccurate here) but this is not an explanation of the previous sentence.</p>
<p>In sentence 3, the writer is showing two results or consequences of what happens when local businesses close.</p>
<p>In sentence 4, the second sentence is providing a reason for the previous sentence, so ‘This is because’ would be more accurate</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="jumping-to-a-conclusion" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Jumping to a conclusion</h1>
<p>When candidates don’t allow enough time for critical thinking, they tend to jump to a conclusion that does not seem logical to the reader and so is rather confusing. The phrase ‘jump to a conclusion’ means reaching a quick decision when we don’t have all of the evidence we need, or before considering the evidence. Here is an example:</p>
<p><em>John has arrived late for work every day this week. Clearly, he is not committed to his job.</em></p>
<p>The first sentence is a verifiable fact - we can check the time that John arrived at work every day. However, the second sentence jumps to a conclusion about what this fact tells us about John’s attitude towards work. There are several reasons why John may be arriving late, such as problems with transport, a problem or illness at home, he may even arranged with his manager to stay late to finish an important project and start the day later than normal. The fact in the first sentence requires further investigation before a valid conclusion can be reached about what it means. Similarly, in the writing test, if we do not stop to think, we will not gather the evidence needed to reach a valid, logical conclusion that we can then explain clearly. Even more importantly, if we jump to a conclusion about what the test question means, then we are likely to lose marks for Task response.</p>
<p>Read the paragraph and try to guess what the topic of the writing task was.</p>
<p><em>First, let us consider the disadvantages of this trend towards driving more. If people drive more and more, our fossil fuels are likely to be depleted in the very near future. By 2050, it is estimated that human beings will have used up all of the natural resources if people keep using their vehicles more. Spending more time driving to work also means that people will have less time at work to do meaningful tasks. If it takes a person about 30 minutes to get to their destination, then they will lose approximately 15 hours a month. That invaluable amount of time could be better spend. In addition, the more time people spend driving, the more carbon emissions there will be in the atmosphere, which will further exacerbate our current environmental problems.</em></p>
<p>This is the topic he was asked to discuss:</p>
<p><em>Many people are now spending a lot of time traveling to work or school. Some people believe that this is a negative development while others think there are some benefits.</em></p>
<p>As we can see, driving is not mentioned in the question at all, but work is. This writer had spent a considerable amount of the paragraph explaining an issue that is not mentioned in the question (car driving and its impact on the environment), and then trying to connect this to the issue that <em>is</em> mentioned (work).</p>
<p>When PC asked why he had focused on cars and driving, he told that he lives in a very busy city, with major traffic problems, and where the vast majority of people drive to work or school every day. His perspective led him to interpret this question as, ‘everyone is now driving even more when traveling to work.’ In his city, the logical effects of this are that fossil fuels are being depleted, traffic is made worse, and work time is also being lost. Although we are being asked to use our own knowledge and experience to answer the question, the examiner needs help to be able to see the issue in the same way as we do.</p>
<p>What changes could you make to help the examiner see this candidate’s perspective more clearly? On our worksheet, try to rewrite the paragraph ourself so that the perspective is clear, and the argument is logically connected to the issue raised in the question.</p>
<p><em>First, let us consider the disadvantages of this trend. In my country, the vast majority of people drive to school or work. Therefore, if people are spending more time traveling, this means that they are also driving more and more. Because of this, our fossil fuels are likely to be depleted. In addition, the more people drive, the more carbon emissions there will be in the atmosphere, which will further exacerbate our current environmental problems. Spending more time driving to work and school also means that people will have less time to work on important tasks. If it takes a person about 30 minutes to get to their destination, then they will lose approximately 15 hours a month. That invaluable amount of time could be much better spend if people were abloe to shorten their journeys.</em></p>
<section id="points-to-notice" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="points-to-notice"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Points to notice</h2>
<ul>
<li>We can now understand the perspective and, as a result, the argument is clearer.</li>
<li>She used the phrases ‘In my country’ and ‘this means’ to show a different way of lokking at the issue raised in the question - one that reflects the perspective of the writer.</li>
<li>She has changed the order of some ideas so that they are organized more logically.</li>
<li>She cut this sentence: ‘<em>By 2050, it is estimated that human beings will have used up all of the natural resources if people keep using their vehicles more.</em>’ She did this because it is not necessary (the point about fossil fuels has already bene explained) and it is not directly connected to the original question. Going off on a tangent like this will reduce our Task response score.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-5/Pasted image 20250910155553.png" class="img-fluid"></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-5/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Listening practice - mistake log IELTS Practice Set 20 listening test 2</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/listening-practice-set-20-test-2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>37/40</p>
<section id="recording-1" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Recording 1</h1>
</section>
<section id="recording-2" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Recording 2</h1>
<section id="q18.-what-is-the-most-important-requirement-for-volunteers-at-the-festivals" class="level3" data-number="2.0.1">
<h3 data-number="2.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q18.-what-is-the-most-important-requirement-for-volunteers-at-the-festivals"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.1</span> <strong>Q18. What is the most important requirement for volunteers at the festivals?</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Transcript extract:</strong></p>
<p><em>“We try to use volunteers who are flexible, though, because some festival events are held outdoors and the weather may affect the size of the audience and even whether the event can take place. So there can be changes at short notice.</em> <strong><em>What’s essential, though, is being able to get on well with other people and also to deal with someone who’s behaving badly, as occasionally happens.</em></strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Your answer:</strong> C (Flexibility)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Correct answer:</strong> A (Interpersonal skills)</p></li>
</ul>
<p>✅ <strong>Why?</strong></p>
<p>The speaker first <em>mentions flexibility</em> (and IELTS often puts distractors before the correct answer). But then comes the keyword <em>“What’s essential, though…”</em> which signals the true answer.</p>
<p>So, the test checks if you notice the contrast between <em>“try to use”</em> vs.&nbsp;<em>“What’s essential”</em>.</p>
<p>⚠️ <strong>Your mistake:</strong> You stopped at “flexibility” and treated it as the final answer. But IELTS often hides the real answer in the <em>second half</em> of the sentence with phrases like <em>“but, however, what’s essential, in fact”</em>.</p>
</section>
<section id="q19.-new-volunteers-will-start-working-in-the-week-beginning" class="level3" data-number="2.0.2">
<h3 data-number="2.0.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q19.-new-volunteers-will-start-working-in-the-week-beginning"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.2</span> <strong>Q19. New volunteers will start working in the week beginning …</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Transcript extract:</strong></p>
<p><em>“Our plan is to get your work in September</em> <strong><em>after a week’s training starting on the 2nd</em></strong>_. So, we’ll be timetabling you for duties_ <strong><em>the following week from the 9th onward.</em></strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Your answer:</strong> A (2 September)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Correct answer:</strong> B (9 September)</p></li>
</ul>
<p>✅ <strong>Why?</strong></p>
<p>The speaker mentions <em>training starts on the 2nd</em> (distractor), but the actual <em>start of work</em> is <em>the following week from the 9th onward</em>.</p>
<p>The key is the words <em>“after a week’s training”</em> → you don’t start on the 2nd, that’s only training.</p>
<p>⚠️ <strong>Your mistake:</strong> You focused on the first date you heard (Sept 2) instead of waiting for the sentence to finish. IELTS loves this “first date is training, second date is real start” trap. # Recording 3</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="recording-4" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Recording 4</h1>
<section id="what-happened-on-q33" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-happened-on-q33"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> <strong>What happened on Q33</strong></h2>
<p><strong>Question:</strong> “Famous (33) ______ are influential.”</p>
<p><strong>Transcript cue:</strong> “…what <strong>well-known chefs</strong> are putting on their menus.”</p>
<p><strong>Your answer:</strong> <em>chiefs</em></p>
<p><strong>Correct:</strong> <strong>chefs</strong> (also accepted: <em>cooks</em>)</p>
<section id="why-chiefs-is-wrong" class="level3" data-number="3.1.1">
<h3 data-number="3.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-chiefs-is-wrong"><span class="header-section-number">3.1.1</span> <strong>Why “chiefs” is wrong</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Meaning:</strong> <em>Chief</em> = leader/boss (police chief, tribal chief) → doesn’t fit “putting things on menus.”</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Context collocations:</strong> <em>famous/well-known/celebrity</em> <strong><em>chefs</em></strong> + <em>menus</em> is a strong culinary collocation.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Pronunciation trap:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>chef</strong> /ʃef/ (starts with <strong>sh</strong> sound)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>chief</strong> /tʃiːf/ (starts with <strong>ch</strong> sound, long <strong>ee</strong>)</p>
<p>In fast speech, the vowel + consonant can blur, so you rely on <strong>context</strong> (“menus”) + <strong>topic</strong> (food marketing).</p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="quick-discrimination-drill-say-them-aloud" class="level3" data-number="3.1.2">
<h3 data-number="3.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quick-discrimination-drill-say-them-aloud"><span class="header-section-number">3.1.2</span> <strong>Quick discrimination drill (say them aloud)</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>chef</strong> = /ʃ/ as in <strong>sh</strong>e, short <strong>e</strong>: <em>sh-ef</em></p></li>
<li><p><strong>chief</strong> = /tʃ/ as in <strong>ch</strong>eese, long <strong>ee</strong>: <em>cheef</em></p>
<p>Try: <em>celebrity chefs</em>, <em>head chef</em>, <em>Michelin-starred chef</em> vs.&nbsp;<em>police chief</em>, <em>tribal chief</em>, <em>chief executive</em>.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="exam-tactics-for-this-item-type" class="level3" data-number="3.1.3">
<h3 data-number="3.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exam-tactics-for-this-item-type"><span class="header-section-number">3.1.3</span> <strong>Exam tactics for this item type</strong></h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Pre-read the gap:</strong> “Famous ___ are influential.”</p>
<p>Predict likely nouns: <em>chefs, influencers, brands, retailers</em>. With “menus” later, <strong>chefs</strong> becomes obvious.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Use domain cues:</strong> This section is about <strong>food trends</strong> → expect <em>chefs, restaurants, menus, supermarkets</em>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Grammar check (fast):</strong> “Famous <strong>chef</strong> are …” (ungrammatical) → needs plural <strong>chefs</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Write what you hear, but sanity-check with context.</strong> If you wrote <em>chiefs</em>, ask, “Do chiefs have menus?” → no → revise to <strong>chefs</strong>.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="re-usable-collocations-from-this-passage" class="level3" data-number="3.1.4">
<h3 data-number="3.1.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="re-usable-collocations-from-this-passage"><span class="header-section-number">3.1.4</span> <strong>Re-usable collocations from this passage</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>celebrity / well-known / Michelin-starred chefs</strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong>put (a dish/ingredient) on the menu</strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong>influence food trends</strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong>supermarkets track what’s trending</strong></p></li>
<li><p><strong>brand ambassadors / social media influencers</strong></p></li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>listening</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/listening-practice-set-20-test-2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Creating Different types of Argument</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-3/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="arguing-by-adding-information" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Arguing by adding information</h1>
<p>The choice will depend on the ideas that occur to us when planning our essay - it cannot be decided in advance. This is because our ideas shape our argument, which then determines the language we must use. This cannot happen in reverse, beginning with the language, which is why a fixed template approach will not work.</p>
<p>When creating an argument:</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-3/Pasted image 20250904165711.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>One way to build a clear argument is by presenting the different reasons that, when added together, led us to our conclusion. In our planning, we can use plus sign (+) to show arguments like this.</p>
<p>Words and phrases often used in this type or argument are:</p>
<p><strong>Firstly, Secondly, Thirdly, In addition, Similarly, also, etc.</strong></p>
<p>We will look at a model and use critical thinking to identity the ideas within the argument and to understand how the ideas are connected.</p>
<section id="practice" class="level3" data-number="1.0.1">
<h3 data-number="1.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice"><span class="header-section-number">1.0.1</span> Practice</h3>
<p>Look at the argument being made in the paragraph below and try to identify 3 points or ideas (PC’s conclusion) and 3 reasons given for believing them. (Mentally adding ‘because’, or ‘therefore’ can help us identify a reason or conclusion - this is helpful for IELTS reading too)</p>
<p><em>There are several reasons why the government collects taxes. Firstly, the money raised can be used to build new roads or public buildings. Secondly, existing infrastructure, such as schools and hospitals, can be updated or repaired. Finally, these funds are needed to pay the salaries of all government workers, including firefighters and the police. Thus, taxes help improve the community while also making it safer.</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The ‘evidence’ is the reason why her believe a conclusion is valid or reasonable, so the three reasons given in this paragraph are her supporting evidence. She used her experience and knowledge of the world to think of these, which is what the task tells us to do. The conclusions, or the points she make, are her personal views about what this evidence shows or tells us. Remember, each of these conclusions, or points, reveals her position on this issue - if the reasons she give to support are unclear or illogical (as we saw in the previous lesson), then her position and conclusions will also be unclear. If this evidence is missing, her ideas will be both unclear and undeveloped.</li>
<li>The points she make (her conclusion) are broad, general ideas (e.g.&nbsp;Taxes help make the community safer). In contrast, the reasons given are more specific, and they provide concrete supporting evidence to support her ideas (e.g.&nbsp;Taxes are used to pay the salaries of firefighters). Notice also that she was able to provide supporting evidence without using the phrases ‘For example’. We will review this idea in Lesson 6.</li>
<li>Notice her use of referencing in this paragraph (the way that she refer back to previous ideas). In the practice exercise, she used the word ‘taxes’ repeatedly, by if we look at her paragraph, we will see that she used synonyms to avoid repeating this word. This helps with our Coherence and cohesion score, and shows how building our vocabulary helps improve our writing score.</li>
</ol>
<p>Two words are used as synonyms to refer back to ‘taxes’: money, funds</p>
<p>Infrastructure refers to public services such as water, transport, rubbish collection etc.</p>
<p>Salaries refer to the money paid to workers. ## Adding emphasis</p>
<p>The language used in this argument tells the reader that each reason is equally important. However, we sometimes want to show that one reason is more important than the others, as in the following example.</p>
<p>There are several reasons why the government collects taxes. In terms of infrastructure, the money raised can be used to build new roads or public buildings, or to maintain existing structures such as schools and hospitals. <strong>More importantly,</strong> these funds are needed to pay the salaries of all government workers, including firefighters and the police. Thus, taxes <strong>not only</strong> help improve the community <strong>but also</strong> make it safer.</p>
<p>The phrases in bold are used to show her position, which can be summed up as: there are several good reasons for collecting taxes, and I believe that safety is the most important of these. Other phrases we may find useful when making an argument like this are:</p>
<p><strong>Moreover, Furthermore, What is more, Even more importantly.</strong></p>
<p>Notice that she did not use a connecting phrases between the first two sentences - the link between them is made clear through the use of referencing (‘the money raised’ refers back to ‘collects taxes’). As we have seen, some writers go even further, omitting even more connecting words and phrases. As well as removing clear signposting, this also creates a different tone in the writing, and sometimes goes too far.</p>
<p>Version 1:</p>
<p><em>There are several reasons why the government collects taxes. Firstly, the money raised can be used to build new roads or public buildings. Secondly, existing infrastructure, such as schools and hospitals, can be updated or repaired. Finally, these funds are needed to pay the salaries of all government workers, including firefighters and the police.</em></p>
<p>Version 2:</p>
<p><em>There are several reasons why the government collects taxes. The money raised can be used to build new roads or public buildings. Existing infrastructure, such as schools and hospitals, can be updated or repaired. The funds are needed to pay the salaries of all government workers, including firefighters and the police.</em></p>
<p>Second version is far more difficult for language learners to master.</p>
<p>In Version 2 the links are made clear through the use of synonyms (‘collects taxes’ in sentence 1 = ‘The money raised’ in sentence 2 and ‘these funds’ in sentence 3) The sentences are also connected through a common theme or context - each sentence provides a reason why the government collects taxes.</p>
<p>Something between these two:</p>
<p>Version 3:</p>
<p>There are several reasons why the government collects taxes. The money raised can be used to build new roads or public buildings. Existing infrastructure, such as schools and hospitals, can also be updated or repaired. Furthermore, the funds are needed to pay the salaries of all government workers, including firefighters and the police.</p>
</section>
<section id="practice-1" class="level3" data-number="1.0.2">
<h3 data-number="1.0.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice-1"><span class="header-section-number">1.0.2</span> Practice</h3>
<p>Match conclusion and point</p>
<p>The money can be used to build new roads or public buildings.</p>
<p>taxes pay the salaries of government workers including firefighters and the police</p>
<p>existing infrastructure such as schools and hospitals can be updated or repaired.</p>
<p>all of the ideas in this paragraph</p>
<p>Conclusion 1: There are several reasons why governments collect taxes.</p>
<p>Conclusion 2: taxes help improve the community</p>
<p>Conclusion 3: taxes make the community safer.</p>
<hr>
<p>Conclusion 2: taxes help improve the community -&gt; The money can be used to build new roads or public buildings., -&gt; -&gt; existing infrastructure such as schools and hospitals can be updated or repaired.</p>
<p>C 3: taxes make the community safer. taxes pay the salaries of government workers including firefighters and the police</p>
<p>C1: all of the ideas in this paragraph</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="arguing-by-showing-cause-and-effect" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Arguing by showing cause and effect</h1>
<p>Rather than separate reasons added together, these arguments show that one idea has an impact on a second, and perhaps even a third, in a domino effect.</p>
<p>They are all connected, like links in a chain, which is why we also refer to this as a chain reaction. This type of argument helps explain that we believe something is a good or bad idea because of the effect it can have, and these provide the evidence in this type of argument. Generally, these arguments are based on facts or claims made by the writer, which may come from a claim made in the question itself or may be based on our own knowledge or experience.</p>
<p>In planning, we should use an arrow to show the connection between ideas in this kind of argument. Here are some examples of phrases that are often used to present an argument like this:</p>
<p><em>This means that …; This causes …; This can lead to …; As a result …; in turn; if … then …</em></p>
<section id="practice-2" class="level3" data-number="2.0.1">
<h3 data-number="2.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice-2"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.1</span> Practice</h3>
<p>Read the extract and identify the claim being made and three effects this has.</p>
<p>In many big cities, the population exceeds the number of flats and houses available, which means that many people do not have anywhere to live. This causes several problems. Firstly, it can put pressure on local charities, who then have to find food and shelter for the homeless.</p>
</section>
<section id="point-to-notice" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="point-to-notice"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Point to notice</h2>
<p>This argument relies on her ability to clearly explain a complex problem: a lack of houses leads to increased homelessness, which then increases problems for local charities. A plan or map of this argument looks like this:</p>
<p>In many big cities the population exceeds the number of flats and house -&gt; many people do not have anywhere to love -&gt; puts pressure of local charities -&gt; charities have to find food and shelter for the homeless.</p>
<p>The complex chain of events forced her to produce complex grammatical structures. Complexity is not something we should aim to build into our writing through adding even more complex grammar points, creating overly long sentences, or using high-level vocabulary.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>If you try to boost your score by writing long, complex sentences, the complex issues you are explaining will be confusing to the reader, and your argument will be impossible to follow. Explaining complex ideas in a clear and simple way will raise your chances of achieving band 7, not lower it.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-3/Pasted image 20250904173330.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="arguing-by-predicting-a-result-or-effect" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Arguing by predicting a result or effect</h1>
<p>We may want to prove that an action is good or bad by making a claim about the effect or result it <em>will, would, may,</em> or <em>could</em> have. in this type or argument, we are offering this predicted result as a reason why we believe it should, or should not, be allowed to happen. We may be sure of the result or effect of this action because we have direct experience of it, or we may be expressing a future concern, or making a possible prediction.</p>
<p>This type of argument uses the language of speculation, and such sentences often begin with ‘If’ or ‘When’. The language tells us how likely it is that the action will occur, and how confident the writer feels about the result of the action. Thus, when it is used accurately and appropriately, the language we use helps to make our position clear and, if it is used inaccurately, it can make our position less clear.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Many people try to use complex grammatical structures such as conditionals in their writing to boost their Grammatical range and accuracy score. However, this will only work if the structures are used accurately and appropriately - in other words, when they help to clearly explain your argument and your position.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="practice-3" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice-3"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Practice</h2>
<section id="q-1" class="level3" data-number="3.1.1">
<h3 data-number="3.1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q-1"><span class="header-section-number">3.1.1</span> Q 1</h3>
<p>In conditional sentences (using if or when), one clause is dependent on another clause happening first. We are essentially saying: If (or when) X happens / happened, Y will / would / may / might / could (etc.) happen / happens as a result.</p>
<p>We can see these two clauses as the action and the result, or effect, of this action.</p>
<p>The different tenses used tell us how likely these actions and results (or effects) are.</p>
<p>Look at the following sentences (1-6) and identify the action and the result.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>If the government helps homeless people, this will solve all of their problems. (action: helps homeless people, result: all their problems are solved)</li>
<li>When homeless people are given free accommodation, their health often improves as a result. (action: give free accommodation to homeless people, result: improve their health)</li>
<li>If the government built more affordable housing, this could improve the situation for many people.</li>
<li>When homeless people have nowhere to shelter, winter is extremely difficult for them.</li>
<li>Very few people would be upset if taxes were increased to help the homeless.</li>
<li>If people are unemployed for a long time, they can eventually become homeless.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="q2" class="level3" data-number="3.1.2">
<h3 data-number="3.1.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q2"><span class="header-section-number">3.1.2</span> Q2</h3>
<p>Look at the tense used for each action in the sentences above and decide how likely it is to happen.</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 48%">
<col style="width: 14%">
<col style="width: 14%">
<col style="width: 21%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>this happens in the real world</th>
<th>this is possible in the future</th>
<th>this is less likely to happen in the future</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>If the government helps homeless people, this will solve all of their problems.</td>
<td></td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>When homeless people are given free accommodation, their health often improves as a result.</td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>If the government built more affordable housing, this could improve the situation for many people.</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>ok</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>When homeless people have nowhere to shelter, winter is extremely difficult for them.</td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Very few people would be upset if taxes were increased to help the homeless.</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>ok</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>If people are unemployed for a long time, they can eventually become homeless.</td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Notice that the writer is telling us how likely these actions are through the use of the different tenses:</p>
<p>If + the simple present tells us this is possible in the future</p>
<p>When + the simple present tells us this generally happens (If can also be used in other way:)</p>
<p>If + simple past tells us the writer thinks this is less likely to happen.</p>
<p>For sentences 1 and 6, we need to consider both clauses. In sentence 1, the use of ‘will solve’ tells us the writer is presenting a possible future action in the first clause (‘if the government helps’). In sentence 6, the second clause (‘can eventually become’) tells us the writer is presenting a real situation and not an imagined one.</p>
</section>
<section id="q3" class="level3" data-number="3.1.3">
<h3 data-number="3.1.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q3"><span class="header-section-number">3.1.3</span> Q3</h3>
<p>Now look at the tense used for each result. How sure does the writer feel about each result?</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 75%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 7%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>100% sure</th>
<th>75% sure</th>
<th>50% sure</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>…this will solve all of their problems.</td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>… their health often improves as a result.</td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>… this could improve the situation for many people.</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td>ok</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>… winter is extremely difficult for them.</td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Very few people would be upset if taxes were increased to help the homeless.</td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>… they can eventually become homeless.</td>
<td>ok</td>
<td></td>
<td>ok</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>again, the tenses used tell us how confident or sure the writer feels about this result. In conditional sentences (where the result is dependent on a previous action): - the simple present, will, and would all tell us the writer is 100% sure that this will / would result - the modal verbs may, could, might tell us the writer is only 50% sure, or sees this as just one possible result - adverbs (e.g.&nbsp;probably) and phrases such as ‘is likely to’ can be used to show 75% certainty that a result would or will probably happen or is likely to happen.</p>
<p>Being cautious</p>
<p>If the government helps homeless people, this … solve … of their problems.</p>
<p>…, this could/ may /might/ is likely to solve many/ some/ most of their problems.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="points-to-notice-about-conditional-sentences" class="level2" data-number="3.2">
<h2 data-number="3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="points-to-notice-about-conditional-sentences"><span class="header-section-number">3.2</span> Points to notice about conditional sentences</h2>
<ul>
<li>The likely <strong>actions</strong> are i the simple present, and use if or when</li>
<li>The <strong>less likely / unlikely actions</strong> use the simple past.</li>
<li>The less certain results use <strong>may / could / possibly</strong> / etc.</li>
<li>The 100% sure results use <strong>will, would</strong>, or <strong>the simple present</strong></li>
<li>Remember, these sentences require 2 clauses, and one clause (B) is ‘conditional’ upon the other (A).</li>
<li>We can say: ‘If A happens then B will result’. This is a very firm prediction about the result.</li>
<li>We can also say: ‘If A happened then B would result’. Although the first event is less likely to happen, we are still making a firm prediction about the result. We are saying that ‘A’ is less certain (it may not happen), but if it <strong>DID</strong> happen, then B <strong>would definitely</strong> result from this.</li>
</ul>
<p>The first sentence from this exercise makes a very strong prediction about the result of the government’s action</p>
<p><em>If the government helps homeless people, this will solve all of their problems.</em></p>
<p>It is highly unlikely that all of the problems that homeless people face will definitely be solved in this way. In formal writing, it is better to be more cautious about claims or predictions that we make. The language used to show this is known has ‘hedging language’, and it is important in making an argument and in making our position clear.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-3/Pasted image 20250904181229.png" class="img-fluid"> • To practise further, look through any of your previous essays and scan your writing for the following words and phrases: If, when, as a result, result in, causes, will, would, could, might. • Look carefully at the arguments you made using these words — is your position clear? Does the tense or verb accurately reflect how sure you feel about the result? (Think about your use of conditionals and modal verbs.) Make a note of any grammar points you need to study and make sure to practise these often. • If you have written any essays based on questions asking you to discuss the problems and solutions or the causes and effects of a problem, look at the body paragraphs in your essay and think about the following: • Can you Identify any claims you have made and the effects that you discussed? • How are the ideas in your argument connected? • How did you show this connection? • What improvements can you make?</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-3/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Article a/an before noun phrases</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/common-mistake-advance-2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="tick-the-correct-sentence-in-each-pair" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Tick the correct sentence in each pair</h1>
<p>1 a The company has captured a significant share of the market. b the company has captured significant share of the market.</p>
<p>-&gt; a share is a countable noun (a share, two shares)</p>
<p>2 a I think they are also right to certain extent. b I think they are also right to a certain extent.</p>
<p>2 -&gt; a -&gt;&gt; b</p>
<p>a certain extent is a phrase</p>
<p>Don’t forget to include <em>a/an</em> before an adjective + singular noun combination.</p>
<p><em>He clearly has <strong>a good understanding</strong> of the issues.</em></p>
<p><em>Many students have <strong>a part-time job</strong> while studying.</em></p>
<p>Notice the position of adverbs (very, really, quite, etc.) in these phrases:</p>
<p><em>We have <strong>a very high percentage</strong> of women working in senior government posts.</em></p>
<p><em>There was <strong>a really good atmosphere</strong>.</em></p>
<p><em>In my view, this is <strong>quite a strong argument</strong>.</em></p>
<p>Some common noun phrases to be careful with:</p>
<ul>
<li>to a certain extent/degree: I agree with you to a certain degree.</li>
<li>a wide range/variety: We have a wide range of books to choose from.</li>
<li>a(n) large/small/equal number/amount: an equal number of men and women</li>
<li>a high/large/small/greater proportion/percentage: a small proportion of patients</li>
<li>a long time: I haven’t seen her for a long time.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="correct-the-mistake-below" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Correct the mistake below</h1>
<p>All competitors should have a equal chance of winning.</p>
</section>
<section id="use-the-words-below-in-the-same-order-to-form-correct-sentences-adding-any-necessary-articles-or-prepositions" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Use the words below in the same order to form correct sentences, adding any necessary articles or prepositions</h1>
<p>1 Only / small / number / troublemakers / were / responsible for / problems.</p>
<p>-&gt; Only a small number of trouble makers were responsible for the problems.</p>
<p>2 Computers / play / very / important / role / education / nowadays.</p>
<p>-&gt; Computers play a very important role in education nowadays.</p>
<p>3 She / can’t / afford to / study / full-time / basis.</p>
<p>-&gt; She can’t afford to study on a full-time basis.</p>
<p>verb phrase: can’t afford to</p>
<p>expression is ‘on a full-time basis’</p>
<p>4 Teenagers / should be / allowed / greater / degree / freedom</p>
<p>-&gt; Teenagers should be allowed a greater degree of freedom.</p>
<p>a greater degree of freedom</p>
<p>5 They / have / slightly / different / approach to / studying</p>
<p>They have a slightly different approach to studying</p>
<p>6 We / had / one-week / intensive / training / course.</p>
<p>We had a one-week intensive training course.</p>
<p>7 There / has been / gradual / increase / number / thefts.</p>
<p>There has been gradual increase a number of thefts.</p>
<p>-&gt; They has been a gradual increase in the number of thefts.</p>
<p>8 They / offer / quite / wide / variety / courses.</p>
<p>They offer a quite wide variety of courses.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/common-mistake-advance-2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>More complex arguments</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="arguing-by-showing-contrast" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Arguing by showing contrast</h1>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Candidates at C1 and C2 (bands 7 to 9) have mastered the language from A1 to C2; they use high-level language accurately and only at the appropriate time. You will show C1 and C2 skills by clearly explaining a complex argument, not by using as much high-level grammar or vocabulary as possible.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>We can provide strong reasoning or give extra support for an idea by making a point a bout a contrasting idea or argument. This can be a useful way of finding extra ideas when we are stuck. To get ideas like this, ask ourseves, ‘<em>What would happen if we <u>didn’t</u> have / <u>do</u> this?</em>’ or ‘<em>What happens when we <u>don’t</u> have / <u>do</u> this?</em>’ For example, ’What happens if the government <u>doesn’t </u>help poor people.</p>
<p>This type of argument can be useful when writing about whether a development is positive or negative. The words and phrases we might find in this type of argument are:</p>
<p><strong>If … does not … then; Without … ,</strong></p>
<p>Look at the following example:</p>
<p><em>In many big cities, the population exceeds the number of flats and houses available, which means that many people do not have anywhere to live. This causes several problems. Firstly, it can put pressure on local charities, who have to find food and shelter for the homeless. If the government does not step in to help people who are struggling financially, then this puts even more stress on community programs, and causes homelessness to rise even further.</em></p>
<section id="point-to-notice" class="level2" data-number="1.1">
<h2 data-number="1.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="point-to-notice"><span class="header-section-number">1.1</span> Point to notice</h2>
<ul>
<li>The tenses used here (the simple present and the conditional) indicate that the writer has some experience or knowledge of this topic, and feels very confident that these effects <em>will</em> happen. Remember, if we are less certain, we can show this by using modal verbs (can, may etc) like this</li>
</ul>
<p>If the government does not step in to help people who are struggling financially, then this can put even more stress on community programs, and may cause homelessness to rise even further</p>
<ul>
<li>The same language is useful in presenting a counterargument.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="combining-different-types-of-arguments" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Combining different types of arguments</h1>
<p>At the moment, our paragraph is quite short. However, if we want to add another negative effect resulting from a lack of housing, we need to be very careful. A common mistake at band 6 is to simply add a new idea, like the final sentence in this extract:</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/Pasted image 20250904182248.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The final sentence here creates a referencing problem - the pronoun ‘it’ confuses the reader, and so the conclusion becomes unclear. A pronoun generally refers back to the last noun or idea mentioned, which in this case is either the rise in homelessness, or ‘If the government does not step in to help people.’</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/Pasted image 20250904182419.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The reader understands this as</p>
<p>If the government does not step into help people who are struggling financially, this means that house prices and rents remain very high.</p>
<p>or</p>
<p>If homelessness rises further, this means that house prices and rents remain very high.</p>
<p>In both cases, the link between these ideas is not clear, so a referencing problem like this often results in a band 6 ‘unclear conclusion’.</p>
<p>The writer actually intended to add another negative effect of the issue mentioned in the first sentence of this paragraph and make the following more logical argument:</p>
<p>‘When the population exceeds the number of houses and flats available, this makes house prices high’.</p>
<p>To show that we are adding a new point to a much earlier idea, we need to use a synonym or paraphrase to refer back, like this.</p>
<p>‘In addition, a lack of accommodation means that house prices and rents remain very high.’</p>
<p>Using paraphrase or a synonym rather than a pronoun to refer back to an earlier part of the paragraph clearly signals which 2 ideals are being linked by the connection phrases. ‘In addition.’ Look out for this type of referencing in the IELTS reading test too.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/Pasted image 20250904182832.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="exercises" class="level3" data-number="2.0.1">
<h3 data-number="2.0.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercises"><span class="header-section-number">2.0.1</span> Exercises</h3>
<section id="q1" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q1">Q1</h4>
<p>Which of the following points would follow on logically to conclude our paragraph?</p>
<p>Thus, housing problems have an impact on everyone in the community.</p>
<p>Thus, houses are likely to become even more expensive in the future.</p>
<p>Thus, employment is also a very important issue.</p>
<p>Thus, the government is not responsible for housing problems.</p>
<p>1 <img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/Pasted image 20250904183157.png" class="img-fluid"> # Joining ideas together to vary sentence length</p>
<p>High-level writers show an awareness of style, and try to vary the length of their sentences. Using a mixture of long and shorter sentences makes reading easier and also makes our writing less repetitive.</p>
<p><em>In many big cities, the population exceeds the number of flats and houses available, which means that many people do not have anywhere to live. This causes several problems. Firstly, it can put pressure on local charities, who have to find food and shelter for the homeless. If the government does not step in to help people who are struggling financially, then this puts even more stress on community programmes, and causes homelessness to rise even further. In addition, a lack of accommodation means that house prices and rents remain very high. Thus, housing problems have an impact on everyone in the community.</em></p>
<p>The first sentence of the paragraph makes a claim, and the remaining sentences either explain the effects of this claim, or a reaching conclusion about what these effects tell us. Remember, the effects can be seen as the supporting evidence or reasoning in this type of argument.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="practice" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practice"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Practice</h2>
<p>Use symbols to show how the ideas are connected.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/Pasted image 20250904184111.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>There some symbols we can used in planning</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/Pasted image 20250904184142.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Alternatives to use easily in keyboard:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 26%">
<col style="width: 26%">
<col style="width: 46%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th><strong>Meaning</strong></th>
<th><strong>Symbol (hard)</strong></th>
<th><strong>Easy keyboard alternative</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>therefore / thus</td>
<td>∴</td>
<td><strong>=&gt;</strong> or <strong>so</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>this means</td>
<td>=</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>rises / increases</td>
<td>↑</td>
<td><strong>up</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>falls / decreases</td>
<td>↓</td>
<td><strong>dn</strong></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="tracing-the-development-of-an-argument" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tracing-the-development-of-an-argument"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Tracing the development of an argument</h2>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/Pasted image 20250904184407.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>As this image shows, this is a very complex argument. It combines arguing by showing cause and effect, arguing by showing contrast, and arguing by adding information. Because of this complexity, there is a greater chance of language errors, and it is particularly difficult to explain the progression of the argument clearly and simply. When planning, we need to be aware of how complex our argument is before begin writing so that we can take extra care when connecting our ides, particularly when referring back to a much earlier idea.</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/Pasted image 20250904184636.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Vocabulary note:
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>We can say that <strong>A causes B</strong> or that <strong>B is the result of A</strong>. Reversing ideas like this is a useful way to avoid repeating the same language and structures. Here are some other variations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise can cause obesity.</li>
<li>Obesity can be caused by eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise.</li>
<li>Obesity is often the result of eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise.</li>
<li>Eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise an result in obesity.</li>
<li>Eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise can lead to obesity.</li>
<li>Obesity can result from eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise.</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<section id="exercise" class="level3" data-number="2.2.1">
<h3 data-number="2.2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="exercise"><span class="header-section-number">2.2.1</span> Exercise</h3>
<p>Fill in the blanks with the correct verb or preposition?</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>A poor diet can <font color="#245bdb">cause / lead to</font> health problems such as Type 2 diabetes.</li>
<li>Type 2 diabetes can be caused <font color="#245bdb">by</font> eating food that is high in sugar.</li>
<li>Type 2 diabetes is often the <font color="#245bdb">result</font> of eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise.</li>
<li>Eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise can result <font color="#245bdb">in</font> many health problems.</li>
<li>Eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise can <font color="#245bdb">lead</font> to Type 2 diabetes.</li>
<li>Type 2 diabetes can <font color="#245bdb">result</font> from eating too much fast food and a lack of exercise.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="extra-practice" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="extra-practice"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Extra practice</h2>
<p>Practice changing the length of the sentences in our paragraph by doing the following:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>make the first sentence shorter and the second sentence longer</p></li>
<li><p>break the third sentence up it into 2 shorter ones</p></li>
<li><p>connect the last 2 sentences</p></li>
<li><p>Be sure to study and practise relative clauses if you struggle with this exercise.</p></li>
<li><p>Rewrite the paragraph using one or more variations of the verb ‘cause’ from the language note.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Varying sentence lengths</strong></p>
<p>In many big cities, the population exceeds the number of flats and houses available. This means that many people do not have anywhere to live, which causes several problems. Firstly, it can put pressure on local charities and homeless shelters, who have to find food and shelter for the homeless. If the government does not step in to help people who are struggling financially, this puts even more stress on community programmes. When this happens, it can cause homelessness to rise even further. In addition, a lack of accommodation means that house prices and rents remain very high, which shows that housing problems affect everyone in the community.</p>
<p>In many big cities, the population exceeds the number of flats and houses available.</p>
<p>shorter -&gt;</p>
<p>In many big cities, people outnumber available home.</p>
<p><strong>In many big cities where people outnumber available homes.</strong></p>
<p>This means that many people do not have anywhere to live, which causes several problems.</p>
<p>-&gt; longer</p>
<p>This means that a large number of people find themselves without nay place to live, a situation which inevitable causes several problems for both individuals and society.</p>
<p>Firstly, it can put pressure on local charities and homeless shelters, who have to find food and shelter for the homeless. -&gt; break to 2 shorter sentences</p>
<p>Firstly, it can put pressure on local charities and homeless shelters. In particular, they have to find food and shelter for the homeless.</p>
<p>When this happens, it can cause homelessness to rise even further. In addition, a lack of accommodation means that house prices and rents remain very high, which shows that the housing problem affects everyone in the community.</p>
<p>-&gt; connect 2 to 1</p>
<p>When this happens, it can cause homelessness to rise even further, and the lack of accommodation also means that house prices and rents remain very high, showing that the housing problem affects everyone in the community.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/writing-task-2-4/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>GRE Verbal Practice</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/gre-verbal-practice/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Although the film is rightly judged imperfected by most of today’s critics, the film being created today are … it, since its release in 1940 provoked sufficient critical discussion to enhance the intellectual respectively of cinema considerably.</p>
<p>A beholden to</p>
<p>B in debted to</p>
<p>C derivate of</p>
<p>D based on</p>
<p>E distinguishable from</p>
<p>F biased against</p>
<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/gre-verbal-practice/Pasted image 20250902174949.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Step 1: Logic</p>
<p>The sentence contrast two ideas:</p>
<ul>
<li>The 1940 film is imperfect. (negative)</li>
<li>Despite this, it had an important influence on films today (positive).</li>
</ul>
<p>So, the blank must mean “owe something to / influenced by”.</p>
<p>Step 2: Options</p>
<p>A beholden to -&gt; means “indebted to” (slightly archaic but valid) B indebted to -&gt; directly means “owe something to” C derivative of -&gt; means “copied from” (too strong slightly off) D based on -&gt; possible, but usually used for content/story, not influence E distinguishable from -&gt; opposite meaning F biased against -&gt; opposite meaning</p>
<p>Step 3: Best fit</p>
<p>the correct sense: today’s films owe something to that 1940 film.</p>
<p>So the best choice is:</p>
<p>B/ indebted to</p>
<p>(A. beholden to could also work in older/literary phrasing, but GRE prefers the more standard form).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>gre</category>
  <category>verbal</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/gre-verbal-practice/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Practice Writing Task 1</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w1-pie/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w1-pie/Pasted image 20250901114900.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The three pie charts compare the proportions of five categories of books sold by a bookseller in 1972, 1992, and 2012.</p>
<p>Overall, adult fiction rose dramatically to dominate sales by the end of the period, whereas biography and the residual “others” category both contracted sharply. Children’s titles edged up slightly, while travel books first gained ground and then fell back.</p>
<p>In 1972, sales were fairly balanced: adult fiction, children’s fiction and biography each accounted for 20%, with travel on 15% and others the single largest segment at 25%. By 1992, adult fiction had become the clear leader at 25%, children’s books stood at 22%, and travel rose to 18%. In contrast, biography slipped to 15%, and others declined to 20%.</p>
<p>The most pronounced change occurred over the following two decades. Adult fiction more than doubled its share, surging to 45% in 2012. Children’s fiction continued a modest upward trajectory to 25%, placing it second. By comparison, travel’s slice nearly halved to 10%, biography fell even more steeply to 8%, and others shrank to 12%. Consequently, by 2012, the market had become far less even, with adult fiction alone representing almost half of all books sold.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>graphs</category>
  <category>task-1</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w1-pie/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to express agree/disagree, positive/negative, compare</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w-express/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Use in Writing Task 2</p>
<section id="express-agree-disagree" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Express Agree / Disagree</h1>
<p><strong>I agree that</strong> + S + V / <strong>I agree with</strong> ~</p>
<p><strong>I agree that</strong> any child can become a good musician with enough practice.</p>
<p>I firmly believe that + S + V</p>
<p>I firmly believe that money is a better motivator than a job title for some employees.</p>
<p>I support the idea that + S + V</p>
<p>I support the idea that governments should fine people who do not recycle.</p>
<p>Some people think that + S + V</p>
<p>Some people think that learning languages is an important part of a well-rounded education.</p>
<p>It is a common belief that + S + V</p>
<p>It is a common belief that concentrating on practical skills is beneficial for students.</p>
<p>It is true that + S + v</p>
<p>It is true that people today are under more stress than in the past.</p>
<p>It is evident that + S + V</p>
<p>It is evident that developing artificial intelligence is advantageous.</p>
<p>There is a more persuasive argument that parents should prioritize their children over their careers.</p>
<p>It seems clear that + S + V + for several reasons.</p>
<p>It seems clear that exercise is more important than diet for several reasons.</p>
<p>I object to ~ / I object that + S + V</p>
<p>I object to spending tax money on sponsoring international sporting events.</p>
<p>I am against ~</p>
<p>I am against using the death penalty to prevent crimes.</p>
</section>
<section id="express-advantage-disadvantage" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Express advantage / disadvantage</h1>
<section id="the-main-advantage-disadvantage-is-that-s-v" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-main-advantage-disadvantage-is-that-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> The main advantage / Disadvantage is that + S + v</h2>
<p>The main advantage is that students can learn technical skills.</p>
</section>
<section id="s-has-its-own-advantages-and-disadvantages" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="s-has-its-own-advantages-and-disadvantages"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> S + has its (own) advantages and disadvantages</h2>
<p>Opening borders to immigrants has its advantages and disadvantages.</p>
</section>
<section id="it-seems-advantageous-that-s-v" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="it-seems-advantageous-that-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> It seems advantageous that + S + V</h2>
<p>It seems advantegeous that the firm has many bilingual staff members # Comparison</p>
</section>
<section id="similarly-s-v" class="level2" data-number="2.4">
<h2 data-number="2.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="similarly-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">2.4</span> Similarly, S + V</h2>
<p>Similarly, saving for the future is more important than spending money now.</p>
</section>
<section id="compared-to-s-v" class="level2" data-number="2.5">
<h2 data-number="2.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="compared-to-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">2.5</span> Compared to ~, S + V</h2>
<p>Compared to other living costs, housing expenses are expensive.</p>
</section>
<section id="it-is-preferable-for-to--" class="level2" data-number="2.6">
<h2 data-number="2.6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="it-is-preferable-for-to--"><span class="header-section-number">2.6</span> It is preferable for ~ to -</h2>
<p>It is preferable for governments to invest in education to foster long-term economic development.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="express-contrast" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Express contrast</h1>
<section id="conversely-s-v" class="level2" data-number="3.1">
<h2 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conversely-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> Conversely, S + V</h2>
<p>Conversely, playing sports teaches students the value of teamwork and leadership.</p>
</section>
<section id="on-the-one-hand-s-v" class="level2" data-number="3.2">
<h2 data-number="3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="on-the-one-hand-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">3.2</span> On the one hand, S + V</h2>
<p>On the one hand, parental involvement encourages children to study.</p>
</section>
<section id="on-the-contrary-s-v" class="level2" data-number="3.3">
<h2 data-number="3.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="on-the-contrary-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">3.3</span> On the contrary, S + V</h2>
<p>On the contrary, spending on health care has increased.</p>
</section>
<section id="however-unlike-s-v" class="level2" data-number="3.4">
<h2 data-number="3.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="however-unlike-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">3.4</span> However, unlike ~, S + V</h2>
<p>However, unlike lecture-based classes, project-based learning offers hands-on experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="while-it-is-undeniable-that-s-v-s-v" class="level2" data-number="3.5">
<h2 data-number="3.5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="while-it-is-undeniable-that-s-v-s-v"><span class="header-section-number">3.5</span> While it is undeniable that + S + V, S + V</h2>
<p>While it is undeniable that communities need to stay safe, privacy rights are also important.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="exercises" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Exercises</h1>
<p>There is a more persuasive argument that children should take art classes.</p>
<p>Preserving the rainforests has its own advantages and disadvantages.</p>
<p>Some people think that the high salaries paid to athletes are justified.</p>
<p>The main advantage is that everyone has the same career opportunities.</p>
<p>Similarly, classmates can have a major impact on a student’s education.</p>
<p>I firmly believe that wearing bicycle helmets should be mandatory.</p>
<p>However, unlike most forms of renewable energy, wind power is relatively reliable.</p>
<p>I am against using animals in product testing.</p>
<p>I support the idea that universities should focus on teaching students professional skills.</p>
<p>It seems advantageous that students can provide feedback about their teachers.</p>
<p>Compared to college graduates, the salaries of those without university degrees tend to be low.</p>
<p>On the contrary, having a hobby can inspire students to be more creative.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>listening</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/w-express/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Listening practice - mistake log IELTS Practice Set 19 listening test 1</title>
  <dc:creator>Hung </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/listening-practice-set-19-test-1/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="performance-summary" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Performance summary</h1>
<p>Correct: 38/40</p>
</section>
<section id="recording-1" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Recording 1</h1>
<section id="q3-you-wrote-insects-correct-answer-data" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q3-you-wrote-insects-correct-answer-data"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> <strong>Q3 (you wrote</strong>&nbsp; <strong>INSECTS</strong>&nbsp;<strong>— correct answer</strong>&nbsp;<strong>DATA</strong>*)**</h2>
<p><strong>Where it appears in the recording:</strong> “They also collect and analyse <strong>data</strong> about the things they see.”</p>
<p><strong>Why DATA is correct:</strong> the verbs <em>collect and analyse</em> naturally collocate with <em>data</em> (you collect/record data, not collect insects in this context).</p>
<p><strong>Why you were tempted:</strong> earlier the speaker mentions <em>birds and insects</em> in the list of wildlife, and the science activity also involves plants and insects — it’s easy to grab a nearby noun instead of the object of the verb phrase.</p>
<p><strong>How to avoid it:</strong> focus on the <strong>verb + object</strong> pair. When you hear <em>collect / analyse</em>, expect a <strong>non-count / abstract noun</strong> (data / information / evidence) rather than a concrete species name. Train yourself to listen one or two words after the verb phrase to catch the direct object.</p>
</section>
<section id="q7-discovery---freedom" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q7-discovery---freedom"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Q7 DISCOVERY -&gt; FREEDOM</h2>
<p><strong>Where it appears in the recording:</strong> “I would imagine they get a sense of <strong>freedom</strong> that might not be a normal part of their lives.”</p>
<p><strong>Why FREEDOM is correct:</strong> the exact phrase is <em>a sense of freedom</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Why you were tempted:</strong> the paragraph earlier uses <em>explore and discover</em>, so <em>discovery</em> feels topically relevant and was in your short-term memory.</p>
<p><strong>How to avoid it:</strong> watch for <strong>fixed expressions</strong> such as <em>a sense of </em>___. If the speaker uses <em>a sense of …</em>, the missing word is usually an abstract state (freedom, independence, belonging). Also, when you hear the pattern “I would imagine they get a sense of …”, slow down in your head and expect one concrete abstract noun — not a gerund or verbal noun derived from the previous sentence.</p>
</section>
<section id="q10-leader---leaders" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="q10-leader---leaders"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Q10 LEADER -&gt; LEADERS</h2>
<p><strong>Where it appears in the recording:</strong> “There’s no charge for <strong>leaders</strong> and other adults - as many as you want to bring.”</p>
<p><strong>Why LEADERS (plural) is correct:</strong> the phrase <em>as many as you want</em> makes clear the plural; the recording explicitly uses <em>leaders</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Why you were tempted:</strong> hearing the single word <em>leader</em> in isolation (or reading the question fragment quickly) can look plausible, but it fails the grammar/number test.</p>
<p><strong>How to avoid it:</strong> check <strong>number signals</strong> in the sentence (as many / each / every / a / the). If the context allows more than one, answer must be plural. For summary completion always re-read the sentence mentally with your candidate word: does it fit grammatically?</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="quick-practice-drills-2-minutes" class="level2" data-number="2.4">
<h2 data-number="2.4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quick-practice-drills-2-minutes"><span class="header-section-number">2.4</span> <strong>Quick practice drills (2 minutes)</strong></h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Hear the verb <strong>“collect and analyse”</strong> → supply the noun that collocates (answer: <strong>data</strong>).</p></li>
<li><p>Hear the phrase <strong>“a sense of …”</strong> → think of abstract nouns that fit (freedom, pride, belonging). Practice choosing the one that fits the passage meaning.</p></li>
<li><p>Hear <strong>“as many as …”</strong> or <strong>“each”</strong> → force yourself to write plural vs singular appropriately (leaders ≠ leader</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Look again at the original sentence from the recording:</p>
<p><em>“There’s no charge for</em> <strong><em>leaders</em></strong> <em>and other</em> <strong><em>adults</em></strong> <em>— as many as you want to bring.”</em></p>
<ul>
<li><p>The word <strong>adults</strong> is plural, and it’s paired with <strong>leaders</strong> in the same structure.</p></li>
<li><p>In English, when two nouns are linked with <strong>and</strong> in a parallel list, they normally match in number and form.</p></li>
<li><p>If it were singular, the sentence would be odd: <em>“no charge for leader and other adults”</em> — imbalance.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>So yes, <strong>ADULTS</strong> works as a <strong>plural signal</strong> for the missing word.</p>
<section id="strategy-tip" class="level3" data-number="2.4.1">
<h3 data-number="2.4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strategy-tip"><span class="header-section-number">2.4.1</span> <strong>Strategy tip:</strong></h3>
<p>When filling blanks in IELTS <strong>sentence completion</strong>, always:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Look <strong>left and right</strong> of the blank for number cues (plural nouns, “as many as,” “other,” “these”).</p></li>
<li><p>Match your word form to those cues — IELTS often plants the singular/plural trap.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="recording-2" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Recording 2</h1>
</section>
<section id="recording-3" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Recording 3</h1>
</section>
<section id="recording-4" class="level1" data-number="5">
<h1 data-number="5"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Recording 4</h1>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>english</category>
  <category>listening</category>
  <guid>https://kimhungbui.github.io/english/listening-practice-set-19-test-1/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
